<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-13T21:28:23+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 497: Judgement Cast!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/11/day-497-judgement-cast/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 497: Judgement Cast!"/><published>2025-02-12T02:04:06+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T02:04:06+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/11/day-497-judgement-cast</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/11/day-497-judgement-cast/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I just finished judging my first round of writing battle submissions and it was a lot of fun. The stories were better than I was expecting and I thought both participants did a great job. I can't mention any specifics, but the genre I was judging for was 'aliens.' I love aliens in fiction and the responses were both creative and fun so I couldn't really ask for more. The feedback system on the website is really straightforward and I can't wait to read my own when the round is finished. I'm sure it'll be helpful. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I read my submission back and on a second look, I don't think it's very good. The pacing is kinda off and the subject matter is not my usual cup of tea, but I was feeling adventurous while writing. Hopefully its clunkiness isn't held against me too badly. That three day time limit is brutal! I don't think I'll win, but I'm sure to get some good feedback.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I just finished judging my first round of writing battle submissions and it was a lot of fun. The stories were better than I was expecting and I thought both participants did a great job. I can't mention any specifics, but the genre I was judging for was 'aliens.' I love aliens in fiction and the responses were both creative and fun so I couldn't really ask for more. The feedback system on the website is really straightforward and I can't wait to read my own when the round is finished. I'm sure it'll be helpful. I read my submission back and on a second look, I don't think it's very good. The pacing is kinda off and the subject matter is not my usual cup of tea, but I was feeling adventurous while writing. Hopefully its clunkiness isn't held against me too badly. That three day time limit is brutal! I don't think I'll win, but I'm sure to get some good feedback. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 496: Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/10/day-496-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 496: Progress Update"/><published>2025-02-11T04:03:51+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T04:03:51+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/10/day-496-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/10/day-496-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I'm up late on a Monday again. Yesterday I submitted to the latest writing battle and I think I used up a lot of my brain power. Today I haven't been able to write much of anything. Weird how it comes and goes.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think I'm going to spend some more time on the blog, and start working on a new book haul. It's been a while since I've had one, but I've been trying not to break the bank lately so there's been good reason. My next book haul is going to focus on more modern titles, but this time I'm going to look for some good ones dang it. My last experiment with contemporary books was not very good, with the exception of discovering Abraham Verghese, who blew everybody else I read out of the water. I want to find some modern sci-fi titles to read, maybe some fantasy too. It'll be like getting back to my roots. Some of the first books I remember reading were sci-fi/fantasy published almost the same year I read them. Should be fun!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm up late on a Monday again. Yesterday I submitted to the latest writing battle and I think I used up a lot of my brain power. Today I haven't been able to write much of anything. Weird how it comes and goes. I think I'm going to spend some more time on the blog, and start working on a new book haul. It's been a while since I've had one, but I've been trying not to break the bank lately so there's been good reason. My next book haul is going to focus on more modern titles, but this time I'm going to look for some good ones dang it. My last experiment with contemporary books was not very good, with the exception of discovering Abraham Verghese, who blew everybody else I read out of the water. I want to find some modern sci-fi titles to read, maybe some fantasy too. It'll be like getting back to my roots. Some of the first books I remember reading were sci-fi/fantasy published almost the same year I read them. Should be fun! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 495: Writing Battle Day 2</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/07/day-295-writing-battle-day-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 495: Writing Battle Day 2"/><published>2025-02-08T03:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-08T03:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/07/day-495-writing-battle-day-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/07/day-295-writing-battle-day-2/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Well I was planning on using all my resources this time around, but the first prompt I got was Revenge - Leader - Suitcase, and that seems like the juiciest prompt I'm liable to get. I'm almost disappointed I didn't get to use my mulligans. This prompt has actually proved a different problem, in that I'm not sure how to choose between the many options the prompt presents. I've been blindsided and now I'm not sure how to proceed with only two days left to figure it out!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well I was planning on using all my resources this time around, but the first prompt I got was Revenge - Leader - Suitcase, and that seems like the juiciest prompt I'm liable to get. I'm almost disappointed I didn't get to use my mulligans. This prompt has actually proved a different problem, in that I'm not sure how to choose between the many options the prompt presents. I've been blindsided and now I'm not sure how to proceed with only two days left to figure it out! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 294: The Writing Battle Starts Soon</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/06/day-294-the-writing-battle-starts-soon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 294: The Writing Battle Starts Soon"/><published>2025-02-07T02:38:38+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-07T02:38:38+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/06/day-494-the-writing-battle-starts-soon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/06/day-294-the-writing-battle-starts-soon/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The writing battle starts right after this post! <a href="https://writingbattle.com/battle">You can still join in right here up until the second day of the competition.</a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm excited to see what prompt I get this time. Something I didn't realize until reviewing the rules again today is that this competition is actually peer judged, meaning I'll have to read through several of my competitor's short stories to rank them against one another. I'm sure to read some good stuff over the next couple of weeks! I'm hoping that as the rounds go on, the decisions will get harder and harder as I read better and better stories. In the end, it better be a real nail biter. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The writing battle starts right after this post! You can still join in right here up until the second day of the competition. I'm excited to see what prompt I get this time. Something I didn't realize until reviewing the rules again today is that this competition is actually peer judged, meaning I'll have to read through several of my competitor's short stories to rank them against one another. I'm sure to read some good stuff over the next couple of weeks! I'm hoping that as the rounds go on, the decisions will get harder and harder as I read better and better stories. In the end, it better be a real nail biter. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 493: Blog Migration Continues</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/05/day-493-blog-migration-continues/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 493: Blog Migration Continues"/><published>2025-02-06T01:55:52+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T01:55:52+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/05/day-493-blog-migration-continues</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/05/day-493-blog-migration-continues/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Today I've been puzzling over the best way to import images from WordPress to my new blog. After much thought, I think the real answer is 'only keep one blog, stupid,' but I'm hard headed and I need to keep this one at least until I can get the email service set up. The process of getting images over is still painful though, so I think I may avoid pictures for the next few days. The best part of the new blog is how customizable each blog post is since I can include anything I want using html and markdown, but that's also the problem. I have to put everything in myself if I want it to work. I can't seem to figure out how to export all the photos from this site easily so I end up having to fill in each and every photo manually by downloading them one at a time. It's about as far from ideal as I can get. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The email system should be more straightforward. Once it's set up, I should just be able to copy a list over from my current subscribers and continue sending out emails seamlessly. I'll also add a button to sign up on the blog once I get it going for new readers. After that, I should be ready to migrate over completely and host the blog from there then on out.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today I've been puzzling over the best way to import images from WordPress to my new blog. After much thought, I think the real answer is 'only keep one blog, stupid,' but I'm hard headed and I need to keep this one at least until I can get the email service set up. The process of getting images over is still painful though, so I think I may avoid pictures for the next few days. The best part of the new blog is how customizable each blog post is since I can include anything I want using html and markdown, but that's also the problem. I have to put everything in myself if I want it to work. I can't seem to figure out how to export all the photos from this site easily so I end up having to fill in each and every photo manually by downloading them one at a time. It's about as far from ideal as I can get. The email system should be more straightforward. Once it's set up, I should just be able to copy a list over from my current subscribers and continue sending out emails seamlessly. I'll also add a button to sign up on the blog once I get it going for new readers. After that, I should be ready to migrate over completely and host the blog from there then on out. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 492: Writing Battle 2!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/04/day-492-writing-battle-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 492: Writing Battle 2!"/><published>2025-02-05T03:10:46+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-05T03:10:46+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/04/day-492-writing-battle-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/04/day-492-writing-battle-2/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I've got the blog set up to tinker away with, so now my focus is going to be on the next <a href="https://writingbattle.com/battle">writing battle competition</a>. I've got two days until it starts, and now that I know what I'm in for I think I'll do better. This time I have just three days to write a 1000 word short story. I won't see my prompt until it begins, when I'll draw three cards from a deck to randomize my options. I get five mulligans on the character and object/subject cards, but only one mulligan for the genre card. My plan is to go through mulligans as fast as I can to land on a good prompt more quickly. The last story could have used a day more to bake, but I had spent a lot of time assessing which prompt I wanted to use. This time, I'll aim to settle on a prompt within the first hour or so. Last time I was picky and analytical, so instead I'm just going to go by feel and first impressions. If something strikes me I'll take it, otherwise I'll just keep redrawing until I'm out. I also barely used my redraws last time since I got such a solid prompt on my first redraw but I expect it's often more difficult to get a good prompt. I guess I'll find out.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've got the blog set up to tinker away with, so now my focus is going to be on the next writing battle competition. I've got two days until it starts, and now that I know what I'm in for I think I'll do better. This time I have just three days to write a 1000 word short story. I won't see my prompt until it begins, when I'll draw three cards from a deck to randomize my options. I get five mulligans on the character and object/subject cards, but only one mulligan for the genre card. My plan is to go through mulligans as fast as I can to land on a good prompt more quickly. The last story could have used a day more to bake, but I had spent a lot of time assessing which prompt I wanted to use. This time, I'll aim to settle on a prompt within the first hour or so. Last time I was picky and analytical, so instead I'm just going to go by feel and first impressions. If something strikes me I'll take it, otherwise I'll just keep redrawing until I'm out. I also barely used my redraws last time since I got such a solid prompt on my first redraw but I expect it's often more difficult to get a good prompt. I guess I'll find out. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 491: My New Blog Site is Ready!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/03/day-491-my-new-blog-site-is-ready/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 491: My New Blog Site is Ready!"/><published>2025-02-03T20:27:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T20:27:16+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/03/day-491-my-new-blog-site-is-ready</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/03/day-491-my-new-blog-site-is-ready/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Great new everyone! I've got my new blog site up and running. It's got a similar look to this blog on WordPress, but several nice features that put it in a league above the current blog. For starters, you can see all of my posts, regardless of how long ago they were posted. You can search through my posts for specific tags and topics too, for example, if you wanted to read all my reviews just search for 'review' and all the book, movie, and TV reviews I've done over the last couple years will show up. The new blog also has a publications page where you can find links to all my published works (that will hopefully grow over time), a CV page where you can check out my writing resume, and a button that'll let you send me an email on the bottom of the about page. There's even a little button that'll let you switch from a dark theme to a light theme in the upper right corner! All these quality of life features make me really happy, since none of them exist in the current blog. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>There are a few missing pieces though, like how there is currently no way to comment on my posts. This is a big issue that I'm still working toward fixing. The issue with comments is that they actually open up all sorts of security concerns that might let a bad actor hack into my website. There's no sensitive data on there, but still. It'd be awkward to wake up and find out someone has posted a bunch of penises or something on my personal blog. Similarly, you can't sign up for a newsletter yet, but I'm working on that too. The template I used has integrated support for something called loops, which I haven't messed with yet. Apparently it'll let me send out email notifications with ease. That's what I'm going to look into next. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>There are some other little things too, like the second publication won't display the bibliography attached even though the first one will (maddening, I swear I've been trying to figure this one out since I started), and also the suggested reading footer always displays random articles that have nothing to do with my page. Finally several posts are missing because they have links to images that no longer work. Those are smaller issues that I'll fix over time. Right now I'm just glad to have the blog in a functional state. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Over the next couple of months I'll continue to make adjustments to the blog, and eventually I'll stop using this Wordpress site altogether. For now, I'll be posting on both sites. This post won't be included because linking the site to itself would be weird. Friday's post also won't be there cause it doesn't exist. I was exhausted after being sick all week and couldn't budge from my place on the bed. Sorry! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><a href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/">You can check out the new blog right here!</a> Let me know what you think.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="blogging"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="wordpress"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Great new everyone! I've got my new blog site up and running. It's got a similar look to this blog on WordPress, but several nice features that put it in a league above the current blog. For starters, you can see all of my posts, regardless of how long ago they were posted. You can search through my posts for specific tags and topics too, for example, if you wanted to read all my reviews just search for 'review' and all the book, movie, and TV reviews I've done over the last couple years will show up. The new blog also has a publications page where you can find links to all my published works (that will hopefully grow over time), a CV page where you can check out my writing resume, and a button that'll let you send me an email on the bottom of the about page. There's even a little button that'll let you switch from a dark theme to a light theme in the upper right corner! All these quality of life features make me really happy, since none of them exist in the current blog. There are a few missing pieces though, like how there is currently no way to comment on my posts. This is a big issue that I'm still working toward fixing. The issue with comments is that they actually open up all sorts of security concerns that might let a bad actor hack into my website. There's no sensitive data on there, but still. It'd be awkward to wake up and find out someone has posted a bunch of penises or something on my personal blog. Similarly, you can't sign up for a newsletter yet, but I'm working on that too. The template I used has integrated support for something called loops, which I haven't messed with yet. Apparently it'll let me send out email notifications with ease. That's what I'm going to look into next. There are some other little things too, like the second publication won't display the bibliography attached even though the first one will (maddening, I swear I've been trying to figure this one out since I started), and also the suggested reading footer always displays random articles that have nothing to do with my page. Finally several posts are missing because they have links to images that no longer work. Those are smaller issues that I'll fix over time. Right now I'm just glad to have the blog in a functional state. Over the next couple of months I'll continue to make adjustments to the blog, and eventually I'll stop using this Wordpress site altogether. For now, I'll be posting on both sites. This post won't be included because linking the site to itself would be weird. Friday's post also won't be there cause it doesn't exist. I was exhausted after being sick all week and couldn't budge from my place on the bed. Sorry! You can check out the new blog right here! Let me know what you think. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 489: Third Thumb</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 489: Third Thumb"/><published>2025-01-31T02:49:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T02:49:11+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p><a href="https://www.daniclodedesign.com/thethirdthumb">I found something neat today and I thought I'd share. </a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I've always thought it would be cool to have a third thumb. I don't know why. It's probably not very useful if I'm being honest. Like what can you really do with an extra thumb? Unscrew a bottle cap with one hand? Other than that I can't really think of anything. Stupid tricks like that are still enough to make me want one though. Maybe if I'm lucky these things will catch on and I can find one for cheap!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I found something neat today and I thought I'd share. I've always thought it would be cool to have a third thumb. I don't know why. It's probably not very useful if I'm being honest. Like what can you really do with an extra thumb? Unscrew a bottle cap with one hand? Other than that I can't really think of anything. Stupid tricks like that are still enough to make me want one though. Maybe if I'm lucky these things will catch on and I can find one for cheap! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 488: Almost Missed One!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 488: Almost Missed One!"/><published>2025-01-30T03:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-30T03:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>So I pretty much took the day off on account of my sore throat. It's been pretty bad, but thankfully getting better and not worse. I took some cold medicine with plans to watch some TV and then get some work done ... before passing right out and getting nothing done at all. At least I woke up to get the blog done, but it'll be a shallow one.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think I'm going to take tomorrow off too. I've been sleeping poorly for the past few days and I'm not sure my brain can handle much more restless nights. I'll probably just try to get some sleep while I can.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So I pretty much took the day off on account of my sore throat. It's been pretty bad, but thankfully getting better and not worse. I took some cold medicine with plans to watch some TV and then get some work done ... before passing right out and getting nothing done at all. At least I woke up to get the blog done, but it'll be a shallow one. I think I'm going to take tomorrow off too. I've been sleeping poorly for the past few days and I'm not sure my brain can handle much more restless nights. I'll probably just try to get some sleep while I can. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 487: Locking the Door</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 487: Locking the Door"/><published>2025-01-29T02:18:57+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-29T02:18:57+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I was reminded today of a writing technique I like, sometimes referred to as 'locking the door.' The idea is to take a straightforward conflict and liven things up by throwing a spanner in the works, usually something simpler than the overall conflict that nevertheless adds a lot of suspense. For example ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he pushes through the front door and slams it behind him. <em>The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em></em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It's the most basic story I can come up with. Characters are introduced, there's a clear conflict, the stakes rise a little, and then it's resolved. But it feels really shallow, almost too easy, right? Blink, and you'll miss the whole thing. Generally in fiction (and often in life) problems aren't so easily solved, even simple things. It can be endlessly frustrating when you know something should be pretty straightforward only to encounter one confounding issue after the next. Anybody who has worked on a car or done some DIY knows the pain of a stuck bolt, especially when that's the one bolt between you and the finish line. The flip side to this is that watching someone overcome adversity is gratifying. We tend to love seeing emotional moments after huge problems are resolved, but the issue with these big problems is that they can only be so big on paper. They're chock full of little obstacles that compound together, but nobody wants to read a dissertation about every little thing that goes wrong just to feel something when a character achieves their goals. As ever, the best way to make something feel massive is to imply its size with a pertinent issue. A locked door, in this case. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps closer than ever. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and falls through the door. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>This has a little more tension to it. By drawing the conflict out it seems to escalate, even though one might imagine the bear as equally close in the first and second versions. I don't cover every beat of the man's heart, or the slipperiness of the grass, or the rusty lock, but you get the picture. One pertinent complication is often enough to make the conflict a lot more suspenseful. It can be taken further if you want though. I don't think the solution is to give the man another issue since he has his own already, but there are two characters here. What if the bear has its own stumbling block to overcome?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps behind him. He hears a deep growl of pain and spares a terrified glance over his shoulder. The bear has been caught up in the rose bushes in his garden, tangled as if by barbed wire. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and ... it still won't open! The bear pulls itself out of the thorny bramble and comes roaring forward again, angrier than ever. The man steps back, braces himself, and kicks the door in with a defiant shout. He falls inside and throws himself against the ruined door to brace it. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. After holding it off for what feels like forever, the bear gets bored. A biker passes by on the road beyond and it gets distracted. The man watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em> </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Notice that the two locked doors have compounded. This version is much longer than the others. Every additional problem adds more complexity than the last, more baggage for the writer to handle in the end. Now the man has to solve his locked door, and the bear has to extract itself from the brambles. It also gives me free reign to give the man a harder time too. The story might feel a little sparse without it. The conflict has to keep escalating until it doesn't, and I can't have the protagonist being outdone, so I had him put in some extra effort for more payoff. Kicking down the door is a lot more dramatic than just opening the door, and it paints the man as ultimately more powerful than than the bear. Is that a little ridiculous? Sure. But hey, it's fiction. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I couldn't just wind up with one sentence of the bear shuffling off either. I had to give a little breathing room for the resolution to settle in. The higher the tension, the longer it takes to fall. This story really ought to have some paragraph breaks too. It looks a little bloated, but it's probably fine. I hope it gets my point across about locking the door.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="bears"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="short story"/><category term="tips"/><category term="writing"/><category term="writing-tips"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was reminded today of a writing technique I like, sometimes referred to as 'locking the door.' The idea is to take a straightforward conflict and liven things up by throwing a spanner in the works, usually something simpler than the overall conflict that nevertheless adds a lot of suspense. For example ... A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he pushes through the front door and slams it behind him. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. It's the most basic story I can come up with. Characters are introduced, there's a clear conflict, the stakes rise a little, and then it's resolved. But it feels really shallow, almost too easy, right? Blink, and you'll miss the whole thing. Generally in fiction (and often in life) problems aren't so easily solved, even simple things. It can be endlessly frustrating when you know something should be pretty straightforward only to encounter one confounding issue after the next. Anybody who has worked on a car or done some DIY knows the pain of a stuck bolt, especially when that's the one bolt between you and the finish line. The flip side to this is that watching someone overcome adversity is gratifying. We tend to love seeing emotional moments after huge problems are resolved, but the issue with these big problems is that they can only be so big on paper. They're chock full of little obstacles that compound together, but nobody wants to read a dissertation about every little thing that goes wrong just to feel something when a character achieves their goals. As ever, the best way to make something feel massive is to imply its size with a pertinent issue. A locked door, in this case. A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps closer than ever. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and falls through the door. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. This has a little more tension to it. By drawing the conflict out it seems to escalate, even though one might imagine the bear as equally close in the first and second versions. I don't cover every beat of the man's heart, or the slipperiness of the grass, or the rusty lock, but you get the picture. One pertinent complication is often enough to make the conflict a lot more suspenseful. It can be taken further if you want though. I don't think the solution is to give the man another issue since he has his own already, but there are two characters here. What if the bear has its own stumbling block to overcome? A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps behind him. He hears a deep growl of pain and spares a terrified glance over his shoulder. The bear has been caught up in the rose bushes in his garden, tangled as if by barbed wire. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and ... it still won't open! The bear pulls itself out of the thorny bramble and comes roaring forward again, angrier than ever. The man steps back, braces himself, and kicks the door in with a defiant shout. He falls inside and throws himself against the ruined door to brace it. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. After holding it off for what feels like forever, the bear gets bored. A biker passes by on the road beyond and it gets distracted. The man watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. Notice that the two locked doors have compounded. This version is much longer than the others. Every additional problem adds more complexity than the last, more baggage for the writer to handle in the end. Now the man has to solve his locked door, and the bear has to extract itself from the brambles. It also gives me free reign to give the man a harder time too. The story might feel a little sparse without it. The conflict has to keep escalating until it doesn't, and I can't have the protagonist being outdone, so I had him put in some extra effort for more payoff. Kicking down the door is a lot more dramatic than just opening the door, and it paints the man as ultimately more powerful than than the bear. Is that a little ridiculous? Sure. But hey, it's fiction. I couldn't just wind up with one sentence of the bear shuffling off either. I had to give a little breathing room for the resolution to settle in. The higher the tension, the longer it takes to fall. This story really ought to have some paragraph breaks too. It looks a little bloated, but it's probably fine. I hope it gets my point across about locking the door. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>