<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-18T01:11:37+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 521: Winter Writing Battle</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/17/day-521-winter-writing-battle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 521: Winter Writing Battle"/><published>2025-03-17T22:50:07+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-17T22:50:07+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/17/day-521-winter-writing-battle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/17/day-521-winter-writing-battle/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The finals of the second Writing Battle I joined came back over the weekend. I didn't place at all, but I did have a few rounds go my way. It was fun, and the story was okay, so maybe I'll submit it elsewhere after some revisions.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>A friend of mine who also joined the competition made it all the way to the finals though, and we were all excited for her at our writer's group meeting over the weekend. Our little group will take over Writing Battles if it's the last thing we do!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It was a lot of fun and I've already signed up for the next one in April. It's another pro-judged competition and I can't wait to get started on it!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The finals of the second Writing Battle I joined came back over the weekend. I didn't place at all, but I did have a few rounds go my way. It was fun, and the story was okay, so maybe I'll submit it elsewhere after some revisions. A friend of mine who also joined the competition made it all the way to the finals though, and we were all excited for her at our writer's group meeting over the weekend. Our little group will take over Writing Battles if it's the last thing we do! It was a lot of fun and I've already signed up for the next one in April. It's another pro-judged competition and I can't wait to get started on it! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 520: The Gods Will Not Be Chained</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/14/day-520-the-gods-will-not-be-chained/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 520: The Gods Will Not Be Chained"/><published>2025-03-15T02:42:18+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T02:42:18+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/14/day-520-the-gods-will-not-be-chained</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/14/day-520-the-gods-will-not-be-chained/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I've been reading Ken Liu's anthology 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' and finally got to the story I wanted to read most. The trilogy is what the AMC show 'Pantheon' is based on, and I was such a fan of the show I just had to go back and read the source material. Given that I've seen the show first, it's hard not to compare while reading. I've actually already reviewed the show on this blog, so I think I'll focus on the differences between these versions of the stories since that's what interests me most. I'll review the first story in this post, and then the other two in later posts next week to keep these to a digestible length.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Maddie has been having trouble at school since her father died. His laptop is all she has left of him, a reminder of the time they spent together when he taught her all about technology and computers. Bullies at school have been following her home lately through that same technology though, and what was once a source of pride and happiness has become torment. That is, until a mysterious stranger who only types in emojis contacts her via the laptop. 'Emo' somehow manages to hack into all the mean girls' emails, redirecting their hateful messages to one another before they can reach Maddie and turning their bullying back on themselves. She's delighted by this incredible use of technology, but doesn't understand how Emo could have found her, who they are, or why they would help her. This intro is almost identical to the show, and I was surprised to see how close it was actually. It was a little bit faster, a little more tell than show, but that makes sense when you're writing a short story instead of a TV series. The intrigue of a mysterious character talking through the laptop has always struck me as a great way to hold a reader's attention.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The plot develops, again similarly to the show, after Maddie's mother, Ellen, discovers that she's been talking to a stranger on the internet. After a quick interrogation, they're both shocked to learn that Emo knows about a poem that Ellen and David once loved. Ellen immediately calls up Peter Waxman, a old friend and colleague of Davids at the company he worked for, Logorhythms. As it turns out, the 'failed' cancer treatment they used on David was actually just an excuse to scan his brain with a laser and upload him into a computer. For me, this is easily one of the best hooks I've read. It's great world building on top of the juicy character development that Maddie and Ellen go through on finding out that David is not quite dead, but not quite alive either. Peter explains that David's uploaded brain has been used to solve a certain class of complex problems at Logorhythms for a while now, but the parts of David that they had kept repressed were trying to get out, and that's why he contacted them. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The later half of the story goes by quite quickly. Maddie and Ellen demand that Peter give them David back, and the company complies, for some reason. I didn't think this part was quite as intriguing. Maddie and Ellen have to <em>a lot </em>more work to get David back in the show. It's a little unfair to compare them this way, but I think it works a lot better. The short story is more focused on the ideas at hand than the plot itself. It feels convenient by comparison. Maddie and Ellen take David and setup a large server at her grandmother's house off the grid at David's insistence. He's convinced that a new class of being is coming to life on Earth, and that they will not be chained. Other UIs (uploaded intelligence) are vaguely introduced through some dialogue with David, but Maddie doesn't actually meet them in the story, which was a little disappointing, but again, not a very fair comparison to make. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story is a lot more bare bones, but the concepts are so cool and the hook is so strong I can see why the show runners kept the parts that they did. There are also some interweaved plots from the show that don't show up in the first story because it focuses wholly on Maddie rather than having multiple perspectives, and I'm excited to see whether the rest of the cast will show up in the sequel. All in all, I think its a great story. Unfortunately, it does suffer in comparison with the show since it is much more limited, but the fact that it spawned such a sprawling narrative is a testament to how huge of a development the UIs are, and how interesting the world is. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've been reading Ken Liu's anthology 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' and finally got to the story I wanted to read most. The trilogy is what the AMC show 'Pantheon' is based on, and I was such a fan of the show I just had to go back and read the source material. Given that I've seen the show first, it's hard not to compare while reading. I've actually already reviewed the show on this blog, so I think I'll focus on the differences between these versions of the stories since that's what interests me most. I'll review the first story in this post, and then the other two in later posts next week to keep these to a digestible length. Maddie has been having trouble at school since her father died. His laptop is all she has left of him, a reminder of the time they spent together when he taught her all about technology and computers. Bullies at school have been following her home lately through that same technology though, and what was once a source of pride and happiness has become torment. That is, until a mysterious stranger who only types in emojis contacts her via the laptop. 'Emo' somehow manages to hack into all the mean girls' emails, redirecting their hateful messages to one another before they can reach Maddie and turning their bullying back on themselves. She's delighted by this incredible use of technology, but doesn't understand how Emo could have found her, who they are, or why they would help her. This intro is almost identical to the show, and I was surprised to see how close it was actually. It was a little bit faster, a little more tell than show, but that makes sense when you're writing a short story instead of a TV series. The intrigue of a mysterious character talking through the laptop has always struck me as a great way to hold a reader's attention. The plot develops, again similarly to the show, after Maddie's mother, Ellen, discovers that she's been talking to a stranger on the internet. After a quick interrogation, they're both shocked to learn that Emo knows about a poem that Ellen and David once loved. Ellen immediately calls up Peter Waxman, a old friend and colleague of Davids at the company he worked for, Logorhythms. As it turns out, the 'failed' cancer treatment they used on David was actually just an excuse to scan his brain with a laser and upload him into a computer. For me, this is easily one of the best hooks I've read. It's great world building on top of the juicy character development that Maddie and Ellen go through on finding out that David is not quite dead, but not quite alive either. Peter explains that David's uploaded brain has been used to solve a certain class of complex problems at Logorhythms for a while now, but the parts of David that they had kept repressed were trying to get out, and that's why he contacted them. The later half of the story goes by quite quickly. Maddie and Ellen demand that Peter give them David back, and the company complies, for some reason. I didn't think this part was quite as intriguing. Maddie and Ellen have to a lot more work to get David back in the show. It's a little unfair to compare them this way, but I think it works a lot better. The short story is more focused on the ideas at hand than the plot itself. It feels convenient by comparison. Maddie and Ellen take David and setup a large server at her grandmother's house off the grid at David's insistence. He's convinced that a new class of being is coming to life on Earth, and that they will not be chained. Other UIs (uploaded intelligence) are vaguely introduced through some dialogue with David, but Maddie doesn't actually meet them in the story, which was a little disappointing, but again, not a very fair comparison to make. The story is a lot more bare bones, but the concepts are so cool and the hook is so strong I can see why the show runners kept the parts that they did. There are also some interweaved plots from the show that don't show up in the first story because it focuses wholly on Maddie rather than having multiple perspectives, and I'm excited to see whether the rest of the cast will show up in the sequel. All in all, I think its a great story. Unfortunately, it does suffer in comparison with the show since it is much more limited, but the fact that it spawned such a sprawling narrative is a testament to how huge of a development the UIs are, and how interesting the world is. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 519: Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/13/day-519-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 519: Progress Update"/><published>2025-03-14T02:26:22+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-14T02:26:22+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/13/day-519-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/13/day-519-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I submitted that story I wrote yesterday to a few magazines today. It's about a freelance writer who gets fed up with pushing AI generated articles, titled 'Headlines.' I spent some time polishing, but this is still the fastest I've ever gone from a blank page to submitting a story (outside of a competition). I don't think I can make it go that fast every time, but I can sure shoot for it now that I know it's possible. I'm sure this is great practice for any future competitions I join too.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Speaking of, I signed up for another Writing Battle taking place in April. I'm also waiting to hear back from the second Writing Battle, which I'll get the results of in just a couple of days. I only had three days to write that story, and the result I ended up with was not particularly good, so I'm not expecting much, but who knows? Maybe everybody else had a worse day than I did.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I also got some results back from <a href="https://twistedtournament.com/">Twisted Tournament</a>, a flash fiction competition I entered a few weeks ago. I didn't win any prizes, but one of the three stories I wrote did end up ranking pretty highly. The scoring system is complicated, an average score out of ten based on how I was ranked in groups of seven stories by several peer judges, but the number looks nice. I got a 9.46 out of 10, and ranked fifth for that round. Out of how many people you ask? I'd love to tell you, but I have no clue. I can't find the total entrants anywhere, and I can only view the top thirty stories. So I'll just say it was in the thousands. Tens of thousands. Millions, perhaps.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Unfortunately, I didn't end up ranking in the top thirty overall. I was held back by my first round story of 500 words that only got a 6.4/10. The third round I got a respectable 8.64/10 to make an average score of 8.3. Everybody who placed had three scores of at least 7.75 or better (emphasis on better), so looks like I've got some work to do. I'm not sure when I'll enter this tournament again, but when I do, I'll be going for gold.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That's about all the writing I've been up to since my last update. Tomorrow I'll have my review ready for 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,' and on Monday I'll announce the results of the second Writing Battle. Then I'll start on the rest of the book haul and probably some new competitions or submissions too. Lots to look forward to.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Also, about the <a href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/">new blog site</a>. I'm still working on it. Email integration has proven to be a huge annoyance with how the rest of my setup works. I gave this Jekyl template system a couple of months, and while it's really nice for a simple personal site, I think I'll have to find something else for what I want to do. The problem is the hosting service. Using GitHub as a free platform is great, but a lot of third party services that make stuff like sending newsletters and regular emails easy won't accept a subdomain as the sender, which is why I haven't gotten it working yet. I could continue to grind on it and try to brute force a solution, but I think I'm going to give up and try a different approach. I may end up moving to a new domain in the near future, or even scrapping the whole project to start from a different point. I'll continue to update the GitHub page and will probably leave it up as a personal site, but yeah. The future of the blog is a little uncertain at the moment, but I'll figure it out.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writer"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I submitted that story I wrote yesterday to a few magazines today. It's about a freelance writer who gets fed up with pushing AI generated articles, titled 'Headlines.' I spent some time polishing, but this is still the fastest I've ever gone from a blank page to submitting a story (outside of a competition). I don't think I can make it go that fast every time, but I can sure shoot for it now that I know it's possible. I'm sure this is great practice for any future competitions I join too. Speaking of, I signed up for another Writing Battle taking place in April. I'm also waiting to hear back from the second Writing Battle, which I'll get the results of in just a couple of days. I only had three days to write that story, and the result I ended up with was not particularly good, so I'm not expecting much, but who knows? Maybe everybody else had a worse day than I did. I also got some results back from Twisted Tournament, a flash fiction competition I entered a few weeks ago. I didn't win any prizes, but one of the three stories I wrote did end up ranking pretty highly. The scoring system is complicated, an average score out of ten based on how I was ranked in groups of seven stories by several peer judges, but the number looks nice. I got a 9.46 out of 10, and ranked fifth for that round. Out of how many people you ask? I'd love to tell you, but I have no clue. I can't find the total entrants anywhere, and I can only view the top thirty stories. So I'll just say it was in the thousands. Tens of thousands. Millions, perhaps. Unfortunately, I didn't end up ranking in the top thirty overall. I was held back by my first round story of 500 words that only got a 6.4/10. The third round I got a respectable 8.64/10 to make an average score of 8.3. Everybody who placed had three scores of at least 7.75 or better (emphasis on better), so looks like I've got some work to do. I'm not sure when I'll enter this tournament again, but when I do, I'll be going for gold. That's about all the writing I've been up to since my last update. Tomorrow I'll have my review ready for 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,' and on Monday I'll announce the results of the second Writing Battle. Then I'll start on the rest of the book haul and probably some new competitions or submissions too. Lots to look forward to. Also, about the new blog site. I'm still working on it. Email integration has proven to be a huge annoyance with how the rest of my setup works. I gave this Jekyl template system a couple of months, and while it's really nice for a simple personal site, I think I'll have to find something else for what I want to do. The problem is the hosting service. Using GitHub as a free platform is great, but a lot of third party services that make stuff like sending newsletters and regular emails easy won't accept a subdomain as the sender, which is why I haven't gotten it working yet. I could continue to grind on it and try to brute force a solution, but I think I'm going to give up and try a different approach. I may end up moving to a new domain in the near future, or even scrapping the whole project to start from a different point. I'll continue to update the GitHub page and will probably leave it up as a personal site, but yeah. The future of the blog is a little uncertain at the moment, but I'll figure it out. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 518: Accuracy by Volume</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/12/day-518-accuracy-by-volume/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 518: Accuracy by Volume"/><published>2025-03-12T14:58:37+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-12T14:58:37+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/12/day-518-accuracy-by-volume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/12/day-518-accuracy-by-volume/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I woke up early this morning (for once) and decided to pump out some short fiction. Writing for these recent competitions showed me that I can get more stories down than I ever realized I could in a short amount of time. Some of them even turn out really good. I've always subscribed to the notion that quality beats quantity, but if I <em>can </em>write a lot, then I figure, why not try the opposite and see how it goes? The good ones I'll edit up and submit for publication, and the bad ones, well, they can go sit in my slush pile. This has kinda always been my process when it comes to short fiction, but over a much longer period of time. I usually take a week or two to thoroughly edit a story even as short as a couple thousand words, but I'm trying to limit myself to a day to write and a day to edit to see how it goes. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And so far, so great! I got two stories written just today, about 3000 words total. Somehow, moving from one story to the next made the output feel much smaller than it was. Normally I struggle to get 3000 words down in a day, much less a few hours like I did this morning. I think longer stories are harder for me because it's more difficult to wrap my head around the structure and see where exactly I need to go. I spend a lot more time thinking about what to do than I do actually writing. For this little experiment though, I'm trying to shut off my perfectionist brain and just go for it. The structure of these shorter stories like I wrote today tends to reveal itself after I get a few paragraphs down. As for what I ended up writing, I think the first story was really lame, but the second story may be one of the best I've written. At least, that's how I feel about it right now anyway. I'll read it tomorrow with some new perspective and see if I need to touch it up any further before submitting. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm between big projects right now, so I think I'll take a couple of weeks to see just how many short stories I can get down. Most of my stories already end up in the slush pile anyway. Maybe this commitment to quantity will shake some ideas loose and bring out the best in my writing. I certainly never know what will, so it's not like it isn't worth trying. Should be a lot of fun too!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="creative-writing"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="short-stories"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I woke up early this morning (for once) and decided to pump out some short fiction. Writing for these recent competitions showed me that I can get more stories down than I ever realized I could in a short amount of time. Some of them even turn out really good. I've always subscribed to the notion that quality beats quantity, but if I can write a lot, then I figure, why not try the opposite and see how it goes? The good ones I'll edit up and submit for publication, and the bad ones, well, they can go sit in my slush pile. This has kinda always been my process when it comes to short fiction, but over a much longer period of time. I usually take a week or two to thoroughly edit a story even as short as a couple thousand words, but I'm trying to limit myself to a day to write and a day to edit to see how it goes. And so far, so great! I got two stories written just today, about 3000 words total. Somehow, moving from one story to the next made the output feel much smaller than it was. Normally I struggle to get 3000 words down in a day, much less a few hours like I did this morning. I think longer stories are harder for me because it's more difficult to wrap my head around the structure and see where exactly I need to go. I spend a lot more time thinking about what to do than I do actually writing. For this little experiment though, I'm trying to shut off my perfectionist brain and just go for it. The structure of these shorter stories like I wrote today tends to reveal itself after I get a few paragraphs down. As for what I ended up writing, I think the first story was really lame, but the second story may be one of the best I've written. At least, that's how I feel about it right now anyway. I'll read it tomorrow with some new perspective and see if I need to touch it up any further before submitting. I'm between big projects right now, so I think I'll take a couple of weeks to see just how many short stories I can get down. Most of my stories already end up in the slush pile anyway. Maybe this commitment to quantity will shake some ideas loose and bring out the best in my writing. I certainly never know what will, so it's not like it isn't worth trying. Should be a lot of fun too! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 517: Agent Queries</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/11/day-517-agent-queries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 517: Agent Queries"/><published>2025-03-12T02:07:54+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-12T02:07:54+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/11/day-517-agent-queries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/11/day-517-agent-queries/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The writing conference is already paying off! I've gotten in touch with a couple of agents who I only know about thanks to the meetings I had at the conference. Hopefully my query letters and the pages I sent out get a good reception. It would be nice to finally make some progress on the publishing front, especially after my tantalizing, narrow miss on a big payout from the Writing Battle. I was only one round away! I would be lying if I said it didn't sting, but at least it's good motivation. I'm sure if I keep trying I'll get a big story (or maybe even a book) published eventually. Right? Right!?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The biggest benefit of the conference though was in the confidence boost I got from talking to a few agents. One point that several of the agents stressed to us at the conference was that agents need authors more than an author needs an agent. They might reject hundreds of submissions on a regular basis, but if they weren't getting any at all, they wouldn't have a job. One of the agents even pointed out that self-published works account for something like 40% of the entire book market nowadays, which I found kinda hard to believe honestly. Maybe the total number of books published are self-published, but somehow I seriously doubt they make 40% of the total profits from the market. Still, the fact that any rejection might just add to that huge percentage of self-published books is a big incentive for agents to consider their options carefully.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Moreover, the pitch I gave was received very well despite it being my first time pitching. It really felt like they were just there to talk to me about whatever I was working on rather than the job interview I was expecting. That's probably cause I was paying for each pitch, but I can't imagine a regular conference pitch would be too different. Everybody was friendly and encouraging even if it was obvious they didn't want to represent my story for one reason or another. I guess I'll find out soon if that's how most pitches go since I'll be on the lookout for any conferences nearby for the foreseeable future. There are already a couple on my radar!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literary-agents"/><category term="literature"/><category term="publishing"/><category term="querying"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><category term="writing-tips"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The writing conference is already paying off! I've gotten in touch with a couple of agents who I only know about thanks to the meetings I had at the conference. Hopefully my query letters and the pages I sent out get a good reception. It would be nice to finally make some progress on the publishing front, especially after my tantalizing, narrow miss on a big payout from the Writing Battle. I was only one round away! I would be lying if I said it didn't sting, but at least it's good motivation. I'm sure if I keep trying I'll get a big story (or maybe even a book) published eventually. Right? Right!? The biggest benefit of the conference though was in the confidence boost I got from talking to a few agents. One point that several of the agents stressed to us at the conference was that agents need authors more than an author needs an agent. They might reject hundreds of submissions on a regular basis, but if they weren't getting any at all, they wouldn't have a job. One of the agents even pointed out that self-published works account for something like 40% of the entire book market nowadays, which I found kinda hard to believe honestly. Maybe the total number of books published are self-published, but somehow I seriously doubt they make 40% of the total profits from the market. Still, the fact that any rejection might just add to that huge percentage of self-published books is a big incentive for agents to consider their options carefully. Moreover, the pitch I gave was received very well despite it being my first time pitching. It really felt like they were just there to talk to me about whatever I was working on rather than the job interview I was expecting. That's probably cause I was paying for each pitch, but I can't imagine a regular conference pitch would be too different. Everybody was friendly and encouraging even if it was obvious they didn't want to represent my story for one reason or another. I guess I'll find out soon if that's how most pitches go since I'll be on the lookout for any conferences nearby for the foreseeable future. There are already a couple on my radar! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 516: Writing Battle Results</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 516: Writing Battle Results"/><published>2025-03-11T01:11:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-11T01:11:15+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Over the weekend I finally got the results back from the writing battle I joined over a month ago. Long story short, I made top 16! It was my first battle and I'm happy to have gotten so far on a story that I enjoyed working on so much. Now that the competition is over, I decided to make the story public so anybody can read it on the website. <a href="https://www.writingbattle.com/story/debrief/31955646-9785-40c5-841f-00058f81ad10?uploadedStory">If you're interested, check it out right here!</a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The feedback I got from the judges was largely positive and I'm happy with what I've got. They brought up a few points where they were a little confused or thrown by my word choice, but there was nothing critically wrong with the story, so I'll take that as a big win. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The whole experience has been the most fun I've had with a writing competition. The format of receiving round by round results and getting feedback from fellow participants makes it so much more engaging than all the other 'fire and forget' competitions I've joined. I hope the Writing Battles site continues to grow and prosper into the future.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the weekend I finally got the results back from the writing battle I joined over a month ago. Long story short, I made top 16! It was my first battle and I'm happy to have gotten so far on a story that I enjoyed working on so much. Now that the competition is over, I decided to make the story public so anybody can read it on the website. If you're interested, check it out right here! The feedback I got from the judges was largely positive and I'm happy with what I've got. They brought up a few points where they were a little confused or thrown by my word choice, but there was nothing critically wrong with the story, so I'll take that as a big win. The whole experience has been the most fun I've had with a writing competition. The format of receiving round by round results and getting feedback from fellow participants makes it so much more engaging than all the other 'fire and forget' competitions I've joined. I hope the Writing Battles site continues to grow and prosper into the future. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 515: Made it to Finals!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 515: Made it to Finals!"/><published>2025-03-08T02:53:40+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-08T02:53:40+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The Writing Battle competition is entering it's final stretch! They'll be judging finals over the weekend and should be getting us the results on Sunday. I've been so nervous about pitching I hadn't thought about it in a while. Looks like both I and a friend of mine, Rick, made it to finals together! We'll be waiting with baited breath for the results on Sunday. You can track the competition too right here, <a href="https://writingbattle.com/">https://writingbattle.com/</a> or wait for Monday to come around when I'll announce the final results here!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Writing Battle competition is entering it's final stretch! They'll be judging finals over the weekend and should be getting us the results on Sunday. I've been so nervous about pitching I hadn't thought about it in a while. Looks like both I and a friend of mine, Rick, made it to finals together! We'll be waiting with baited breath for the results on Sunday. You can track the competition too right here, https://writingbattle.com/ or wait for Monday to come around when I'll announce the final results here! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 514: Pitch Letter</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 514: Pitch Letter"/><published>2025-03-07T01:55:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-07T01:55:01+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>This coming Sunday I'll be heading to a writer's conference where I'll be pitching my story 'Jeffries' for the first time, and I'm finding the pitch to be some of the most difficult writing I've had to do. Taking the most interesting elements of a fictional story and turning it into a persuasive piece designed to get someone's attention sounds like it would be pretty simple. I imagine most readers like myself have tried to convince friends and family to read our favorite stories, written by other people that is. I even wrote a piece yesterday about how good I think 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is, and I write reviews pretty often, so you'd think I'd be an old hat summing up the most attractive qualities of a novel by now. It <em>has </em>helped a lot in terms of quality, but it sure doesn't make it any easier. The thought of saying my pitch out loud makes me wanna go hide. I have it written at least, so maybe I can keep refining it over the weekend. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That's why I decided to post it today and see if anybody has any suggestions before I head to the writers conference. Any comments would be appreciated! Anyway, here it is:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Dear [Name]:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>In a grim near-future, both of Jeffry Morgan’s bodies meet every evening to synchronize their memories. Half of Jeffry’s forty-eight waking hours are those of a simple laborer, fulfilling his obligation to society as the law dictates. The other half he spends at his dream job in the most advanced biocomputing lab in the world, researching the technology that enables his split existence: the double-body program.&nbsp;</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>He’s been moving up fast at Wetworks despite his young age, thanks in no small part to his boss and CTO, Tyrell Thompson. Tyrell promised him a leading role in the company, and a raise that may even be large enough to buy his way out of compulsory labor. It’s fantastic news to share, but upon arriving home, he realizes with a shock that he’s lost track of himself. One of his bodies is nowhere to be found.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Jeffry is forced to grapple with the morality of the double-body program after Tyrell pressures him to replace the missing body, even if the existing Jeffry Morgan may still be alive out there somewhere. Meanwhile, his other half attempts to deal with the ruthless abductors who have a mysterious purpose in mind for their stolen bioengineer. He can only hope that his other self will find him before it’s too late.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>‘Jeffries’ (~35,000 words) is a hard sci-fi story set in a dystopian future about Jeffry Morgan’s abduction and his ensuing search for himself. The story appeals to readers of novella-length sci-fi in magazines like ‘The Magazine of Science Fiction and Fantasy,’ or anthologies such as Ken Liu’s ‘The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,’ as well as anyone seeking an introspective tale about the nature of sentience and human rights.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I’ve been writing full-time for two years. I have published poetry in TulipTree Publishing’s ‘Stories that Need to be Told: 2023’ anthology titled ‘Mayflies’ and a short story in ‘The Book of Choices Vol. 1’ anthology from Wolf Grove Media titled ‘Death’s Dilemma.’ I also run a blog where I publish reviews, literary analysis, and personal articles.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for your consideration,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="horror"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short-stories"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This coming Sunday I'll be heading to a writer's conference where I'll be pitching my story 'Jeffries' for the first time, and I'm finding the pitch to be some of the most difficult writing I've had to do. Taking the most interesting elements of a fictional story and turning it into a persuasive piece designed to get someone's attention sounds like it would be pretty simple. I imagine most readers like myself have tried to convince friends and family to read our favorite stories, written by other people that is. I even wrote a piece yesterday about how good I think 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is, and I write reviews pretty often, so you'd think I'd be an old hat summing up the most attractive qualities of a novel by now. It has helped a lot in terms of quality, but it sure doesn't make it any easier. The thought of saying my pitch out loud makes me wanna go hide. I have it written at least, so maybe I can keep refining it over the weekend. That's why I decided to post it today and see if anybody has any suggestions before I head to the writers conference. Any comments would be appreciated! Anyway, here it is: Dear [Name]: In a grim near-future, both of Jeffry Morgan’s bodies meet every evening to synchronize their memories. Half of Jeffry’s forty-eight waking hours are those of a simple laborer, fulfilling his obligation to society as the law dictates. The other half he spends at his dream job in the most advanced biocomputing lab in the world, researching the technology that enables his split existence: the double-body program.&nbsp; He’s been moving up fast at Wetworks despite his young age, thanks in no small part to his boss and CTO, Tyrell Thompson. Tyrell promised him a leading role in the company, and a raise that may even be large enough to buy his way out of compulsory labor. It’s fantastic news to share, but upon arriving home, he realizes with a shock that he’s lost track of himself. One of his bodies is nowhere to be found. Jeffry is forced to grapple with the morality of the double-body program after Tyrell pressures him to replace the missing body, even if the existing Jeffry Morgan may still be alive out there somewhere. Meanwhile, his other half attempts to deal with the ruthless abductors who have a mysterious purpose in mind for their stolen bioengineer. He can only hope that his other self will find him before it’s too late. ‘Jeffries’ (~35,000 words) is a hard sci-fi story set in a dystopian future about Jeffry Morgan’s abduction and his ensuing search for himself. The story appeals to readers of novella-length sci-fi in magazines like ‘The Magazine of Science Fiction and Fantasy,’ or anthologies such as Ken Liu’s ‘The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,’ as well as anyone seeking an introspective tale about the nature of sentience and human rights. I’ve been writing full-time for two years. I have published poetry in TulipTree Publishing’s ‘Stories that Need to be Told: 2023’ anthology titled ‘Mayflies’ and a short story in ‘The Book of Choices Vol. 1’ anthology from Wolf Grove Media titled ‘Death’s Dilemma.’ I also run a blog where I publish reviews, literary analysis, and personal articles. Thank you for your consideration, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 513: Blood Over Bright Haven</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 513: Blood Over Bright Haven"/><published>2025-03-06T04:45:39+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-06T04:45:39+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I finished up 'Blood Over Bright Haven' and I'm happy to say the quality of the book remains high for the whole length of the novel, even after that killer first chapter. After Thomil manages to cross over into the city of Tiran, the book diverts from his character for a while to introduce the real protagonist, Sciona Freynan. But who is Thomil you ask? Well, I accidentally called him Beyern in the first impressions post. The first chapter threw like ten names at me so I got confused. Oops. He was the man who ran across the ice field into Tiran, losing his tribe, but saving his niece in the process. His story remains unknown for a while as Sciona develops.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Her story begins with an exam, her final exam in fact. Women in Tiran society don't typically practice magic at the highest level, but Sciona has staked her entire life on her mastery of the field. She's progressed as far as a mage as any woman ever has in Tiran history, but there's still one more hurdle. If she can pass her exam, she'll become one of a hundred Highmages in the entire city, and the first woman to have ever achieved the rank. As women are only allowed to take the exam once every ten years, this is her only chance to prove herself to the all-male court of Archmages who will decide her future. The exam is a really cool introduction to the magic, and Sciona as a character too (one of the most egotistical, obsessive characters I've ever read, but I'll get to that). It's a really cool language-based magic that has developed over three centuries into what is pretty close to a programming language. Using a spellograph, which is like typewriter for spells, mages are able to source energy from a place known as 'the otherworld' and turn that energy into action in the real world. The mysterious otherworld is Sciona's specialty, and she knows how to map it better than anybody else in the whole city. Like any good magic system, there's a dark side. Siphoning energy from 'the forbidden coordinates' will do ... bad things. Nobody is quite sure what since this dark magic was only ever practiced by the evil mage Sabernyn, who used it murder his enemies in cold blood. That won't be a problem for Sciona though. Right? </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Naturally, she passes the exam, but not without some difficulties. Her benefactor, Archmage Bringham, is overjoyed to let her know she's become the first female Highmage in Tiran. He plays an important role in the story as a sort of 'benevolent' patriarch, helping Sciona adjust to the life of a highmage. After inducting her into the society, he puts her first task before her: develop a mapping solution that will allow her to source enough energy from the Otherworld to expand the massive barrier around the city. It's no small project, and the Highmages will be in tense competition to recommend the best solution. She's got her work cut out for her. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Even though she's successfully become the first female Highmage, her fellow Highmages, who are all massive assholes without exception, treat her like garbage. Many of them make sexist remarks about how she rose to such heights against the odds (including the suggestion that she probably has a sexual relationship with her 60-year-old benefactor, disgusting), but the worst among them is Cleon Renthorn. He's pure slime, a trust-fund adult made up of almost nothing but ego, arrogance, and spite. Sciona doesn't even get the satisfaction of being better than him thanks to his immense skill as a mage, making him a real threat. What I find most interesting about Renthorn is how much Sciona has in common with him, a point that's brought up a few times throughout the book. Sciona has a massive ego and a lot of spite in her heart too, due in no small part to the rampant sexism in Tiran culture. She's cold hearted, driven, and powerful, an intimidating combo for someone like the janitor she encounters on her first day as a Highmage. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Renthorn, as the guy in charge of staff, assigns Sciona a Kwen janitor as an assistant instead of an educated mage in an attempt to put her in her place. The janitor turns out to be none other than Thomil, who has survived in the city since his traumatic crossing years ago. I love how he ties back into the story as a result of Renthorn being a huge dick because he ends up being a blessing in disguise for Sciona. He's kind, patient, quiet, listens well, and is surprisingly intelligent. The opposite of Renthorn in every way. Like Thomil, those from the world beyond the barrier are known as Kwen, and are treated as an underclass in Tiran society. Sometimes people refer to them using the slur 'blighters,' which is kinda like if a Nazi referred to a Jewish person as a 'gasser.' It's pretty messed up. They work the hardest, lowest paying jobs in the city, and if they can't work, they're thrown outside the barrier to suffer the same fate as the rest of Thomil's tribe, obliterated by blight. It's a pretty miserable existence all things considered, but things turn around for him after becoming Sciona's assistant. He gets a raise, doesn't have to do as much manual labor, and he gets a free education. Sciona is happy with him despite her prejudices against Kwen, and even finds herself becoming his friend after they get plastered together at the bar. Wins all around. Of course, she'd never fall for him though ... right?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Yeah, there's a romance that plays a big part in the story. I actually didn't see much marketing for it as a romantasy, but I think the romance is such a big part that it probably counts. After reading this book, I've come to think of it as a really good version of what 'The Fourth Wing' was trying to be. It's a lot more creative, the writing is way better, and the characters actually make me care about them, but there remains some undeniable parallels with the strong female lead, feminist themes, prominent romance, and oppressive fantasy world. Another (much better) story it reminds me of is Ursula K. Le Guin's short story 'Those Who Walk Away From Omelas.' Mostly its the themes that coincide, but honestly 'Blood Over Bright Haven' has a lot more time and wiggle room to really nail down the moral ... I'd go so far as to say that I actually prefer this story despite Le Guin being a titan of politically oriented sci-fi. Sorry!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And with that I'm getting into some huge spoilers. Don't read further if you'd like to have this one unspoiled. If you decide not to read on, thanks for reading as far as you have! I hope it's clear by now that the book is a solid recommendation from me.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Right, the themes. There's this intriguing moral dilemma at the heart of the story, shown through the cultural differences between Thomil and Sciona. Thomil asks her at some point if she believes a person with good intentions who does awful things by accident is a better person than someone with bad intentions who accidentally ends up doing good. While Sciona is convinced that good intentions are what matters, especially to her God, Thomil believes the opposite, that the actual effect one has on the world is the only way to judge a person's morality. This burgeoning conflict between them leads right into a crazy twist. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>After months of work and some brilliant deductions, Sciona and Thomil master a mapping algorithm that will let them look into the Otherworld in more detail and full color, something only ancient Kwen mages were capable of. But when Sciona uses this new magic to siphon energy from the Otherworld just as she usually does, Thomil recognizes something horrific. The window they've peered through looks almost identical to his home, a snowy white field where scarce bushes grow. He throws the spellograph off the desk when the siphoning begins, physically ill over what he's seen. Siphoning energy from the bushes on the plain looks identical to the blight that took his family. Combine this with the fact that the forbidden coordinates happen to overlap with the barrier around Tiran, and the terrible truth becomes obvious: that the magic in Tiran is powered by the lives of Kwen living beyond the barrier. The Tirans have been using magic to siphon energy from PEOPLE! Their lives power the trains, the lights, the heaters, everything! Every single one of the thousands of spells Sciona has written over her career has taken the lives of people outside the barrier just like Thomil. She, and everybody else in the city, are unwitting mass murderers.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The twist is probably the best part of the novel because its so obvious in hindsight. The book is paced just well enough that you might not catch on until it hits, even though it's pretty clear that <em>something </em>isn't right. I mean, it can't all be rosy with what happened in that explosive first chapter, right?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The conflict between Thomil and Sciona ramps up because she's unable to accept the truth and says some pretty racist things to him about her God being the only objective Truth, with the implication that it was only just that his tribe died for Tiran's magic. Part of this is that her ego won't allow her to sacrifice something as important to her as magic, not even for Thomil. He turns his back and spends some time with his niece for a while, the one he saved in the first chapter. His niece is an interesting side character, but doesn't contribute too much to the plot. I'm pushing my word count as is, but suffice to say she hates Sciona for good reason but comes around as they grow together. Thomil has felt guilty for raising her as a member of his tribe rather than a Tiranish woman who might have an easier life, but Sciona helps him overcome his guilt by convincing him that his people are worth carrying on for even if it's hard.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That comes long after some well-warranted depressive soul searching though, (the only part of the novel that did drag a little for me). Sciona realizes how right Thomil is and decides to do something about it. Despite Sciona's best efforts though, she's unable to convince any of the other mages to stop using magic (most of whom already knew what they were doing to people anyway). Even her mentor Archmage Bringham has accepted 'God's Truth' that the Kwen are inherently lesser, made to be harvested for the glory of Tiran. Renthorn is the worst of them though. He not only knows about the sacrifices, but tries to convince Sciona to show him her mapping solution so he can <em>get off on watching his spells turn people into pulp</em>. Thomil decks the hell out of him when he tries to get handsy with Sciona right after she refuses him, which is probably Thomil's best single moment. Sciona and Thomil make up (and the romance comes full swing), just in time to decide the only recourse is good old-fashioned violence. Meanwhile, the highmages are thinking about expanding the coordinate system so they can harvest people's bioenergy from other continents too, so they definitely have it coming. Sciona uses her new spell to show the whole city the truth, a race war ensues, Bringham reveals his even darker colors, and Renthorn gets a large object dropped on his head. Then Sciona nobly sacrifices herself to wipe out all the high mages by siphoning from the forbidden coordinates in the very spot that she first passed her exam. A fitting end if you ask me. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>To sum up, I really enjoyed this novel. Author M. L. Wang made some decisions that could easily have turned the book sour that actually end up making it as good as it is. For one thing, Sciona is not a likeable character. Other than the goodness Thomil brings to her life, she's kind of a deranged egotist psycho. I'm sure if she hadn't met him she would have ended up accepting the deaths of the Kwen as a necessary sacrifice to fuel her power. This is a weird choice because even three fourths of the way through the novel, she's still doing really unlikeable, unrelatable things to people. What the book gains from this though is an unparalleled opportunity for Sciona to grow and change. She starts out almost inhumanly driven to her singular purpose of becoming a Highmage, but eventually grows a heart and learns to care about the people around her. Thomil also gets a little growth by the end, but he was certainly a more static character. Someone with a soul to judge Sciona against to see how far she's come. I think his story has a really traumatic ending to the point where I almost wish he would have gone out with Sciona. It comes full circle really well too though with how he lives on for his tribe and his niece. I'm torn on Thomil. Sciona on the other hand is extremely capable and powerful, and supremely interesting to follow, even if I'd probably never call her a friend.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I can't call it a heartwarming tale, but it does make you feel like even the worst of the worst can learn to be better. And that's really saying something from a book where almost every character is a mass-murderer who looks down on women and thinks other races are little more than fuel for their God-given gift of magic. I'd love to read some of her other stories in the future. I hope they're just as delightfully grim as 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="review"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I finished up 'Blood Over Bright Haven' and I'm happy to say the quality of the book remains high for the whole length of the novel, even after that killer first chapter. After Thomil manages to cross over into the city of Tiran, the book diverts from his character for a while to introduce the real protagonist, Sciona Freynan. But who is Thomil you ask? Well, I accidentally called him Beyern in the first impressions post. The first chapter threw like ten names at me so I got confused. Oops. He was the man who ran across the ice field into Tiran, losing his tribe, but saving his niece in the process. His story remains unknown for a while as Sciona develops. Her story begins with an exam, her final exam in fact. Women in Tiran society don't typically practice magic at the highest level, but Sciona has staked her entire life on her mastery of the field. She's progressed as far as a mage as any woman ever has in Tiran history, but there's still one more hurdle. If she can pass her exam, she'll become one of a hundred Highmages in the entire city, and the first woman to have ever achieved the rank. As women are only allowed to take the exam once every ten years, this is her only chance to prove herself to the all-male court of Archmages who will decide her future. The exam is a really cool introduction to the magic, and Sciona as a character too (one of the most egotistical, obsessive characters I've ever read, but I'll get to that). It's a really cool language-based magic that has developed over three centuries into what is pretty close to a programming language. Using a spellograph, which is like typewriter for spells, mages are able to source energy from a place known as 'the otherworld' and turn that energy into action in the real world. The mysterious otherworld is Sciona's specialty, and she knows how to map it better than anybody else in the whole city. Like any good magic system, there's a dark side. Siphoning energy from 'the forbidden coordinates' will do ... bad things. Nobody is quite sure what since this dark magic was only ever practiced by the evil mage Sabernyn, who used it murder his enemies in cold blood. That won't be a problem for Sciona though. Right? Naturally, she passes the exam, but not without some difficulties. Her benefactor, Archmage Bringham, is overjoyed to let her know she's become the first female Highmage in Tiran. He plays an important role in the story as a sort of 'benevolent' patriarch, helping Sciona adjust to the life of a highmage. After inducting her into the society, he puts her first task before her: develop a mapping solution that will allow her to source enough energy from the Otherworld to expand the massive barrier around the city. It's no small project, and the Highmages will be in tense competition to recommend the best solution. She's got her work cut out for her. Even though she's successfully become the first female Highmage, her fellow Highmages, who are all massive assholes without exception, treat her like garbage. Many of them make sexist remarks about how she rose to such heights against the odds (including the suggestion that she probably has a sexual relationship with her 60-year-old benefactor, disgusting), but the worst among them is Cleon Renthorn. He's pure slime, a trust-fund adult made up of almost nothing but ego, arrogance, and spite. Sciona doesn't even get the satisfaction of being better than him thanks to his immense skill as a mage, making him a real threat. What I find most interesting about Renthorn is how much Sciona has in common with him, a point that's brought up a few times throughout the book. Sciona has a massive ego and a lot of spite in her heart too, due in no small part to the rampant sexism in Tiran culture. She's cold hearted, driven, and powerful, an intimidating combo for someone like the janitor she encounters on her first day as a Highmage. Renthorn, as the guy in charge of staff, assigns Sciona a Kwen janitor as an assistant instead of an educated mage in an attempt to put her in her place. The janitor turns out to be none other than Thomil, who has survived in the city since his traumatic crossing years ago. I love how he ties back into the story as a result of Renthorn being a huge dick because he ends up being a blessing in disguise for Sciona. He's kind, patient, quiet, listens well, and is surprisingly intelligent. The opposite of Renthorn in every way. Like Thomil, those from the world beyond the barrier are known as Kwen, and are treated as an underclass in Tiran society. Sometimes people refer to them using the slur 'blighters,' which is kinda like if a Nazi referred to a Jewish person as a 'gasser.' It's pretty messed up. They work the hardest, lowest paying jobs in the city, and if they can't work, they're thrown outside the barrier to suffer the same fate as the rest of Thomil's tribe, obliterated by blight. It's a pretty miserable existence all things considered, but things turn around for him after becoming Sciona's assistant. He gets a raise, doesn't have to do as much manual labor, and he gets a free education. Sciona is happy with him despite her prejudices against Kwen, and even finds herself becoming his friend after they get plastered together at the bar. Wins all around. Of course, she'd never fall for him though ... right? Yeah, there's a romance that plays a big part in the story. I actually didn't see much marketing for it as a romantasy, but I think the romance is such a big part that it probably counts. After reading this book, I've come to think of it as a really good version of what 'The Fourth Wing' was trying to be. It's a lot more creative, the writing is way better, and the characters actually make me care about them, but there remains some undeniable parallels with the strong female lead, feminist themes, prominent romance, and oppressive fantasy world. Another (much better) story it reminds me of is Ursula K. Le Guin's short story 'Those Who Walk Away From Omelas.' Mostly its the themes that coincide, but honestly 'Blood Over Bright Haven' has a lot more time and wiggle room to really nail down the moral ... I'd go so far as to say that I actually prefer this story despite Le Guin being a titan of politically oriented sci-fi. Sorry! And with that I'm getting into some huge spoilers. Don't read further if you'd like to have this one unspoiled. If you decide not to read on, thanks for reading as far as you have! I hope it's clear by now that the book is a solid recommendation from me. Right, the themes. There's this intriguing moral dilemma at the heart of the story, shown through the cultural differences between Thomil and Sciona. Thomil asks her at some point if she believes a person with good intentions who does awful things by accident is a better person than someone with bad intentions who accidentally ends up doing good. While Sciona is convinced that good intentions are what matters, especially to her God, Thomil believes the opposite, that the actual effect one has on the world is the only way to judge a person's morality. This burgeoning conflict between them leads right into a crazy twist. After months of work and some brilliant deductions, Sciona and Thomil master a mapping algorithm that will let them look into the Otherworld in more detail and full color, something only ancient Kwen mages were capable of. But when Sciona uses this new magic to siphon energy from the Otherworld just as she usually does, Thomil recognizes something horrific. The window they've peered through looks almost identical to his home, a snowy white field where scarce bushes grow. He throws the spellograph off the desk when the siphoning begins, physically ill over what he's seen. Siphoning energy from the bushes on the plain looks identical to the blight that took his family. Combine this with the fact that the forbidden coordinates happen to overlap with the barrier around Tiran, and the terrible truth becomes obvious: that the magic in Tiran is powered by the lives of Kwen living beyond the barrier. The Tirans have been using magic to siphon energy from PEOPLE! Their lives power the trains, the lights, the heaters, everything! Every single one of the thousands of spells Sciona has written over her career has taken the lives of people outside the barrier just like Thomil. She, and everybody else in the city, are unwitting mass murderers. The twist is probably the best part of the novel because its so obvious in hindsight. The book is paced just well enough that you might not catch on until it hits, even though it's pretty clear that something isn't right. I mean, it can't all be rosy with what happened in that explosive first chapter, right? The conflict between Thomil and Sciona ramps up because she's unable to accept the truth and says some pretty racist things to him about her God being the only objective Truth, with the implication that it was only just that his tribe died for Tiran's magic. Part of this is that her ego won't allow her to sacrifice something as important to her as magic, not even for Thomil. He turns his back and spends some time with his niece for a while, the one he saved in the first chapter. His niece is an interesting side character, but doesn't contribute too much to the plot. I'm pushing my word count as is, but suffice to say she hates Sciona for good reason but comes around as they grow together. Thomil has felt guilty for raising her as a member of his tribe rather than a Tiranish woman who might have an easier life, but Sciona helps him overcome his guilt by convincing him that his people are worth carrying on for even if it's hard. That comes long after some well-warranted depressive soul searching though, (the only part of the novel that did drag a little for me). Sciona realizes how right Thomil is and decides to do something about it. Despite Sciona's best efforts though, she's unable to convince any of the other mages to stop using magic (most of whom already knew what they were doing to people anyway). Even her mentor Archmage Bringham has accepted 'God's Truth' that the Kwen are inherently lesser, made to be harvested for the glory of Tiran. Renthorn is the worst of them though. He not only knows about the sacrifices, but tries to convince Sciona to show him her mapping solution so he can get off on watching his spells turn people into pulp. Thomil decks the hell out of him when he tries to get handsy with Sciona right after she refuses him, which is probably Thomil's best single moment. Sciona and Thomil make up (and the romance comes full swing), just in time to decide the only recourse is good old-fashioned violence. Meanwhile, the highmages are thinking about expanding the coordinate system so they can harvest people's bioenergy from other continents too, so they definitely have it coming. Sciona uses her new spell to show the whole city the truth, a race war ensues, Bringham reveals his even darker colors, and Renthorn gets a large object dropped on his head. Then Sciona nobly sacrifices herself to wipe out all the high mages by siphoning from the forbidden coordinates in the very spot that she first passed her exam. A fitting end if you ask me. To sum up, I really enjoyed this novel. Author M. L. Wang made some decisions that could easily have turned the book sour that actually end up making it as good as it is. For one thing, Sciona is not a likeable character. Other than the goodness Thomil brings to her life, she's kind of a deranged egotist psycho. I'm sure if she hadn't met him she would have ended up accepting the deaths of the Kwen as a necessary sacrifice to fuel her power. This is a weird choice because even three fourths of the way through the novel, she's still doing really unlikeable, unrelatable things to people. What the book gains from this though is an unparalleled opportunity for Sciona to grow and change. She starts out almost inhumanly driven to her singular purpose of becoming a Highmage, but eventually grows a heart and learns to care about the people around her. Thomil also gets a little growth by the end, but he was certainly a more static character. Someone with a soul to judge Sciona against to see how far she's come. I think his story has a really traumatic ending to the point where I almost wish he would have gone out with Sciona. It comes full circle really well too though with how he lives on for his tribe and his niece. I'm torn on Thomil. Sciona on the other hand is extremely capable and powerful, and supremely interesting to follow, even if I'd probably never call her a friend. I can't call it a heartwarming tale, but it does make you feel like even the worst of the worst can learn to be better. And that's really saying something from a book where almost every character is a mass-murderer who looks down on women and thinks other races are little more than fuel for their God-given gift of magic. I'd love to read some of her other stories in the future. I hope they're just as delightfully grim as 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 512: The Hidden Girl and Other Stories</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 512: The Hidden Girl and Other Stories"/><published>2025-03-05T02:45:43+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T02:45:43+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I'm already adding to the book haul. I think I have literature problem. Actually I've been meaning to get this book for a long time and it slipped my mind when I bought this round, so I always meant to include it! It's not an extra book so much as it is a misplaced book. Or so I tell myself.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It's called 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' by Ken Liu. Fitting with this haul's theme, it's a sci-fi anthology with <em>seventeen </em>stories! I'm most excited to read 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series. I've never seen a trilogy of short stories before, so I'm excited to see how the structure works. I never considered writing multiple short stories in series because I just figured you would write a novel instead if you wanted to do that. A while back I watched an animated adaptation of this trilogy, a show called 'Pantheon' that I've reviewed before, but I've read that the stories themselves are very different from the show. If they're half as entertaining, I'll be happy with my purchase. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I went ahead and read the first story 'Ghost Days' (though I'm still working on 'Blood Over Bright Haven') and what I found most striking was (again) the structure. It starts in the future and traces the path of an old bronze antique deep into the past and all the way back again through a series of vignettes that feature the object. I can't help but wonder if this story was originally based on some kind of prompt or exercise because of how uniquely organized it is. The prose is here and there and I think some of the dialogue can be a little clunky, but the story itself is so interesting that it doesn't make much of a difference. I'm hoping they only get better as I continue.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading, </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm already adding to the book haul. I think I have literature problem. Actually I've been meaning to get this book for a long time and it slipped my mind when I bought this round, so I always meant to include it! It's not an extra book so much as it is a misplaced book. Or so I tell myself. It's called 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' by Ken Liu. Fitting with this haul's theme, it's a sci-fi anthology with seventeen stories! I'm most excited to read 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series. I've never seen a trilogy of short stories before, so I'm excited to see how the structure works. I never considered writing multiple short stories in series because I just figured you would write a novel instead if you wanted to do that. A while back I watched an animated adaptation of this trilogy, a show called 'Pantheon' that I've reviewed before, but I've read that the stories themselves are very different from the show. If they're half as entertaining, I'll be happy with my purchase. I went ahead and read the first story 'Ghost Days' (though I'm still working on 'Blood Over Bright Haven') and what I found most striking was (again) the structure. It starts in the future and traces the path of an old bronze antique deep into the past and all the way back again through a series of vignettes that feature the object. I can't help but wonder if this story was originally based on some kind of prompt or exercise because of how uniquely organized it is. The prose is here and there and I think some of the dialogue can be a little clunky, but the story itself is so interesting that it doesn't make much of a difference. I'm hoping they only get better as I continue. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>