<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-04T02:33:51+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 511: Blood Over Bright Haven First Impressions</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 511: Blood Over Bright Haven First Impressions"/><published>2025-03-04T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-04T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I started reading 'Blood Over Bright Haven' by M. L. Wang over the weekend and was completely blown away. I think the first chapter of this novel is the best I've ever read. It somehow established massive stakes, multiple great characters, an immediate call to action, and an interesting fantasy world to boot. It's easily the most action-packed first chapter I've ever read too, and the emotional investment it got out of me within ten pages is more than some whole novels. Seriously, I can't understate how incredible the intro is. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story begins with a dying tribe making their last ditch attempt to reach to safety. It reads a bit more like a prologue than a true chapter one with how it plays out, but I'm more than forgiving it for that nitpick. I won't be able to get across the depth of emotion the perspective character, Beyern, goes through in trying to save his family, but I can tell you that I've never gotten as upset over a first chapter before. Their tribe, who live in an unforgiving tundra plagued by something known as blight, once numbered in the tens of thousands. Now there are but forty left, the only ones not killed by blight and starvation. Their salvation awaits under the magic dome of the city of Tiran, which keeps out the blight and creates an area of warm weather, but to get there, they'll have to cross over a frozen lake. Its not the thin ice or the freezing temperatures that Beyern feels so threatened by though. Blight is waiting beneath the ice, and begins to take his fellows one at a time as soon as the two-mile crossing starts. Streamers of light erupt from the ice to pierce the skin, and just a touch is enough to kill, unravelling their bodies like packaged meat. Will Beyern make it across the lake in time with his sister and niece? And even if they do make it, will they be able to carry on the tribe's legacy into the future?! Read to find out!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Okay, I don't want to spoil it too badly, but I think you can probably guess what happens. Wang is able to establish the kind of stakes I dream of with this horrific crossing by making it about more than just a character. She highlights many of the tribe's long-held traditions as Beyern watches his fellows die horribly to blight. It's not just his people he's losing, but his whole society, a once-great nation reduced to puddles of blood behind him as he sprints to safety with his niece in his arms. Their children are all that stand between them and extinction now. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Pushing the stakes hard, all the way up to a societal level is difficult to execute in normal circumstances, but Wang was able to do it smoothly within only ten pages or so. It's so easy to slip into meaningless statistics, but these people were not just names or numbers. They felt like well-developed characters. The skills, traditions, and memories they carry are all summed up in relation to Beyern in just a sentence or three, but every single one who goes down hurts. It was also a sneaky way to inject a huge amount of world building into a small, tension-fraught package, which I can't help but be a little jealous of too. The gut-punch at the end just as they reach safety ties the chapter up nicely, and flows right into the next chapter. It's so good it's hard to wrap my head around. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I can't wait to read the rest of this. It slows down a lot in the second chapter, but the stakes are still relatively high and I'm once again immediately invested in the new characters that show up. I'm certain this book will be a great read.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I started reading 'Blood Over Bright Haven' by M. L. Wang over the weekend and was completely blown away. I think the first chapter of this novel is the best I've ever read. It somehow established massive stakes, multiple great characters, an immediate call to action, and an interesting fantasy world to boot. It's easily the most action-packed first chapter I've ever read too, and the emotional investment it got out of me within ten pages is more than some whole novels. Seriously, I can't understate how incredible the intro is. The story begins with a dying tribe making their last ditch attempt to reach to safety. It reads a bit more like a prologue than a true chapter one with how it plays out, but I'm more than forgiving it for that nitpick. I won't be able to get across the depth of emotion the perspective character, Beyern, goes through in trying to save his family, but I can tell you that I've never gotten as upset over a first chapter before. Their tribe, who live in an unforgiving tundra plagued by something known as blight, once numbered in the tens of thousands. Now there are but forty left, the only ones not killed by blight and starvation. Their salvation awaits under the magic dome of the city of Tiran, which keeps out the blight and creates an area of warm weather, but to get there, they'll have to cross over a frozen lake. Its not the thin ice or the freezing temperatures that Beyern feels so threatened by though. Blight is waiting beneath the ice, and begins to take his fellows one at a time as soon as the two-mile crossing starts. Streamers of light erupt from the ice to pierce the skin, and just a touch is enough to kill, unravelling their bodies like packaged meat. Will Beyern make it across the lake in time with his sister and niece? And even if they do make it, will they be able to carry on the tribe's legacy into the future?! Read to find out! Okay, I don't want to spoil it too badly, but I think you can probably guess what happens. Wang is able to establish the kind of stakes I dream of with this horrific crossing by making it about more than just a character. She highlights many of the tribe's long-held traditions as Beyern watches his fellows die horribly to blight. It's not just his people he's losing, but his whole society, a once-great nation reduced to puddles of blood behind him as he sprints to safety with his niece in his arms. Their children are all that stand between them and extinction now. Pushing the stakes hard, all the way up to a societal level is difficult to execute in normal circumstances, but Wang was able to do it smoothly within only ten pages or so. It's so easy to slip into meaningless statistics, but these people were not just names or numbers. They felt like well-developed characters. The skills, traditions, and memories they carry are all summed up in relation to Beyern in just a sentence or three, but every single one who goes down hurts. It was also a sneaky way to inject a huge amount of world building into a small, tension-fraught package, which I can't help but be a little jealous of too. The gut-punch at the end just as they reach safety ties the chapter up nicely, and flows right into the next chapter. It's so good it's hard to wrap my head around. I can't wait to read the rest of this. It slows down a lot in the second chapter, but the stakes are still relatively high and I'm once again immediately invested in the new characters that show up. I'm certain this book will be a great read. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 510: Book Haul!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 510: Book Haul!"/><published>2025-03-01T02:13:51+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T02:13:51+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It's been a long time coming, but I'm finally buying some more books. Despite my belated book haul, it's not like I've been wanting for something to read. Quite the contrary! I've been involved in multiple peer-judged competitions, and I've been doing some beta reading for friends. Also, the last thing I read was the Green Bone Saga and I needed to recover after that one. Anyway, here's what's next on my menu!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>This time I wanted to focus on more contemporary sci-fi and fantasy. That's why first up is a novel published in 2023 by M. L. Wang called 'Blood Over Bright Haven.' Its a fantasy novel about the first woman ever admitted to a prestigious order of mages. She unravels a secret conspiracy that could change the practice of magic forever. I totally stole that phrasing from Google by the way. It sounds pretty fun, I'm imagining dark Harry Potter at the moment, but we'll see how it goes after I get into it. I heard about it at my writing group. In fact, I think every book on this list was a recommendation from someone or another. I've got a lot of catching up to do on recommendations I guess ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>No time like today to get started, and that's with a book that someone recommended me so long ago that I bought it as a Christmas gift. I'm looking forward to reading it, it's 'Red Rising,' by Pierce Brown, a dystopian novel that centers around the conflict generated by an oppressive caste system. I remember eating 'The Hunger Games' up as a kid, so I'm sure I'll enjoy this one. There's something about a good underdog story set in an abysmally tragic world that always works.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Well, I hope so anyway, because this next novel is pretty similar actually. Another dystopian novel about a utopian island where everything is not as it seems. And yes, I did steal that phrasing from Google too. 'The Ferryman,' by Justin Cronin is one of the more mysterious books I've come across. Not even the internet will spoil it for me, much less my friends, which means that the concept is either amazing, or just really, really complicated. Hopefully the former.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And finally, 'Pushing Ice,' by Alastair Reynolds. I've read Reynolds before, specifically his Revelation Space trilogy, and this is anything like that, I know I'm bound to be blown away. The sci-fi concepts he's able to come up with are like nothing else I've ever read, and he seems to have an unlimited number of incredible ideas for future technology, alien (and not-so-alien) civilization, and unusual characters to fit into these strange new worlds. I'm excited to read this one, which is why I've left it for last! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And as always, I'll probably add a book to these somewhere along the line. Expect many reviews in the next few weeks! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a long time coming, but I'm finally buying some more books. Despite my belated book haul, it's not like I've been wanting for something to read. Quite the contrary! I've been involved in multiple peer-judged competitions, and I've been doing some beta reading for friends. Also, the last thing I read was the Green Bone Saga and I needed to recover after that one. Anyway, here's what's next on my menu! This time I wanted to focus on more contemporary sci-fi and fantasy. That's why first up is a novel published in 2023 by M. L. Wang called 'Blood Over Bright Haven.' Its a fantasy novel about the first woman ever admitted to a prestigious order of mages. She unravels a secret conspiracy that could change the practice of magic forever. I totally stole that phrasing from Google by the way. It sounds pretty fun, I'm imagining dark Harry Potter at the moment, but we'll see how it goes after I get into it. I heard about it at my writing group. In fact, I think every book on this list was a recommendation from someone or another. I've got a lot of catching up to do on recommendations I guess ... No time like today to get started, and that's with a book that someone recommended me so long ago that I bought it as a Christmas gift. I'm looking forward to reading it, it's 'Red Rising,' by Pierce Brown, a dystopian novel that centers around the conflict generated by an oppressive caste system. I remember eating 'The Hunger Games' up as a kid, so I'm sure I'll enjoy this one. There's something about a good underdog story set in an abysmally tragic world that always works. Well, I hope so anyway, because this next novel is pretty similar actually. Another dystopian novel about a utopian island where everything is not as it seems. And yes, I did steal that phrasing from Google too. 'The Ferryman,' by Justin Cronin is one of the more mysterious books I've come across. Not even the internet will spoil it for me, much less my friends, which means that the concept is either amazing, or just really, really complicated. Hopefully the former. And finally, 'Pushing Ice,' by Alastair Reynolds. I've read Reynolds before, specifically his Revelation Space trilogy, and this is anything like that, I know I'm bound to be blown away. The sci-fi concepts he's able to come up with are like nothing else I've ever read, and he seems to have an unlimited number of incredible ideas for future technology, alien (and not-so-alien) civilization, and unusual characters to fit into these strange new worlds. I'm excited to read this one, which is why I've left it for last! And as always, I'll probably add a book to these somewhere along the line. Expect many reviews in the next few weeks! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 509: Shadow</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 509: Shadow"/><published>2025-02-28T02:52:19+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-28T02:52:19+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>There's this Chinese movie I go back and watch again every once in a while called 'Shadow' that always hits just right. It's got a little bit of everything, being part period film, part fantasy, part espionage thriller, and probably like three part Kung Fu movie on top off all that. It's got some really artistic and creative action sequences, and some great effects too, but where I think it really shines is the twisty plot and excellent character building. I find a little something new in every rewatch, putting it in that rare category of movies I'm not sure I'll ever stop seeing again. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story begins years ago, in the aftermath of the kingdom of Pei's losing war against the kingdom of Yang. The important city of Jingzhou was lost after their genius Commander Ziyu was mortally wounded in combat by Yang Cang, and in the time since, Ziyu has been planning his revenge from deep within a secret chamber of the royal palace. To that end, he directs his shadow, a body double, to challenge Yang Cang to single combat. This angers the crafty, but young and undisciplined King, who demands that Ziyu's double play a duet with the Commader's wife for him in recompense. His refusal to do so sets the plot in motion as the King begins to suspect that Ziyu's body double is not the real Commander ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>There's a lot going on even from the very beginning, and the plot never stops getting thicker. There's some question as to whether the Commander's wife will far for his double, and the King's sister becomes a pawn in his plans, and the Yangs have their own role to play in all of this. Oh and the coolest part of the whole movie are the razor blade umbrellas that the protagonist learns to wield in order to defeat Yang. I mean just look at these things.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The acting and the insane action and crazy twists do get a little ridiculous at times, but they never over stay their welcome so much that it's not still cool. Like here, the secret army that the Commader builds up uses a bunch of umbrellas stacked atop one another to slide down the main street of Jingzhou firing wrist-mounted crossbows to take out all the town guards. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Is it kinda silly? Yes. Is it incredibly epic at the same time? Also yes.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I really can't get enough of this movie and think everybody should give it a watch. Let me know if you've ever seen this movie in the comments and if you liked it as much as I did!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="film"/><category term="horror"/><category term="literature"/><category term="movies"/><category term="review"/><category term="reviews"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There's this Chinese movie I go back and watch again every once in a while called 'Shadow' that always hits just right. It's got a little bit of everything, being part period film, part fantasy, part espionage thriller, and probably like three part Kung Fu movie on top off all that. It's got some really artistic and creative action sequences, and some great effects too, but where I think it really shines is the twisty plot and excellent character building. I find a little something new in every rewatch, putting it in that rare category of movies I'm not sure I'll ever stop seeing again. The story begins years ago, in the aftermath of the kingdom of Pei's losing war against the kingdom of Yang. The important city of Jingzhou was lost after their genius Commander Ziyu was mortally wounded in combat by Yang Cang, and in the time since, Ziyu has been planning his revenge from deep within a secret chamber of the royal palace. To that end, he directs his shadow, a body double, to challenge Yang Cang to single combat. This angers the crafty, but young and undisciplined King, who demands that Ziyu's double play a duet with the Commader's wife for him in recompense. His refusal to do so sets the plot in motion as the King begins to suspect that Ziyu's body double is not the real Commander ... There's a lot going on even from the very beginning, and the plot never stops getting thicker. There's some question as to whether the Commander's wife will far for his double, and the King's sister becomes a pawn in his plans, and the Yangs have their own role to play in all of this. Oh and the coolest part of the whole movie are the razor blade umbrellas that the protagonist learns to wield in order to defeat Yang. I mean just look at these things. The acting and the insane action and crazy twists do get a little ridiculous at times, but they never over stay their welcome so much that it's not still cool. Like here, the secret army that the Commader builds up uses a bunch of umbrellas stacked atop one another to slide down the main street of Jingzhou firing wrist-mounted crossbows to take out all the town guards. Is it kinda silly? Yes. Is it incredibly epic at the same time? Also yes. I really can't get enough of this movie and think everybody should give it a watch. Let me know if you've ever seen this movie in the comments and if you liked it as much as I did! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 508: Update on Jeffries</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 508: Update on Jeffries"/><published>2025-02-27T03:27:38+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T03:27:38+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I know it's been a long time coming, but I think I'm finally, finally getting to the end of editing 'Jeffries.' I did a read through today and didn't feel the need to change much, which is a nice feeling. There's one more scene I want to work in. I know I keep saying that. But this time it really is the last one. The previous last scene ended up spiraling into three separate scenes, but that's always how it is. I'm very close to done. It's not perfect, but the only way to make it any better would be to gut the entire ending and start over, and honestly? If I don't do this at some point it will never be finished. I'm gonna finish this last scene, do one more editing pass, and then call it quits on 'Jeffries.' After that, I'll seek to get it published as is. If it's not good enough for trad publishing in a magazine or on it's own, I'll just publish it myself as a standalone on Amazon.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Then all I have to do is decide what to write next!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I know it's been a long time coming, but I think I'm finally, finally getting to the end of editing 'Jeffries.' I did a read through today and didn't feel the need to change much, which is a nice feeling. There's one more scene I want to work in. I know I keep saying that. But this time it really is the last one. The previous last scene ended up spiraling into three separate scenes, but that's always how it is. I'm very close to done. It's not perfect, but the only way to make it any better would be to gut the entire ending and start over, and honestly? If I don't do this at some point it will never be finished. I'm gonna finish this last scene, do one more editing pass, and then call it quits on 'Jeffries.' After that, I'll seek to get it published as is. If it's not good enough for trad publishing in a magazine or on it's own, I'll just publish it myself as a standalone on Amazon. Then all I have to do is decide what to write next! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 507: Goodbye Finn</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 507: Goodbye Finn"/><published>2025-02-26T00:53:54+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:53:54+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It was a sad day today. I drove over to see my grandparents and help bury their cat, Finn. They got him back in 2012 along with two other cats, Jack and Jill, who have been a fixture in their house ever since. Finn was laid to rest right alongside the other family pets buried on the property in good company. I'm sure he will be sorely missed. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Here's a favorite of my grandfather's, a picture he took of Finn with his brother Jack in the background, looking as if he has two heads.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It was a sad day today. I drove over to see my grandparents and help bury their cat, Finn. They got him back in 2012 along with two other cats, Jack and Jill, who have been a fixture in their house ever since. Finn was laid to rest right alongside the other family pets buried on the property in good company. I'm sure he will be sorely missed. Here's a favorite of my grandfather's, a picture he took of Finn with his brother Jack in the background, looking as if he has two heads. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 506: This is Harder Than I Expected</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/24/day-506-this-is-harder-than-i-expected/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 506: This is Harder Than I Expected"/><published>2025-02-25T02:36:35+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T02:36:35+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/24/day-506-this-is-harder-than-i-expected</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/24/day-506-this-is-harder-than-i-expected/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Well, I judged a couple more stories today for the <a href="https://writingbattle.com/battle">writing battle</a>. I can't say I particularly enjoyed this round. I couldn't connect with either story, partly because of the content, and partly because both of them were felt roughly edited. They had lots of repeated phrasing, choppy sentences, and a couple of weird non-sequiturs that made it hard to follow along. The plots were fuzzy, and worst of all, the characters weren't unrelatable at best, and off-putting at worst. I ended up choosing based on which one had the more coherent plot, although I still wasn't a huge fan. I hate to give a lot of negative feedback all at once. It feels bad, especially knowing I've written some real stinkers too. If I hadn't been able to find anything good in those stories I wrote, I might not have continued writing. I'd hate to discourage someone just because they wrote a poorly formed story one time. Then again, they were pretty bad. I'm not sure I'm cut out for this judging thing. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Hopefully I get some better stories, either from the next round of writing battle, or from <a href="https://twistedtournament.com/">twisted tournament</a>. It's still exciting to see what comes next!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well, I judged a couple more stories today for the writing battle. I can't say I particularly enjoyed this round. I couldn't connect with either story, partly because of the content, and partly because both of them were felt roughly edited. They had lots of repeated phrasing, choppy sentences, and a couple of weird non-sequiturs that made it hard to follow along. The plots were fuzzy, and worst of all, the characters weren't unrelatable at best, and off-putting at worst. I ended up choosing based on which one had the more coherent plot, although I still wasn't a huge fan. I hate to give a lot of negative feedback all at once. It feels bad, especially knowing I've written some real stinkers too. If I hadn't been able to find anything good in those stories I wrote, I might not have continued writing. I'd hate to discourage someone just because they wrote a poorly formed story one time. Then again, they were pretty bad. I'm not sure I'm cut out for this judging thing. Hopefully I get some better stories, either from the next round of writing battle, or from twisted tournament. It's still exciting to see what comes next! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 505: Twisted Tournament</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/21/day-505-twisted-tournament/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 505: Twisted Tournament"/><published>2025-02-22T02:07:55+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-22T02:07:55+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/21/day-505-twisted-tournament</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/21/day-505-twisted-tournament/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The <a href="https://twistedtournament.com/">Twisted Tournament</a> I'm competing in is down to the wire. I have just under 22 hours left to write a 100 word story. I won't post the prompts here because it may interfere with the judges' decision if they happen to find the blog, but just know that they're some killer prompts! Well, for a long story they would be. But with only 100 words I don't know if I can turn it into anything. All the reroll options look really interesting too, and I'm frozen with indecision!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Ok, it's not that bad. I'm just gonna use the prompts I have because they're really good and hope I can squish an idea down into 100 words. It's really almost nothing! The paragraph above is 89 words. I only get one more sentence than that. Wish me luck!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Twisted Tournament I'm competing in is down to the wire. I have just under 22 hours left to write a 100 word story. I won't post the prompts here because it may interfere with the judges' decision if they happen to find the blog, but just know that they're some killer prompts! Well, for a long story they would be. But with only 100 words I don't know if I can turn it into anything. All the reroll options look really interesting too, and I'm frozen with indecision! Ok, it's not that bad. I'm just gonna use the prompts I have because they're really good and hope I can squish an idea down into 100 words. It's really almost nothing! The paragraph above is 89 words. I only get one more sentence than that. Wish me luck! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 504: Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/20/day-504-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 504: Progress Update"/><published>2025-02-21T02:34:47+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-21T02:34:47+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/20/day-504-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/20/day-504-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Lately I've been writing a lot of short fiction, just entering as many competitions as I can keep up with. Right now I've got three I'm working on, each at different stages. Two <a href="https://writingbattle.com/">Writing Battles</a> (one I'm peer judging in, the other I'm just waiting for results), and a competition from <a href="https://twistedtournament.com/">Twisted Tournament</a> that I'm still finishing my story for. It's a been a lot of fun writing short stories. I get more practice developing structure than in the longer pieces I work on because I just get more repetitions in. I do wonder if them all being prompt based has any affect on my ability to come up with new stuff though. It's been a long time since I've written anything just for myself besides <em>Jeffries</em>, and that's almost nine months in the making now. Speaking of ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm still rounding out <em>Jeffries </em>and trying to tie it all together. I'm finding it so difficult to make something so big feel cohesive, and it's not even a full length novel. I want to have it ready by mid March, when I'll be attending a writer's conference and pitching my material to some writing agents for the first time. That won't be nerve wracking at all. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And finally, I'll be chipping away at <a href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/">my new blog site</a> probably for the foreseeable future. It's got several things missing that I'm still working on. At least it looks nicer, and you can see posts all the way back to the beginning of the blog. It's getting there!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lately I've been writing a lot of short fiction, just entering as many competitions as I can keep up with. Right now I've got three I'm working on, each at different stages. Two Writing Battles (one I'm peer judging in, the other I'm just waiting for results), and a competition from Twisted Tournament that I'm still finishing my story for. It's a been a lot of fun writing short stories. I get more practice developing structure than in the longer pieces I work on because I just get more repetitions in. I do wonder if them all being prompt based has any affect on my ability to come up with new stuff though. It's been a long time since I've written anything just for myself besides Jeffries, and that's almost nine months in the making now. Speaking of ... I'm still rounding out Jeffries and trying to tie it all together. I'm finding it so difficult to make something so big feel cohesive, and it's not even a full length novel. I want to have it ready by mid March, when I'll be attending a writer's conference and pitching my material to some writing agents for the first time. That won't be nerve wracking at all. And finally, I'll be chipping away at my new blog site probably for the foreseeable future. It's got several things missing that I'm still working on. At least it looks nicer, and you can see posts all the way back to the beginning of the blog. It's getting there! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 503: Snow Day!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/19/day-503-snow-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 503: Snow Day!"/><published>2025-02-20T03:10:58+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T03:10:58+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/19/day-503-snow-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/19/day-503-snow-day/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>We just got the first several inches of snow fall here in Raleigh that started this afternoon. It's supposed to continue until 1 PM tomorrow. I've never seen this much snow here before. Other than it making driving a lot more nerve wracking, it's pretty magical to see everything in a fluffy layer. I almost got lost driving around town because it was so unfamiliar. I guess I'll be spending the next few days at home, watching the snow fall and reading a good book, and hopefully writing one too.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just got the first several inches of snow fall here in Raleigh that started this afternoon. It's supposed to continue until 1 PM tomorrow. I've never seen this much snow here before. Other than it making driving a lot more nerve wracking, it's pretty magical to see everything in a fluffy layer. I almost got lost driving around town because it was so unfamiliar. I guess I'll be spending the next few days at home, watching the snow fall and reading a good book, and hopefully writing one too. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 502: Sunset</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/18/day-502-sunset/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 502: Sunset"/><published>2025-02-19T03:15:28+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-19T03:15:28+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/18/day-502-sunset</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/18/day-502-sunset/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Every once in a while I find something fascinating that just has to go into a story. There's always something going on in the universe, and some of those things we get to lay eyes on thanks to the rovers on mars like Curiosity, which captured this event: </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><a href="https://www.popsci.com/science/mars-shimmering-clouds/">https://www.popsci.com/science/mars-shimmering-clouds/</a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I've never seen a sunset that color before! I'm definitely writing this one into something. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="curiosity"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="mars"/><category term="rover"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="science"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Every once in a while I find something fascinating that just has to go into a story. There's always something going on in the universe, and some of those things we get to lay eyes on thanks to the rovers on mars like Curiosity, which captured this event: https://www.popsci.com/science/mars-shimmering-clouds/ I've never seen a sunset that color before! I'm definitely writing this one into something. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>