<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-03T18:49:04+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 471: Back to Work</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/06/day-471-back-to-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 471: Back to Work"/><published>2025-01-07T00:41:39+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:41:39+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/06/day-471-back-to-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/06/day-471-back-to-work/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The first Monday of the year has me back to regularly scheduled programming. Unfortunately, I had planned on sharing the first deployed version of my new site today, but every time I think I've finally got it working, something else is wrong. It's been quite the learning process (and something of a headache) but I'm steadily approaching a useable state. Any day now ... any day. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I haven't done much else besides edit up a couple of poems I had written a long time ago and pretty much forgotten about. They weren't too bad, so I think I'll find a place to submit them if I can. There's this one big magazine called Poetry Magazine that pays incredibly well, but of course that means huge competition ... and an insane response time EIGHT MONTHS. I've never seen any publisher take that long, but I suppose it makes sense when there are hundreds of thousands of poems submitted each year. The best option is probably just to publish elsewhere, although that $10 per line is still pretty tempting. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first Monday of the year has me back to regularly scheduled programming. Unfortunately, I had planned on sharing the first deployed version of my new site today, but every time I think I've finally got it working, something else is wrong. It's been quite the learning process (and something of a headache) but I'm steadily approaching a useable state. Any day now ... any day. I haven't done much else besides edit up a couple of poems I had written a long time ago and pretty much forgotten about. They weren't too bad, so I think I'll find a place to submit them if I can. There's this one big magazine called Poetry Magazine that pays incredibly well, but of course that means huge competition ... and an insane response time EIGHT MONTHS. I've never seen any publisher take that long, but I suppose it makes sense when there are hundreds of thousands of poems submitted each year. The best option is probably just to publish elsewhere, although that $10 per line is still pretty tempting. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Friday</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/03/happy-friday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Friday"/><published>2025-01-04T03:32:56+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-04T03:32:56+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/03/happy-friday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/03/happy-friday/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Just a slow day today. Still trying to get Jekyll figured out, but I do think this is the direction I want to go. The combination of customization, prebuilt frameworks, and zero cost to host my blog makes it irresistible. I tried some other sites similar to wordpress but frankly all of them had the same issues. High cost for not much of what I want. The only thing I'm missing out on by using Jekyll to create a site and github to host it is that I won't have access to a platform that will promote my content. It's a big thing to miss out on, but I think I might be able to expand in other ways.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Just a slow day today. Still trying to get Jekyll figured out, but I do think this is the direction I want to go. The combination of customization, prebuilt frameworks, and zero cost to host my blog makes it irresistible. I tried some other sites similar to wordpress but frankly all of them had the same issues. High cost for not much of what I want. The only thing I'm missing out on by using Jekyll to create a site and github to host it is that I won't have access to a platform that will promote my content. It's a big thing to miss out on, but I think I might be able to expand in other ways. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mr. Hyde</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/02/mr-hyde/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mr. Hyde"/><published>2025-01-03T02:41:56+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-03T02:41:56+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/02/mr-hyde</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/02/mr-hyde/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Spent most of my time today just trying out different blog sites and solutions. I think I found one I really want to try, only I've had some issues getting it up and running. It's a piece of software called Jekyll that essentially sets up a website for you, based on a language called Ruby. The whole system is very cool in the nerdiest way possible. It's more customizable than any of the other solutions and it lets me use better templates AND it has some add-ons that will let me migrate my blog from WordPress easily. The best part? The software and even the hosting is free by using a github.io domain. I would pay exactly 0 dollars to run my blog. It's really great in every way ... except it's been a pain in the ass to get it working. I got the basic template up, but I can't seem to get any third party templates up. When I found a template I really wanted, it took me like three hours to solve a particularly annoying dependency issue, but immediately after fixing it I ran into another one. I was trying to set it up on a laptop running linux because I assumed the package managers would help me avoid dependency issues in the first place, but it looks like I'll have to manually install some stuff anyway so I guess I'll try it on my Windows machine tomorrow. I gave myself all month to get the new blog going, but it's still frustrating to run into these roadblocks every time I try something new. All that programming experience I gathered never seems to help me avoid this type of problem, only to fix them. I do end up fixing them though ... usually.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spent most of my time today just trying out different blog sites and solutions. I think I found one I really want to try, only I've had some issues getting it up and running. It's a piece of software called Jekyll that essentially sets up a website for you, based on a language called Ruby. The whole system is very cool in the nerdiest way possible. It's more customizable than any of the other solutions and it lets me use better templates AND it has some add-ons that will let me migrate my blog from WordPress easily. The best part? The software and even the hosting is free by using a github.io domain. I would pay exactly 0 dollars to run my blog. It's really great in every way ... except it's been a pain in the ass to get it working. I got the basic template up, but I can't seem to get any third party templates up. When I found a template I really wanted, it took me like three hours to solve a particularly annoying dependency issue, but immediately after fixing it I ran into another one. I was trying to set it up on a laptop running linux because I assumed the package managers would help me avoid dependency issues in the first place, but it looks like I'll have to manually install some stuff anyway so I guess I'll try it on my Windows machine tomorrow. I gave myself all month to get the new blog going, but it's still frustrating to run into these roadblocks every time I try something new. All that programming experience I gathered never seems to help me avoid this type of problem, only to fix them. I do end up fixing them though ... usually. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy New Year!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/01/happy-new-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year!"/><published>2025-01-01T20:29:46+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T20:29:46+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/01/happy-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/01/happy-new-year/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Our small blue world has once again orbited all the way around the giant fusion furnace in the sky, and I can think of no better way for me to kick off 2025 than curled up in my chair typing away. There's always more work to do, a new story to flesh out, or an old one to refine. I can't wait to see what the new year brings for me and get some good stories out. And of course, some good content too.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>First order of business is a little bit of house keeping. This'll be the first post of the year, but to keep my records straight, day 471 will officially begin on Monday. That way I can have my nice, round, five-day pattern for the rest of the year like I always have. Also, it gives me the next three posts to go completely nuts since the posts don't actually count, right? </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I have some big plans going forward this year. First of all, I'm tired of the blog's look. It's basic, boring, and I probably should have upgraded a long time ago. Another major issue I keep running into is the weird limit WordPress puts on the number of posts I'm allowed to give you, the reader, access to. I've been exploring new options, but haven't settled on anything quite yet. Since WordPress has already received my money for the next year of hosting, I'm going to leave this blog up and add all the new posts I make here, as well as on whatever other site I settle on. By the time I need to renew my payment, the migration will be complete. I'm going to make this a project for the first month of the year, and plan to have something much nicer by the time February comes around. Look out for new updates because at some point I'll post a link to another site with all the same content you can find here. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Another big step I want to take is trying to get 'Jeffries' published. I'm going to continue refining it (the editing never ends), but in the meantime I'll be sending out preliminary versions for magazines and other publishers to see if it gets any traction. As they say, published is better than perfect. Although I think I prefer this saying ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>“A good plan violently executed now is better than a perfect plan next week.” -General George S. Patton, Jr.</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Finally, I'm planning on reading lots of good books! Some things should never change. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Do you have any big plans for the new year? Gym resolutions that you'll probably abandon in a couple weeks, perhaps? Let me know in the comments!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our small blue world has once again orbited all the way around the giant fusion furnace in the sky, and I can think of no better way for me to kick off 2025 than curled up in my chair typing away. There's always more work to do, a new story to flesh out, or an old one to refine. I can't wait to see what the new year brings for me and get some good stories out. And of course, some good content too. First order of business is a little bit of house keeping. This'll be the first post of the year, but to keep my records straight, day 471 will officially begin on Monday. That way I can have my nice, round, five-day pattern for the rest of the year like I always have. Also, it gives me the next three posts to go completely nuts since the posts don't actually count, right? I have some big plans going forward this year. First of all, I'm tired of the blog's look. It's basic, boring, and I probably should have upgraded a long time ago. Another major issue I keep running into is the weird limit WordPress puts on the number of posts I'm allowed to give you, the reader, access to. I've been exploring new options, but haven't settled on anything quite yet. Since WordPress has already received my money for the next year of hosting, I'm going to leave this blog up and add all the new posts I make here, as well as on whatever other site I settle on. By the time I need to renew my payment, the migration will be complete. I'm going to make this a project for the first month of the year, and plan to have something much nicer by the time February comes around. Look out for new updates because at some point I'll post a link to another site with all the same content you can find here. Another big step I want to take is trying to get 'Jeffries' published. I'm going to continue refining it (the editing never ends), but in the meantime I'll be sending out preliminary versions for magazines and other publishers to see if it gets any traction. As they say, published is better than perfect. Although I think I prefer this saying ... “A good plan violently executed now is better than a perfect plan next week.” -General George S. Patton, Jr. Finally, I'm planning on reading lots of good books! Some things should never change. Do you have any big plans for the new year? Gym resolutions that you'll probably abandon in a couple weeks, perhaps? Let me know in the comments! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 470: Holiday Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/20/day-470-holiday-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 470: Holiday Update"/><published>2024-12-21T02:22:52+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T02:22:52+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/20/day-470-holiday-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/20/day-470-holiday-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I decided to take next week off. Last year I basically half-assed it through the holidays, and the posts got understandably little traction anyway with holidays on. I figure Christmas and New Years are best spent with the family (or partying). The next post will be in 2025 ... a year that has always sounded like a year that would be in the future to me. I guess it's already here. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Anyway, happy holidays everyone!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I decided to take next week off. Last year I basically half-assed it through the holidays, and the posts got understandably little traction anyway with holidays on. I figure Christmas and New Years are best spent with the family (or partying). The next post will be in 2025 ... a year that has always sounded like a year that would be in the future to me. I guess it's already here. Anyway, happy holidays everyone! Thank you, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 469: Editors on Editing</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/19/day-469-editors-on-editing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 469: Editors on Editing"/><published>2024-12-20T01:26:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T01:26:10+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/19/day-469-editors-on-editing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/19/day-469-editors-on-editing/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I finally got a good start on this book and man it has already been worth it. They really come out swinging from the first essay about what it even is to be an editor in the first place. Then it swings right into the evolution of the American editor, letters to would-be editors, the necessity (or sometimes lack thereof) and I haven't even gotten to the real meat of the issue like 'what editors look for in a manuscript' or 'editing crime fiction.' This book is certainly a gold mine and I plan on reading an essay a night for a long time. I think it's best consumed in moderation, with plenty of time in between to let the information marinate. There's not much else I can say about this book, seeing as all the editors have already said it. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm happy to say that the last several books I've purchased have all been more than worthwhile. With Christmas coming up, I suppose I'll be having another book haul soon too! I can only hope the streak of great literature continues. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I finally got a good start on this book and man it has already been worth it. They really come out swinging from the first essay about what it even is to be an editor in the first place. Then it swings right into the evolution of the American editor, letters to would-be editors, the necessity (or sometimes lack thereof) and I haven't even gotten to the real meat of the issue like 'what editors look for in a manuscript' or 'editing crime fiction.' This book is certainly a gold mine and I plan on reading an essay a night for a long time. I think it's best consumed in moderation, with plenty of time in between to let the information marinate. There's not much else I can say about this book, seeing as all the editors have already said it. I'm happy to say that the last several books I've purchased have all been more than worthwhile. With Christmas coming up, I suppose I'll be having another book haul soon too! I can only hope the streak of great literature continues. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 468: Horse nor Ass</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/18/day-468-horse-nor-ass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 468: Horse nor Ass"/><published>2024-12-19T03:45:15+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-19T03:45:15+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/18/day-468-horse-nor-ass</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/18/day-468-horse-nor-ass/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Today was one of those days where I just couldn't seem to get much done. I barely even read any of 'Editors on Editing' so I'll have to save my first impressions post for tomorrow. It's been pretty good so far, but I haven't sunk my teeth into it yet. The reason being, I have to admit, is that I got distracted by a rabbit hole again. For some reason I started to wonder about that saying, 'To err is human,' and where it came from, so I looked it up and couldn't stop reading. It comes from a poem called 'An Essay on Criticism,' and though it's one of Alexander Pope's best known works, I think it's so good it might still be under-referenced somehow. Throughout part one, Pope shares his unapologetic thoughts on literary critics, with a healthy dose of criticism of his own. I mean just read this banger of a stanza where he talks about the types of people who can pass for poets and critics:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>Some have at first for wits then poets passed<br/>Turned critics next and proved plain fools at last<br/>Some neither can for wits nor critics pass<br/>As heavy mules are neither horse nor ass.<br/>Those half-learned witlings, numerous in our isle,<br/>As half-formed insects on the banks of Nile<br/>Unfinished things one knows not what to call<br/>Their generation is so equivocal<br/>To tell them would a hundred tongues require,<br/>Or one vain wits that might a hundred tire.</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I guess they didn't mince words back in the day because damn. I've never felt like being horse nor ass is a bad thing, but now I'm wondering if I even qualify as anything other than a heavy mule. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Anyway I should probably get back on it tomorrow, but this was just too funny to pass up.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today was one of those days where I just couldn't seem to get much done. I barely even read any of 'Editors on Editing' so I'll have to save my first impressions post for tomorrow. It's been pretty good so far, but I haven't sunk my teeth into it yet. The reason being, I have to admit, is that I got distracted by a rabbit hole again. For some reason I started to wonder about that saying, 'To err is human,' and where it came from, so I looked it up and couldn't stop reading. It comes from a poem called 'An Essay on Criticism,' and though it's one of Alexander Pope's best known works, I think it's so good it might still be under-referenced somehow. Throughout part one, Pope shares his unapologetic thoughts on literary critics, with a healthy dose of criticism of his own. I mean just read this banger of a stanza where he talks about the types of people who can pass for poets and critics: Some have at first for wits then poets passedTurned critics next and proved plain fools at lastSome neither can for wits nor critics passAs heavy mules are neither horse nor ass.Those half-learned witlings, numerous in our isle,As half-formed insects on the banks of NileUnfinished things one knows not what to callTheir generation is so equivocalTo tell them would a hundred tongues require,Or one vain wits that might a hundred tire. I guess they didn't mince words back in the day because damn. I've never felt like being horse nor ass is a bad thing, but now I'm wondering if I even qualify as anything other than a heavy mule. Anyway I should probably get back on it tomorrow, but this was just too funny to pass up. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 467: Kill Your Darlings</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/17/day-467-kill-your-darlings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 467: Kill Your Darlings"/><published>2024-12-18T02:38:45+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-18T02:38:45+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/17/day-467-kill-your-darlings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/17/day-467-kill-your-darlings/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I removed a big section of 'Jeffries' today and couldn't help but remember that old saying. I think the story is better off for it, but there's a lot of missing information that I'll have to find more creative ways to slip in now. It made me wonder if killing your darlings was always meant to be purely about excising unnecessary pieces of a novel, or if it has some deeper meaning. The fact that I'll have to creatively repurpose my darlings in order to get the same information across gives me some inspiration to continue working. Maybe that was always what the intention was.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley </p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I removed a big section of 'Jeffries' today and couldn't help but remember that old saying. I think the story is better off for it, but there's a lot of missing information that I'll have to find more creative ways to slip in now. It made me wonder if killing your darlings was always meant to be purely about excising unnecessary pieces of a novel, or if it has some deeper meaning. The fact that I'll have to creatively repurpose my darlings in order to get the same information across gives me some inspiration to continue working. Maybe that was always what the intention was. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 466: Jade City</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/16/day-466-jade-city/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 466: Jade City"/><published>2024-12-17T02:28:12+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T02:28:12+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/16/day-466-jade-city</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/16/day-466-jade-city/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It's been a long time since I read a fantasy series quite as gripping as Fonda Lee's Green Bone Saga. Her depiction of the characters and the world flows so smoothly from action to dialogue to internal monologue, and even through large spans of time that I found myself going 'hold on, how on Earth did she do that?' and having to read it back every few pages just to experience it again. Most immediately engaging is the crux of concept, Jade, a mineral that enhances physical ability, perception, and even enables telekinetic power. It exists only on the island nation of Kekon, and gives the series' namesake Green Bones their power, both physically, and as a symbol of status. Two generations have past since they won the war for their independence from the Shotarian Empire. In the intervening time, the clans of Green Bones that once fought together against the Shotarians have been nursing new grudges against one another, and a civil war between the two largest clans is brewing in the capital, Janloon, or Jade City as the foreigners know it. The characters are varied, but most of them come from clan No Peak, one of the two most powerful clans, and are descendants or relations of Kaul Sen, the most famous Green Bone leader from the days of rebellion and imperial rule. Their rivals, The Mountain clan, are a powerful enemy whose leader has a vision of a unified Kekon, under the rule of The Mountain of course. The main conflict stems from their ambitions, but the wider world is obsessed with nation's massive Jade stockpile, the most valuable substance in the world. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Beyond the incredible world building, the character building here is top notch too, with certain character arcs leaving my jaw on the floor. Okay, one in particular. Kaul Lan's arc. If you've read the book, you know what I'm talking about. But all of the characters are engaging in their own way. Lee has this perfect blend of completely logical, yet entirely unexpected character interactions that seem inevitable in hindsight, but you know you never would have seen it coming in million years. It gives the whole story an incredible sense of momentum that never lets up. As if every moment is simultaneously preordained and spontaneously generated. Each character has a firmly grounded perspective that's powerful enough to trick you into forgetting that you either hated them or loved their enemies just minutes ago while reading the previous character's chapters. Even the villains from the Mountain, whose perspective is only shown through dialogue and backstory, are charismatic enough to make you really think about whether clan No Peak is doing the right thing sometimes. Both sides of the conflict are cunning, brutal, and just so refreshingly competent at what they do. When they do make the rare mistake, the consequences are always terrible too. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I could go on for hours about how good this series is, and I'm only halfway through! I think instead of gushing about it any longer, I'm just gonna go finish it.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reviews"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a long time since I read a fantasy series quite as gripping as Fonda Lee's Green Bone Saga. Her depiction of the characters and the world flows so smoothly from action to dialogue to internal monologue, and even through large spans of time that I found myself going 'hold on, how on Earth did she do that?' and having to read it back every few pages just to experience it again. Most immediately engaging is the crux of concept, Jade, a mineral that enhances physical ability, perception, and even enables telekinetic power. It exists only on the island nation of Kekon, and gives the series' namesake Green Bones their power, both physically, and as a symbol of status. Two generations have past since they won the war for their independence from the Shotarian Empire. In the intervening time, the clans of Green Bones that once fought together against the Shotarians have been nursing new grudges against one another, and a civil war between the two largest clans is brewing in the capital, Janloon, or Jade City as the foreigners know it. The characters are varied, but most of them come from clan No Peak, one of the two most powerful clans, and are descendants or relations of Kaul Sen, the most famous Green Bone leader from the days of rebellion and imperial rule. Their rivals, The Mountain clan, are a powerful enemy whose leader has a vision of a unified Kekon, under the rule of The Mountain of course. The main conflict stems from their ambitions, but the wider world is obsessed with nation's massive Jade stockpile, the most valuable substance in the world. Beyond the incredible world building, the character building here is top notch too, with certain character arcs leaving my jaw on the floor. Okay, one in particular. Kaul Lan's arc. If you've read the book, you know what I'm talking about. But all of the characters are engaging in their own way. Lee has this perfect blend of completely logical, yet entirely unexpected character interactions that seem inevitable in hindsight, but you know you never would have seen it coming in million years. It gives the whole story an incredible sense of momentum that never lets up. As if every moment is simultaneously preordained and spontaneously generated. Each character has a firmly grounded perspective that's powerful enough to trick you into forgetting that you either hated them or loved their enemies just minutes ago while reading the previous character's chapters. Even the villains from the Mountain, whose perspective is only shown through dialogue and backstory, are charismatic enough to make you really think about whether clan No Peak is doing the right thing sometimes. Both sides of the conflict are cunning, brutal, and just so refreshingly competent at what they do. When they do make the rare mistake, the consequences are always terrible too. I could go on for hours about how good this series is, and I'm only halfway through! I think instead of gushing about it any longer, I'm just gonna go finish it. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 465: Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/13/day-465-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 465: Progress Update"/><published>2024-12-14T02:05:04+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-14T02:05:04+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/13/day-465-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2024/12/13/day-465-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I did a lot of reading this week, but not as much writing as I'd hoped. I have one of the two scenes I wanted to add to 'Jeffries' ready to go, still working on the other. Other than that, there's not much else to report. Come Monday I'll have a review ready for 'Jade City' and I'll have started on 'Editors on Editing,' which I hope is as interesting as I suspect it will be. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Christmas is right around the corner. The blog may take a bit of a back seat to all the festivities, but I should be able to keep up with it as the holidays pick up steam. I might even do some Christmas themed posts! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I did a lot of reading this week, but not as much writing as I'd hoped. I have one of the two scenes I wanted to add to 'Jeffries' ready to go, still working on the other. Other than that, there's not much else to report. Come Monday I'll have a review ready for 'Jade City' and I'll have started on 'Editors on Editing,' which I hope is as interesting as I suspect it will be. Christmas is right around the corner. The blog may take a bit of a back seat to all the festivities, but I should be able to keep up with it as the holidays pick up steam. I might even do some Christmas themed posts! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>