<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-03T19:29:01+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 489: Third Thumb</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 489: Third Thumb"/><published>2025-01-31T02:49:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T02:49:11+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/30/day-489-third-thumb/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p><a href="https://www.daniclodedesign.com/thethirdthumb">I found something neat today and I thought I'd share. </a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I've always thought it would be cool to have a third thumb. I don't know why. It's probably not very useful if I'm being honest. Like what can you really do with an extra thumb? Unscrew a bottle cap with one hand? Other than that I can't really think of anything. Stupid tricks like that are still enough to make me want one though. Maybe if I'm lucky these things will catch on and I can find one for cheap!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I found something neat today and I thought I'd share. I've always thought it would be cool to have a third thumb. I don't know why. It's probably not very useful if I'm being honest. Like what can you really do with an extra thumb? Unscrew a bottle cap with one hand? Other than that I can't really think of anything. Stupid tricks like that are still enough to make me want one though. Maybe if I'm lucky these things will catch on and I can find one for cheap! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 488: Almost Missed One!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 488: Almost Missed One!"/><published>2025-01-30T03:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-30T03:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/29/day-488-almost-missed-one/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>So I pretty much took the day off on account of my sore throat. It's been pretty bad, but thankfully getting better and not worse. I took some cold medicine with plans to watch some TV and then get some work done ... before passing right out and getting nothing done at all. At least I woke up to get the blog done, but it'll be a shallow one.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think I'm going to take tomorrow off too. I've been sleeping poorly for the past few days and I'm not sure my brain can handle much more restless nights. I'll probably just try to get some sleep while I can.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So I pretty much took the day off on account of my sore throat. It's been pretty bad, but thankfully getting better and not worse. I took some cold medicine with plans to watch some TV and then get some work done ... before passing right out and getting nothing done at all. At least I woke up to get the blog done, but it'll be a shallow one. I think I'm going to take tomorrow off too. I've been sleeping poorly for the past few days and I'm not sure my brain can handle much more restless nights. I'll probably just try to get some sleep while I can. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 487: Locking the Door</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 487: Locking the Door"/><published>2025-01-29T02:18:57+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-29T02:18:57+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/28/day-487-locking-the-door/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I was reminded today of a writing technique I like, sometimes referred to as 'locking the door.' The idea is to take a straightforward conflict and liven things up by throwing a spanner in the works, usually something simpler than the overall conflict that nevertheless adds a lot of suspense. For example ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he pushes through the front door and slams it behind him. <em>The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em></em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It's the most basic story I can come up with. Characters are introduced, there's a clear conflict, the stakes rise a little, and then it's resolved. But it feels really shallow, almost too easy, right? Blink, and you'll miss the whole thing. Generally in fiction (and often in life) problems aren't so easily solved, even simple things. It can be endlessly frustrating when you know something should be pretty straightforward only to encounter one confounding issue after the next. Anybody who has worked on a car or done some DIY knows the pain of a stuck bolt, especially when that's the one bolt between you and the finish line. The flip side to this is that watching someone overcome adversity is gratifying. We tend to love seeing emotional moments after huge problems are resolved, but the issue with these big problems is that they can only be so big on paper. They're chock full of little obstacles that compound together, but nobody wants to read a dissertation about every little thing that goes wrong just to feel something when a character achieves their goals. As ever, the best way to make something feel massive is to imply its size with a pertinent issue. A locked door, in this case. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps closer than ever. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and falls through the door. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>This has a little more tension to it. By drawing the conflict out it seems to escalate, even though one might imagine the bear as equally close in the first and second versions. I don't cover every beat of the man's heart, or the slipperiness of the grass, or the rusty lock, but you get the picture. One pertinent complication is often enough to make the conflict a lot more suspenseful. It can be taken further if you want though. I don't think the solution is to give the man another issue since he has his own already, but there are two characters here. What if the bear has its own stumbling block to overcome?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps behind him. He hears a deep growl of pain and spares a terrified glance over his shoulder. The bear has been caught up in the rose bushes in his garden, tangled as if by barbed wire. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and ... it still won't open! The bear pulls itself out of the thorny bramble and comes roaring forward again, angrier than ever. The man steps back, braces himself, and kicks the door in with a defiant shout. He falls inside and throws himself against the ruined door to brace it. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. After holding it off for what feels like forever, the bear gets bored. A biker passes by on the road beyond and it gets distracted. The man watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief.</em> </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Notice that the two locked doors have compounded. This version is much longer than the others. Every additional problem adds more complexity than the last, more baggage for the writer to handle in the end. Now the man has to solve his locked door, and the bear has to extract itself from the brambles. It also gives me free reign to give the man a harder time too. The story might feel a little sparse without it. The conflict has to keep escalating until it doesn't, and I can't have the protagonist being outdone, so I had him put in some extra effort for more payoff. Kicking down the door is a lot more dramatic than just opening the door, and it paints the man as ultimately more powerful than than the bear. Is that a little ridiculous? Sure. But hey, it's fiction. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I couldn't just wind up with one sentence of the bear shuffling off either. I had to give a little breathing room for the resolution to settle in. The higher the tension, the longer it takes to fall. This story really ought to have some paragraph breaks too. It looks a little bloated, but it's probably fine. I hope it gets my point across about locking the door.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="bears"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="short story"/><category term="tips"/><category term="writing"/><category term="writing-tips"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was reminded today of a writing technique I like, sometimes referred to as 'locking the door.' The idea is to take a straightforward conflict and liven things up by throwing a spanner in the works, usually something simpler than the overall conflict that nevertheless adds a lot of suspense. For example ... A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he pushes through the front door and slams it behind him. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. It's the most basic story I can come up with. Characters are introduced, there's a clear conflict, the stakes rise a little, and then it's resolved. But it feels really shallow, almost too easy, right? Blink, and you'll miss the whole thing. Generally in fiction (and often in life) problems aren't so easily solved, even simple things. It can be endlessly frustrating when you know something should be pretty straightforward only to encounter one confounding issue after the next. Anybody who has worked on a car or done some DIY knows the pain of a stuck bolt, especially when that's the one bolt between you and the finish line. The flip side to this is that watching someone overcome adversity is gratifying. We tend to love seeing emotional moments after huge problems are resolved, but the issue with these big problems is that they can only be so big on paper. They're chock full of little obstacles that compound together, but nobody wants to read a dissertation about every little thing that goes wrong just to feel something when a character achieves their goals. As ever, the best way to make something feel massive is to imply its size with a pertinent issue. A locked door, in this case. A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps closer than ever. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and falls through the door. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. He watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. This has a little more tension to it. By drawing the conflict out it seems to escalate, even though one might imagine the bear as equally close in the first and second versions. I don't cover every beat of the man's heart, or the slipperiness of the grass, or the rusty lock, but you get the picture. One pertinent complication is often enough to make the conflict a lot more suspenseful. It can be taken further if you want though. I don't think the solution is to give the man another issue since he has his own already, but there are two characters here. What if the bear has its own stumbling block to overcome? A man comes barreling around the corner, trampling over his garden towards the front door. He's terrified, too scared to even look over his shoulder at the monstrous bear tumbling after him. With only seconds to spare, he crashes into the front door and turns the handle, but it doesn't budge! He curses and pulls the key ring from his pocket. There must be a hundred of them! He flips through the keys with trembling hands as fast as he can, but he can hear the bear's thunderous footsteps behind him. He hears a deep growl of pain and spares a terrified glance over his shoulder. The bear has been caught up in the rose bushes in his garden, tangled as if by barbed wire. Finally, he finds the right key, forces it into the lock, and ... it still won't open! The bear pulls itself out of the thorny bramble and comes roaring forward again, angrier than ever. The man steps back, braces himself, and kicks the door in with a defiant shout. He falls inside and throws himself against the ruined door to brace it. The bear crashes into the frame just as he gets it shut and nearly takes the whole thing off its hinges. After holding it off for what feels like forever, the bear gets bored. A biker passes by on the road beyond and it gets distracted. The man watches the bear shuffle away through the keyhole and breathes a sigh of relief. Notice that the two locked doors have compounded. This version is much longer than the others. Every additional problem adds more complexity than the last, more baggage for the writer to handle in the end. Now the man has to solve his locked door, and the bear has to extract itself from the brambles. It also gives me free reign to give the man a harder time too. The story might feel a little sparse without it. The conflict has to keep escalating until it doesn't, and I can't have the protagonist being outdone, so I had him put in some extra effort for more payoff. Kicking down the door is a lot more dramatic than just opening the door, and it paints the man as ultimately more powerful than than the bear. Is that a little ridiculous? Sure. But hey, it's fiction. I couldn't just wind up with one sentence of the bear shuffling off either. I had to give a little breathing room for the resolution to settle in. The higher the tension, the longer it takes to fall. This story really ought to have some paragraph breaks too. It looks a little bloated, but it's probably fine. I hope it gets my point across about locking the door. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 486: Quick Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/27/day-486-quick-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 486: Quick Progress Update"/><published>2025-01-28T03:41:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-28T03:41:11+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/27/day-486-quick-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/27/day-486-quick-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Had a terrible day for writing today. I woke up with an awfully sore throat that has been distracting me since I sat down to write. I'm not sure what caused it. Hopefully just a one-off, dry air or something.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Anyway, I'm almost done with the blog setup. I think I'll end up launching it on Monday rather than doing something with it in the middle of the week. Everybody knows that going live on a Friday is an awful idea, so Feb 3 is the date to watch. I'll keep you posted.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Had a terrible day for writing today. I woke up with an awfully sore throat that has been distracting me since I sat down to write. I'm not sure what caused it. Hopefully just a one-off, dry air or something. Anyway, I'm almost done with the blog setup. I think I'll end up launching it on Monday rather than doing something with it in the middle of the week. Everybody knows that going live on a Friday is an awful idea, so Feb 3 is the date to watch. I'll keep you posted. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 485: Blood Music Reread</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/24/day-485-blood-music-reread/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 485: Blood Music Reread"/><published>2025-01-25T04:20:11+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T04:20:11+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/24/day-485-blood-music-reread</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/24/day-485-blood-music-reread/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It's still too cold to do anything enjoyable outside, so I spent all of yesterday rereading one of my favorite sci-fi novels, 'Blood Music' by Greg Bear. I don't usually reread books, but this one is an exception. Here are my thoughts on a second look:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>First of all, it is a really quick read. This time it went by even faster than first read, and I think I love that about the book. It's just so dense. There's not a lot of traditional action scenes, but that doesn't prevent the book from feeling action packed because so much is going on all the time. I think this book really lends itself to a reread because of that.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Unfortunately, the characters stuck out to me as kinda thin on the second pass. They're probably the weakest aspect of the book, and maybe Bear's writing in general. I got the same feeling from 'The Forge of God.' The characters aren't weak or unbelievable, it's just that they feel more like slaves to the plot than actors themselves. A lot of the characters have their problems resolved unsatisfactorily in my opinion. It may just be because both of the books I've read from Bear have been disaster stories though. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The last third of the book I just kinda wanted to be over with. It makes an even bigger departure from the characters I was interested in to focus more on what's happening around the world. The appeal of this part of the novel is, well, the novelty, but on a second read it's just something that has to happen.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The sci-fi elements still hold up extremely well on second viewing. Bear clearly did a ton of research into molecular biology. The best class I ever took was a molecular genetics course that taught me all about how DNA gets transcribed into proteins and structures that build the cell and make life what it is. There's no other sci-fi that goes quite as in depth as 'Blood Music' into this topic as far as I'm aware. Bear's exploration of these concepts is very well-done, and doesn't get in the way of the plot for exposition's sake either. Rereading about main character Vergil's process for creating a computer system within the structure of DNA was the highlight of the book for me. It's so convincing it feels like it should be doable in real life. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm happy to say I still love the book. I'm always afraid to go back and reread or rewatch something and find I've grown too much to like it anymore. I don't think I'll ever outgrow 'Blood Music' though.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="rereading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's still too cold to do anything enjoyable outside, so I spent all of yesterday rereading one of my favorite sci-fi novels, 'Blood Music' by Greg Bear. I don't usually reread books, but this one is an exception. Here are my thoughts on a second look: First of all, it is a really quick read. This time it went by even faster than first read, and I think I love that about the book. It's just so dense. There's not a lot of traditional action scenes, but that doesn't prevent the book from feeling action packed because so much is going on all the time. I think this book really lends itself to a reread because of that. Unfortunately, the characters stuck out to me as kinda thin on the second pass. They're probably the weakest aspect of the book, and maybe Bear's writing in general. I got the same feeling from 'The Forge of God.' The characters aren't weak or unbelievable, it's just that they feel more like slaves to the plot than actors themselves. A lot of the characters have their problems resolved unsatisfactorily in my opinion. It may just be because both of the books I've read from Bear have been disaster stories though. The last third of the book I just kinda wanted to be over with. It makes an even bigger departure from the characters I was interested in to focus more on what's happening around the world. The appeal of this part of the novel is, well, the novelty, but on a second read it's just something that has to happen. The sci-fi elements still hold up extremely well on second viewing. Bear clearly did a ton of research into molecular biology. The best class I ever took was a molecular genetics course that taught me all about how DNA gets transcribed into proteins and structures that build the cell and make life what it is. There's no other sci-fi that goes quite as in depth as 'Blood Music' into this topic as far as I'm aware. Bear's exploration of these concepts is very well-done, and doesn't get in the way of the plot for exposition's sake either. Rereading about main character Vergil's process for creating a computer system within the structure of DNA was the highlight of the book for me. It's so convincing it feels like it should be doable in real life. I'm happy to say I still love the book. I'm always afraid to go back and reread or rewatch something and find I've grown too much to like it anymore. I don't think I'll ever outgrow 'Blood Music' though. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 484: It is Freezing</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/23/day-484-it-is-freezing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 484: It is Freezing"/><published>2025-01-23T18:20:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T18:20:15+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/23/day-484-it-is-freezing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/23/day-484-it-is-freezing/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It has been so cold where I am the past few days and I'm starting to go a little stir crazy hiding inside. The roads have been thoroughly salted, so I felt safe enough to drive out and get some groceries today, but man it's still unpleasant out there. The cold seeps into my room through my window to settle on my brain like a thick blanket and my writing turns to soupy fragmented thoughts that don't make much sense. That's why today I'm writing a cop-out post about how I hate the cold. The snow looks pretty, but I'll still be happier when Spring comes around and I can enjoy some sunshine without having my fingers and toes go numb.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It has been so cold where I am the past few days and I'm starting to go a little stir crazy hiding inside. The roads have been thoroughly salted, so I felt safe enough to drive out and get some groceries today, but man it's still unpleasant out there. The cold seeps into my room through my window to settle on my brain like a thick blanket and my writing turns to soupy fragmented thoughts that don't make much sense. That's why today I'm writing a cop-out post about how I hate the cold. The snow looks pretty, but I'll still be happier when Spring comes around and I can enjoy some sunshine without having my fingers and toes go numb. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 483: Jade Legacy</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/22/day-483-jade-legacy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 483: Jade Legacy"/><published>2025-01-23T03:57:33+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-23T03:57:33+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/22/day-483-jade-legacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/22/day-483-jade-legacy/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Yesterday I finally finished Fonda Lee's 'Greenbone Saga' after having started it almost two months ago. The third book in the series feels very different from the other two, and rather doing a straight up review, I'd like to put some thoughts down about what made 'this last book, 'Jade Legacy,' so different. Be warned, there will probably be plenty of minor spoilers, though I'll try be vague when possible.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The structure was unique. Rather than a strong overarching plot like the other two books (and most books in general), 'Jade Legacy' is comprised of several more minor arcs spaced over the course of twenty years. As ever, there is the imposing threat of No Peak's rival clan, The Mountain, but their rivalry has settled into more of a cold-war style slow burn. Both sides have grown too large to attack each other without tearing their home country to pieces, so instead they strive for economic and political victories at home and in foreign countries. This 'slow war' as it's called in the book mirrors the greater conflicts at large in the rest of the world as technology progresses exponentially. Some of these battles were small, some were character defining, and some even changed the course of the world, but they never felt like they were truly wrapping things up until the very last arc. It felt almost like a sequence of short stories and novellas all written in the same world. Taking this route felt more grounded compared to most fantasy I've read. Like many wars in our world, the rivalry between No Peak and The Mountain has a long, bloody tail rather than an explosive end.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>By placing the main conflict from the previous two books in the back seat, Lee was able to tie up more loose ends than I thought possible. About halfway through I was so overwhelmed by the scope of the story that I had lost track of who all even needed a nice ending. The main characters were always in mind of course, but almost every chapter featured a little anecdote about some minor character from the first or second book that lived happily ever after, got their just desserts, or somehow weaseled away with their life yet again to disappear into the night. My personal favorite was an interlude about the death of Kaul Du, a character who was already dead by the beginning of the story, but often referenced by his children, the main characters.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>On top of this milieu of minor characters, every single main character got wrapped up satisfactorily, which is more than I can say for many books. I keep trying to remember a character I wanted more from, or a plot hole left unfilled, but I can't come up with any. Everyone not only got their ending, but stayed true to themselves right up till the end too. Nobody ever felt like a caricature of what they used to be even though all of them did change in fundamental ways over the course of the story. They all grew so much and left huge impressions on the world around them, and of course on the reader too. My only complaint is that some of the characters I came to love absolutely did not deserve the tragedies that befell them. Every last thread tugged at my heartstrings, but man. Did you have to be so cruel???</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>What's most impressive to me is that even though she spent so much time wrapping up lingering threads, Lee was also able to establish new characters and give them satisfying (if more open ended) conclusions too. She had to do this, or risk creating a world that seems static. Everyone has their legacies to pass on to the next generation, and those kids have their own stories to begin. Lee was able to convey this exceptionally well without sacrificing that satisfaction of having a closed ending. Don't ask me how. I just read it and it still seems impossible. As ever, the world goes on, with or without the characters that shaped how it turns while they lived. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Even though it's not what I expected going in, I fully came around by the end of the book. I love that Lee chose to end the series like this rather than with a more traditional structure, and I'm so impressed that she was able to pull it off. It's like driving an F1 car for half the race, then switching to a minivan that jumps the track and does a road trip across the country and back before crossing the finish line. It shouldn't make any sense, and yet, somehow it all adds up by the time the story is over. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday I finally finished Fonda Lee's 'Greenbone Saga' after having started it almost two months ago. The third book in the series feels very different from the other two, and rather doing a straight up review, I'd like to put some thoughts down about what made 'this last book, 'Jade Legacy,' so different. Be warned, there will probably be plenty of minor spoilers, though I'll try be vague when possible. The structure was unique. Rather than a strong overarching plot like the other two books (and most books in general), 'Jade Legacy' is comprised of several more minor arcs spaced over the course of twenty years. As ever, there is the imposing threat of No Peak's rival clan, The Mountain, but their rivalry has settled into more of a cold-war style slow burn. Both sides have grown too large to attack each other without tearing their home country to pieces, so instead they strive for economic and political victories at home and in foreign countries. This 'slow war' as it's called in the book mirrors the greater conflicts at large in the rest of the world as technology progresses exponentially. Some of these battles were small, some were character defining, and some even changed the course of the world, but they never felt like they were truly wrapping things up until the very last arc. It felt almost like a sequence of short stories and novellas all written in the same world. Taking this route felt more grounded compared to most fantasy I've read. Like many wars in our world, the rivalry between No Peak and The Mountain has a long, bloody tail rather than an explosive end. By placing the main conflict from the previous two books in the back seat, Lee was able to tie up more loose ends than I thought possible. About halfway through I was so overwhelmed by the scope of the story that I had lost track of who all even needed a nice ending. The main characters were always in mind of course, but almost every chapter featured a little anecdote about some minor character from the first or second book that lived happily ever after, got their just desserts, or somehow weaseled away with their life yet again to disappear into the night. My personal favorite was an interlude about the death of Kaul Du, a character who was already dead by the beginning of the story, but often referenced by his children, the main characters. On top of this milieu of minor characters, every single main character got wrapped up satisfactorily, which is more than I can say for many books. I keep trying to remember a character I wanted more from, or a plot hole left unfilled, but I can't come up with any. Everyone not only got their ending, but stayed true to themselves right up till the end too. Nobody ever felt like a caricature of what they used to be even though all of them did change in fundamental ways over the course of the story. They all grew so much and left huge impressions on the world around them, and of course on the reader too. My only complaint is that some of the characters I came to love absolutely did not deserve the tragedies that befell them. Every last thread tugged at my heartstrings, but man. Did you have to be so cruel??? What's most impressive to me is that even though she spent so much time wrapping up lingering threads, Lee was also able to establish new characters and give them satisfying (if more open ended) conclusions too. She had to do this, or risk creating a world that seems static. Everyone has their legacies to pass on to the next generation, and those kids have their own stories to begin. Lee was able to convey this exceptionally well without sacrificing that satisfaction of having a closed ending. Don't ask me how. I just read it and it still seems impossible. As ever, the world goes on, with or without the characters that shaped how it turns while they lived. Even though it's not what I expected going in, I fully came around by the end of the book. I love that Lee chose to end the series like this rather than with a more traditional structure, and I'm so impressed that she was able to pull it off. It's like driving an F1 car for half the race, then switching to a minivan that jumps the track and does a road trip across the country and back before crossing the finish line. It shouldn't make any sense, and yet, somehow it all adds up by the time the story is over. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 482: Writing Conference</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/21/day-482-writing-conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 482: Writing Conference"/><published>2025-01-22T03:07:36+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T03:07:36+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/21/day-482-writing-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/21/day-482-writing-conference/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I'm doing some planning for a writer's conference coming up in March. It's an opportunity to pitch my stories, do some networking, and learn a thing or two about the publishing industry while I'm at it. The conference gives attendees an opportunity to do some one-on-one pitches with agents from a bunch of different publishers, and the only catch is you have to pay a little extra for each one. And by a little, I mean a lot. So before I buy my tickets, I'm doing some research on all the agents that I can buy time with to see which ones are most likely to appreciate my stories. So far I have a list of four. Three agents who specify that they're looking for works similar to my own, and one who owns the publisher that they represent. I'm hoping that last one will be able to connect me to some interested agents even if she doesn't want to represent me herself. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>A couple of other things I need to look into are:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <ol class="wp-block-list"></p> <li>How to write a pitch. It's weird that I haven't done this before, but all my focus has been on query letters. I would guess they're almost the same, but I imagine there's some crucial differences when presenting in person.</li> <p></p> <p></p> <li>Ways I might be able to improve my chances of getting published outside of what I've written. Besides my pitch, I think I'll need other strengths on my side to really win anybody over. The blog will probably go a long way, especially the new version which will be up by the end of the month.</li> <p></ol> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think this will give me some much needed motivation. I'm looking forward to the talks too, but the pitches are what I need to do the most to forward my career. Should be fun!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm doing some planning for a writer's conference coming up in March. It's an opportunity to pitch my stories, do some networking, and learn a thing or two about the publishing industry while I'm at it. The conference gives attendees an opportunity to do some one-on-one pitches with agents from a bunch of different publishers, and the only catch is you have to pay a little extra for each one. And by a little, I mean a lot. So before I buy my tickets, I'm doing some research on all the agents that I can buy time with to see which ones are most likely to appreciate my stories. So far I have a list of four. Three agents who specify that they're looking for works similar to my own, and one who owns the publisher that they represent. I'm hoping that last one will be able to connect me to some interested agents even if she doesn't want to represent me herself. A couple of other things I need to look into are: How to write a pitch. It's weird that I haven't done this before, but all my focus has been on query letters. I would guess they're almost the same, but I imagine there's some crucial differences when presenting in person. Ways I might be able to improve my chances of getting published outside of what I've written. Besides my pitch, I think I'll need other strengths on my side to really win anybody over. The blog will probably go a long way, especially the new version which will be up by the end of the month. I think this will give me some much needed motivation. I'm looking forward to the talks too, but the pitches are what I need to do the most to forward my career. Should be fun! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 481: My Writing Battles Submission</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/20/day-481-my-writing-battles-submission/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 481: My Writing Battles Submission"/><published>2025-01-21T02:31:45+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-21T02:31:45+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/20/day-481-my-writing-battles-submission</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/20/day-481-my-writing-battles-submission/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The writing battles competition was so much fun and so informative for me that I'd like to make a habit out of writing shorter stories. The 1000 word limit gave me such a headache that I think it must be the way to go. It stretched my ability to create a lingering thread as well as compress that thread down into a bite-sized format. Working from a prompt also gave me a lot of inspiration to write something I normally wouldn't. Comedy is a rare genre for me, and it took some serious effort to shake the rust off my brain. I wrote several bite-sized comedies during a phase of mine where I would respond to prompts from r/WritingPrompts, but it had been a long time, and none of those stories were particularly good either. I figure if I'm going to make a habit of these shorter stories, I should go back to responding to those prompts for the exercise. Who knows? Maybe I'll get a great result out of one of them.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Also during my research phase for the competition, I came across a clip that I think saved my story. The prompt I received was to write a comedy with a character who was a habitual drinker, and to include a fossil in some way. What came out was a future news report featuring an archeologist who does a walkthrough of a recently unearthed site from the present day. The jokes grew from the archeologist making fun of our culture, and were all duds. Every last one. Even while writing I knew it wasn't funny at all. While trying to figure out why, I remembered this clip from Bryan Cranston on the Hot Ones show that explains it perfectly:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"> <div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"> https://youtu.be/OXEteCPQcGc?si=a8YHAqj6C9kLQvMO&amp;t=427 </div> </figure> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Since everyone from interviewer to archeologist to reader was in on the joke, it just wasn't funny. That first draft didn't do much for me other than get the structure down. Needing a better way to deliver the punchlines, I tried what Cranston suggested, and made it so that the archeologist and the reporter interviewing him thought that they were investigating something absolutely serious. I kinda knew that's the way it should have been all along anyway, but I was struggling to marry the humor to the serious characters. From their perspective, it was a one-in-a-billion find that might change their understanding of history as they knew it. How can that be funny? The answer is, it isn't funny. Not to the characters anyway, and so it has to be funny to the reader somehow. Which was always the goal of course, but I was struggling to achieve that tastefully.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>In the second draft I had the archeologist make a bunch of incredibly poor deductions about the site he was investigating. This let the reader feel in on the joke, but it didn't really work either because it was so on the nose. Like any good story, I was looking to bring in some subtlety to make the reader feel good for piecing things together themselves. Plus, having the archeologist act like an idiot was in pretty poor taste. It turned the characters into fools. Rather than being a comedic story peppered with jokes, it was made up of nonsensical, uninteresting characters making silly statements. The story itself was a joke.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>So I decided to make not only the archeologist, but also the reporter pretty smart. There are several moments where both of them make perfectly logical assumptions about what they're seeing that the reader nevertheless knows are wrong. I think the biggest breakthrough I had was to not only make them intelligent, but also to imply that their whole society was full of deep thinkers, scientists, and philosophers. No longer fools at all, both characters became a lot more charismatic and likeable. They went from making fun of us to holding us in high esteem even when they shouldn't be<em>. Especially </em>when they shouldn't be. Their inclination to give us the benefit of the doubt at every turn came from a place of borderline naivete that makes us all look bad. They were intelligent enough to make complex deductions from the clues left around the site, but never cynical enough to realize what they were actually looking at. The story still makes fun of us, but not outright. Instead, the society analyzing our own is so much better that they can't even fathom what we were getting up to nowadays. I think that central concept is pretty funny on its own, and a lot of the humor came naturally after making this adjustment.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>For the ending I tried to turn it back around and give the archeologist some deep insights into our culture despite the fact that he had gotten most of the broad strokes very wrong. Ironically, he came full circle into understanding us pretty well. This rounded things out nicely, and though it's hard for me to tell if the jokes landed as intended, I think the story works pretty well. Also, I had some help from friends to gauge the humor. They all seemed to think it was pretty funny. I don't know if it's of a caliber to win the competition, but I'm proud of it anyways. I'll post it here once I get the results back either way. Maybe you guys will think it's funny too.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="comedy"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="humor"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The writing battles competition was so much fun and so informative for me that I'd like to make a habit out of writing shorter stories. The 1000 word limit gave me such a headache that I think it must be the way to go. It stretched my ability to create a lingering thread as well as compress that thread down into a bite-sized format. Working from a prompt also gave me a lot of inspiration to write something I normally wouldn't. Comedy is a rare genre for me, and it took some serious effort to shake the rust off my brain. I wrote several bite-sized comedies during a phase of mine where I would respond to prompts from r/WritingPrompts, but it had been a long time, and none of those stories were particularly good either. I figure if I'm going to make a habit of these shorter stories, I should go back to responding to those prompts for the exercise. Who knows? Maybe I'll get a great result out of one of them. Also during my research phase for the competition, I came across a clip that I think saved my story. The prompt I received was to write a comedy with a character who was a habitual drinker, and to include a fossil in some way. What came out was a future news report featuring an archeologist who does a walkthrough of a recently unearthed site from the present day. The jokes grew from the archeologist making fun of our culture, and were all duds. Every last one. Even while writing I knew it wasn't funny at all. While trying to figure out why, I remembered this clip from Bryan Cranston on the Hot Ones show that explains it perfectly: https://youtu.be/OXEteCPQcGc?si=a8YHAqj6C9kLQvMO&amp;t=427 Since everyone from interviewer to archeologist to reader was in on the joke, it just wasn't funny. That first draft didn't do much for me other than get the structure down. Needing a better way to deliver the punchlines, I tried what Cranston suggested, and made it so that the archeologist and the reporter interviewing him thought that they were investigating something absolutely serious. I kinda knew that's the way it should have been all along anyway, but I was struggling to marry the humor to the serious characters. From their perspective, it was a one-in-a-billion find that might change their understanding of history as they knew it. How can that be funny? The answer is, it isn't funny. Not to the characters anyway, and so it has to be funny to the reader somehow. Which was always the goal of course, but I was struggling to achieve that tastefully. In the second draft I had the archeologist make a bunch of incredibly poor deductions about the site he was investigating. This let the reader feel in on the joke, but it didn't really work either because it was so on the nose. Like any good story, I was looking to bring in some subtlety to make the reader feel good for piecing things together themselves. Plus, having the archeologist act like an idiot was in pretty poor taste. It turned the characters into fools. Rather than being a comedic story peppered with jokes, it was made up of nonsensical, uninteresting characters making silly statements. The story itself was a joke. So I decided to make not only the archeologist, but also the reporter pretty smart. There are several moments where both of them make perfectly logical assumptions about what they're seeing that the reader nevertheless knows are wrong. I think the biggest breakthrough I had was to not only make them intelligent, but also to imply that their whole society was full of deep thinkers, scientists, and philosophers. No longer fools at all, both characters became a lot more charismatic and likeable. They went from making fun of us to holding us in high esteem even when they shouldn't be. Especially when they shouldn't be. Their inclination to give us the benefit of the doubt at every turn came from a place of borderline naivete that makes us all look bad. They were intelligent enough to make complex deductions from the clues left around the site, but never cynical enough to realize what they were actually looking at. The story still makes fun of us, but not outright. Instead, the society analyzing our own is so much better that they can't even fathom what we were getting up to nowadays. I think that central concept is pretty funny on its own, and a lot of the humor came naturally after making this adjustment. For the ending I tried to turn it back around and give the archeologist some deep insights into our culture despite the fact that he had gotten most of the broad strokes very wrong. Ironically, he came full circle into understanding us pretty well. This rounded things out nicely, and though it's hard for me to tell if the jokes landed as intended, I think the story works pretty well. Also, I had some help from friends to gauge the humor. They all seemed to think it was pretty funny. I don't know if it's of a caliber to win the competition, but I'm proud of it anyways. I'll post it here once I get the results back either way. Maybe you guys will think it's funny too. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 480: Word Count Woes Pt. 2</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/17/day-480-word-count-woes-pt-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 480: Word Count Woes Pt. 2"/><published>2025-01-18T02:43:03+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T02:43:03+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/17/day-480-word-count-woes-pt-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/01/17/day-480-word-count-woes-pt-2/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I know I already complained about it this week, but man I cannot seem to get a story within a word count. 1000 words is just such an awkward amount of words somehow. If you've ever run track, it reminds me of running an 800 meter race. You can't really sprint an 800 meter race, like you would a 200, but there's also no room at all to show off your pacing skills, and so it just ends up in this weird middle ground. All the good stuff I want won't quite fit, but there's also not much excuse to leave out pertinent details of spatial awareness and what characters look like. Instead I have to pear those down to one or two lines, just the most defining details that I can include. Some of it I can get away with including in dialogue, but a lot of it goes complete unsaid. I just have to hope that the scene plays out smoothly even with a lack of detail.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And that leads me to the other problem. Multiple scenes is basically impossible. I for one have a hard time generating a compelling beginning, middle, and end in only one scene. Not that any scene I write doesn't have those three things, but usually there's a greater arc going on that actually delivers the payload I'm after. Being limited to 1000 words feels like a test of how much power I can fit into just one scene without much in the way of description, scene setting, backstory, or even characterization. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>In other words, great exercise. Or else, really, really annoying, depending on how you want to look at it.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I know I already complained about it this week, but man I cannot seem to get a story within a word count. 1000 words is just such an awkward amount of words somehow. If you've ever run track, it reminds me of running an 800 meter race. You can't really sprint an 800 meter race, like you would a 200, but there's also no room at all to show off your pacing skills, and so it just ends up in this weird middle ground. All the good stuff I want won't quite fit, but there's also not much excuse to leave out pertinent details of spatial awareness and what characters look like. Instead I have to pear those down to one or two lines, just the most defining details that I can include. Some of it I can get away with including in dialogue, but a lot of it goes complete unsaid. I just have to hope that the scene plays out smoothly even with a lack of detail. And that leads me to the other problem. Multiple scenes is basically impossible. I for one have a hard time generating a compelling beginning, middle, and end in only one scene. Not that any scene I write doesn't have those three things, but usually there's a greater arc going on that actually delivers the payload I'm after. Being limited to 1000 words feels like a test of how much power I can fit into just one scene without much in the way of description, scene setting, backstory, or even characterization. In other words, great exercise. Or else, really, really annoying, depending on how you want to look at it. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>