<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-31T21:18:29+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 531: The Ferryman First Impressions</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/31/day-531-the-ferryman-first-impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 531: The Ferryman First Impressions"/><published>2025-03-31T21:15:22+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-31T21:15:22+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/31/day-531-the-ferryman-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/31/day-531-the-ferryman-first-impressions/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I sank my teeth into 'The Ferryman' by Justin Cronin today, and what struck me immediately is that the prose is really good. Its been a while since I read sci-fi by a seriously evocative writer. Cronin uses flowery language in a tasteful way to imbue ordinary moments with extraordinary visual and emotional appeal. Its almost a literary style and it feels old-fashioned. I actually wasn't certain what time period I was reading until electronics and drones started showing up. I guess that makes sense with the age of the protagonists, who are a bit unusual.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>He uses the strength of his prose to tackle a complex subject in the first chapter, wherein a much older couple than is typical adopts a ward who is nearly an adult already. Cronin's approach makes the rather unusual start appealing a way that's hard to describe. There are also immediate hints of a deeper issue at hand that lend the following scenes a lot more gravitas. I was a little confused about what happened at the end of the first chapter, especially given that I couldn't quite tell if the POV had changed for a while at the beginning of the second chapter, but I nevertheless wanted to continue reading. If I could ask for anything, I'd like some names. So far, there's one character, the young man they adopt, who is only referred to as 'the boy,' over and over and over again. It got on my nerves after a few pages. Just saying.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm excited to see where this one goes because I can already tell its not my typical read even though its sci-fi. Should be fun!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I sank my teeth into 'The Ferryman' by Justin Cronin today, and what struck me immediately is that the prose is really good. Its been a while since I read sci-fi by a seriously evocative writer. Cronin uses flowery language in a tasteful way to imbue ordinary moments with extraordinary visual and emotional appeal. Its almost a literary style and it feels old-fashioned. I actually wasn't certain what time period I was reading until electronics and drones started showing up. I guess that makes sense with the age of the protagonists, who are a bit unusual. He uses the strength of his prose to tackle a complex subject in the first chapter, wherein a much older couple than is typical adopts a ward who is nearly an adult already. Cronin's approach makes the rather unusual start appealing a way that's hard to describe. There are also immediate hints of a deeper issue at hand that lend the following scenes a lot more gravitas. I was a little confused about what happened at the end of the first chapter, especially given that I couldn't quite tell if the POV had changed for a while at the beginning of the second chapter, but I nevertheless wanted to continue reading. If I could ask for anything, I'd like some names. So far, there's one character, the young man they adopt, who is only referred to as 'the boy,' over and over and over again. It got on my nerves after a few pages. Just saying. I'm excited to see where this one goes because I can already tell its not my typical read even though its sci-fi. Should be fun! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 530: Happy Friday</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/28/day-530-happy-friday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 530: Happy Friday"/><published>2025-03-29T01:35:33+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-29T01:35:33+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/28/day-530-happy-friday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/28/day-530-happy-friday/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Another slow day today and not much to report. Even less so since I am posting from my phone thanks to an annoying internet outage at my house. It was sunny outside all day, so I can't imagine the cause. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Just wanted to say I'm glad you made it to the end of the week too!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Another slow day today and not much to report. Even less so since I am posting from my phone thanks to an annoying internet outage at my house. It was sunny outside all day, so I can't imagine the cause. Just wanted to say I'm glad you made it to the end of the week too! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 529: Morphotrophic</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/27/day-529-morphotrophic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 529: Morphotrophic"/><published>2025-03-28T01:07:12+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-28T01:07:12+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/27/day-529-morphotrophic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/27/day-529-morphotrophic/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>This book is, in short, an excellent conceptual piece by an incredibly imaginative author with a well-paced (albeit super weird) plot. I think it might be up there with the strangest books I've ever read, but that's not a bad thing in this case. Author Greg Egan leaned into strangeness of his brand of hard sci-fi with elements of body and biological horror. Its chock full of these disturbing scenes where something wholly bizarre will happen as a consequence of the brilliant conceptual basis. 'Morphotrophic' is set in a world where cells can emigrate at will to other organisms, and even change form based on subtle electrical signals. This one rule results in many otherworldly happenings that often feel all too realistic. Scientists diving deep into cell morphotype research unlock the ability to trigger new morphotypes to form from existing cells, swappers exchange their body parts with other human beings to get the best combinations, and mind-bending experiments reveal new biological truths.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think this book starts off extremely strong with just how weird it is. Its hard not to want to read more when the characters are shedding cells and bathing in ground-up pig to get them back in the very first chapter. The prose can get a little bland as the world building aspects extend their welcome at times, but with such a complex basis, I have to forgive Egan for a lot of the exposition that would normally put me off. The science here is so different that it almost feels like fantasy, although I can't claim it ever broke its own logic, just that the logic was so far reaching it was hard to keep up. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Unfortunately, I didn't find any of the characters especially relatable. I think that put a damper on my enjoyment of what would otherwise have been a top-ten book for me. It was just that the plot inflicted itself on so many of them, even the most powerful characters, that I often felt like everyone and everything was at the mercy of something random happening and derailing any plans that anybody had made. I haven't mentioned many plot specifics because honestly its just too hard to summarize it. There are like five main characters and a long series of flashbacks. The antagonists are mysterious and vague, and among all the other highbrow conceptual stuff its easy to get lost. I also noticed that some of the characters had weirdly calm reactions to very strange things happening, strange even for the characters living in the strange world. This only happened once or twice, its really more of a nitpick, but it pulled me out of things when people started spawning new organisms without much of an internal or external reaction. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Overall, this book has a really strong central pillar that helps it stand out among the crowd, but I had some difficulties along the way too. I'll have to read some more of Egan's works to see how I really feel about his style as a whole. I think its beyond a doubt that anything of his I pick up will have some cool sci-fi going on, but I wonder if any of his books feature characters that are more my speed? Here's hoping!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="science-fiction"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This book is, in short, an excellent conceptual piece by an incredibly imaginative author with a well-paced (albeit super weird) plot. I think it might be up there with the strangest books I've ever read, but that's not a bad thing in this case. Author Greg Egan leaned into strangeness of his brand of hard sci-fi with elements of body and biological horror. Its chock full of these disturbing scenes where something wholly bizarre will happen as a consequence of the brilliant conceptual basis. 'Morphotrophic' is set in a world where cells can emigrate at will to other organisms, and even change form based on subtle electrical signals. This one rule results in many otherworldly happenings that often feel all too realistic. Scientists diving deep into cell morphotype research unlock the ability to trigger new morphotypes to form from existing cells, swappers exchange their body parts with other human beings to get the best combinations, and mind-bending experiments reveal new biological truths. I think this book starts off extremely strong with just how weird it is. Its hard not to want to read more when the characters are shedding cells and bathing in ground-up pig to get them back in the very first chapter. The prose can get a little bland as the world building aspects extend their welcome at times, but with such a complex basis, I have to forgive Egan for a lot of the exposition that would normally put me off. The science here is so different that it almost feels like fantasy, although I can't claim it ever broke its own logic, just that the logic was so far reaching it was hard to keep up. Unfortunately, I didn't find any of the characters especially relatable. I think that put a damper on my enjoyment of what would otherwise have been a top-ten book for me. It was just that the plot inflicted itself on so many of them, even the most powerful characters, that I often felt like everyone and everything was at the mercy of something random happening and derailing any plans that anybody had made. I haven't mentioned many plot specifics because honestly its just too hard to summarize it. There are like five main characters and a long series of flashbacks. The antagonists are mysterious and vague, and among all the other highbrow conceptual stuff its easy to get lost. I also noticed that some of the characters had weirdly calm reactions to very strange things happening, strange even for the characters living in the strange world. This only happened once or twice, its really more of a nitpick, but it pulled me out of things when people started spawning new organisms without much of an internal or external reaction. Overall, this book has a really strong central pillar that helps it stand out among the crowd, but I had some difficulties along the way too. I'll have to read some more of Egan's works to see how I really feel about his style as a whole. I think its beyond a doubt that anything of his I pick up will have some cool sci-fi going on, but I wonder if any of his books feature characters that are more my speed? Here's hoping! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 528: Short Progress Update</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/26/day-528-short-progress-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 528: Short Progress Update"/><published>2025-03-27T02:15:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T02:15:01+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/26/day-528-short-progress-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/26/day-528-short-progress-update/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I've had a pretty slow week of incremental progress on 'Jeffries.' Besides that, I submitted some old stories for publication after some touchups here and there, but I haven't heard anything back on any of those. Of course if any of them get published I'll be gushing about it here the second I sign the contract.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The only other thing I've been doing is a lot of reading. I still have 'The Ferryman' by Justin Cronin and 'Pushing Ice' by Alastair Reynolds on my list by the way. I got distracted by other good books, but the book haul remains in progress! I'm hoping to finish up 'Morphotrophic' tomorrow and jump right into the next one. Since 'Pushing Ice' is a series, I think I'll read 'The Ferryman' first so I won't be tempted into another long reading before I finish the haul. Should be a lot of fun!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've had a pretty slow week of incremental progress on 'Jeffries.' Besides that, I submitted some old stories for publication after some touchups here and there, but I haven't heard anything back on any of those. Of course if any of them get published I'll be gushing about it here the second I sign the contract. The only other thing I've been doing is a lot of reading. I still have 'The Ferryman' by Justin Cronin and 'Pushing Ice' by Alastair Reynolds on my list by the way. I got distracted by other good books, but the book haul remains in progress! I'm hoping to finish up 'Morphotrophic' tomorrow and jump right into the next one. Since 'Pushing Ice' is a series, I think I'll read 'The Ferryman' first so I won't be tempted into another long reading before I finish the haul. Should be a lot of fun! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 527: Late Night Post!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/25/day-527-late-night-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 527: Late Night Post!"/><published>2025-03-26T03:12:10+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T03:12:10+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/25/day-527-late-night-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/25/day-527-late-night-post/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I may or may not have let a nap get carried away with me. It was only supposed to be a couple of hours, I swear! I had written a scene in 'Jeffries' and gotten a big errand done too, so I figured, what's the harm? I'll get that blog done after I wake up and get some dinner. Then my alarm woke me up like eight hours later. Isn't that how it always goes?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Anyways, now I'm going to put on my cool nighttime playlist and stare at a screen for another two hours while I try to come up with something cool to write. I figure there's not much else to do in the late hours of the night. Its either that or head to my kitchen and scrounge for scraps like a rat. I think its the best part and the worst part of being a writer. I can get my work done at any time. But also, I can get my job done at literally any time and so there's no good excuse after an elongated nap steals half a day away. Hopefully I can make it all worthwhile with another couple thousand words.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Wish me luck!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I may or may not have let a nap get carried away with me. It was only supposed to be a couple of hours, I swear! I had written a scene in 'Jeffries' and gotten a big errand done too, so I figured, what's the harm? I'll get that blog done after I wake up and get some dinner. Then my alarm woke me up like eight hours later. Isn't that how it always goes? Anyways, now I'm going to put on my cool nighttime playlist and stare at a screen for another two hours while I try to come up with something cool to write. I figure there's not much else to do in the late hours of the night. Its either that or head to my kitchen and scrounge for scraps like a rat. I think its the best part and the worst part of being a writer. I can get my work done at any time. But also, I can get my job done at literally any time and so there's no good excuse after an elongated nap steals half a day away. Hopefully I can make it all worthwhile with another couple thousand words. Wish me luck! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 526: Morphotrophic First Impressions</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/24/day-526-morphotrophic-first-impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 526: Morphotrophic First Impressions"/><published>2025-03-24T16:17:55+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-24T16:17:55+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/24/day-526-morphotrophic-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/24/day-526-morphotrophic-first-impressions/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I saw a book on sale that fit well with my previous book haul's theme (contemporary sci-fi), and I couldn't resist buying it right away. They say not to judge a book by its cover, and if the adage has any truth to it, that probably means judging a book by its title alone is even worse right? Well I was willing to give this one a shot from the second I tried to wrap my brain around the word 'Morphotrophic' on the cover page, and I'm so glad I did.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>This is a hard sci-fi novel by Greg Egan, an Australian author who I somehow hadn't heard of before. He's published a ton of novels and won a bunch of awards too, plus he's right up my alley with his high concept plots. Yet more evidence that there's always a hole in my reading list no matter how hard I look. I can't believe I've been missing out. 'Morphotrophic' has such a unique vibe, with elements of psychological and biological horror, but also a haunting beauty inheriting from the powerful concept at the core of the novel.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It's hard to even approach the concept at hand. The novel does it better than I ever could, but the gist is, in the world of 'Morphotrophic,' all biological organisms have cells that evolved to migrate around rather than stay in one place. Cells share a shape memory with each other to form different organisms from humans all the way down to a nematode. Egan takes this alternate evolutionary path to creative places by imagining what kinds of adaptations would be useful to cells such as these, and what kinds of adaptations could cause problems. The opening scene of a young girl waking in her bed to find that her flesh is abandoning her sets the uncanny, and somewhat disturbing tone of the book. Egan immediately doubles down too by introducing a second character who engages in 'swapper culture,' illegal underground cell swapping. There's a whole culture built around exchanging cells to find the best combination for one's own body. The other plot line develops into more of a research focused thriller, another plot archetype that's right up my alley after having read 'Blood Over Bright Haven.'</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It keeps getting weirder too, that's literally just the beginning of the story. I haven't wrapped my head around what happens next well enough to express any coherent thoughts, other than that its not your everyday adventure. It's some really trippy sci-fi, but unlike a lot of the harder stuff, it isn't too dry either. Egan does wax poetic a little long at times, but its easy to let him get away with it when what's on the page is just so unusual and fresh. I hope the rest of the book keeps innovating on the concept as creatively as it begins.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="morphotrophic"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="science-fiction"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I saw a book on sale that fit well with my previous book haul's theme (contemporary sci-fi), and I couldn't resist buying it right away. They say not to judge a book by its cover, and if the adage has any truth to it, that probably means judging a book by its title alone is even worse right? Well I was willing to give this one a shot from the second I tried to wrap my brain around the word 'Morphotrophic' on the cover page, and I'm so glad I did. This is a hard sci-fi novel by Greg Egan, an Australian author who I somehow hadn't heard of before. He's published a ton of novels and won a bunch of awards too, plus he's right up my alley with his high concept plots. Yet more evidence that there's always a hole in my reading list no matter how hard I look. I can't believe I've been missing out. 'Morphotrophic' has such a unique vibe, with elements of psychological and biological horror, but also a haunting beauty inheriting from the powerful concept at the core of the novel. It's hard to even approach the concept at hand. The novel does it better than I ever could, but the gist is, in the world of 'Morphotrophic,' all biological organisms have cells that evolved to migrate around rather than stay in one place. Cells share a shape memory with each other to form different organisms from humans all the way down to a nematode. Egan takes this alternate evolutionary path to creative places by imagining what kinds of adaptations would be useful to cells such as these, and what kinds of adaptations could cause problems. The opening scene of a young girl waking in her bed to find that her flesh is abandoning her sets the uncanny, and somewhat disturbing tone of the book. Egan immediately doubles down too by introducing a second character who engages in 'swapper culture,' illegal underground cell swapping. There's a whole culture built around exchanging cells to find the best combination for one's own body. The other plot line develops into more of a research focused thriller, another plot archetype that's right up my alley after having read 'Blood Over Bright Haven.' It keeps getting weirder too, that's literally just the beginning of the story. I haven't wrapped my head around what happens next well enough to express any coherent thoughts, other than that its not your everyday adventure. It's some really trippy sci-fi, but unlike a lot of the harder stuff, it isn't too dry either. Egan does wax poetic a little long at times, but its easy to let him get away with it when what's on the page is just so unusual and fresh. I hope the rest of the book keeps innovating on the concept as creatively as it begins. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 525: The Gods Have Not Died in Vain</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/21/day-525-the-gods-have-not-died-in-vain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 525: The Gods Have Not Died in Vain"/><published>2025-03-22T01:27:29+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-22T01:27:29+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/21/day-525-the-gods-have-not-died-in-vain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/21/day-525-the-gods-have-not-died-in-vain/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The third story in 'The Gods Will Not Be Slain' series has thrown me for a bit of a loop. It's a thought provoking story in more ways than one, and not at all what I was expecting. I like having my expectations defied, especially when a story goes above and beyond, but I'm not sure how I feel about it overall. I'll give a quick synopsis first.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story feels as ephemeral as the mind of the machine intelligence that pervades Maddie's life throughout, and most of it takes place from just one little room. First it immediately resolves a cliff hanger from the second story by introducing Mist, Maddie's cloud-born sister. She is a child of David, and possibly many others, who has inherited their traits, including David's love of Maddie and Ellen. The structure of the story is built around Maddie getting to know Mist as they strive to keep a new threat from rising. After burying the last vestiges of David, Mist informs Maddie that a new company called Everlasting has been scouring what networks remain after the world wars have cooled, searching for pieces of the old gods that brought civilization to its knees. Its obvious that the mysterious CEO, Adam Ever, is trying to piece together a new way to upload people's minds to the cloud. Their systems are bulletproof too. Mist can't seem to hack her way in to stop them but she does get ahold of all the scraps of code they've compiled and sends them to Maddie.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Maddie, meanwhile, studies the scraps and tries to piece together what it was that made the gods turn on the world they left behind. Again, all this takes place from one room. Mist gives Maddie regular news reports relating to Everlasting's progress and the general state of the world beyond. Ellen has been working as an advisor to the city of Boston, and also serves as an inlet so the reader can learn new things about the world. Basically everyone is starving and civilization is on the brink of collapse. Its just not possible to support billions of human lives without the advanced infrastructure destroyed in the wars. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The milieu and the inquiry into Everlasting and the gods are the plot threads that drive the story forward. The relationship between Maddie and Mist ties back in when Maddie starts buying up robot parts to build Mist a body so she can interact with the 'real world.' Mist however, doesn't seem to have much of an interest. The body she builds is a cute little rover with a bunch of sensors and mechanical arms, and very neat. Maddie built it to assuage the crippling nostalgia for the real world that she discovers in the leftover bits of code. She comes to realize that this nostalgia is what drove Chanda and the others to destroy the world (a point I'm not completely clear on, but I'll get to that). Mist however does not have this critical flaw. Her body extends into every machine and network on the planet, and since she never lived a corporeal life, she feels no lost connection to the world. The small addendum that Maddie built for her is inconsequential by comparison the vast legion of machines and sensors that Mist can take advantage of. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>In the end, Adam Ever makes contact with Mist. And yes, it kinda does just come out of nowhere. Through Mist, he meets Maddie, and explains that the world is too fragile to support mankind's ambitions any longer, and that his ultimate goal is to upload as many human minds as possible so that humanity might live on in the cloud. He overcame the flaw by willingly destroying his healthy body in the upload process, and to save the world, everybody else will have to join him. The end.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The structure is ... pretty weird, honestly. The antagonist is really slippery, and by that I mean, hard to identify. If I had to classify this story, I'd call it a man vs self. From how I'm interpreting this, I think Maddie is in the process of overcoming her own nostalgia for the world while still living in it. Not a single scene takes place outside of her house, indicative of how withdrawn she already is. Adam Ever is also not really the bad guy despite serving the role for most of the story. The natural conclusion after their meeting would be for Maddie to upload her mind and escape from the limitations of the human world (in my opinion) although the end is left more open than that. If I could change any one thing about the story, it would be to introduce Adam Ever much earlier in the series. His turnabout into a figure that's not actually trying to destroy the world, but save it, would be a lot stronger if he had existed for more than, like, ten pages. There are other things I would change too though.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I think the main goal of this story was provoke deep thought about the corporeal nature of human existence. It feels like the point that Liu was trying to get across all along, and in that way, it resolves the other two stories pretty well. I can't help but feel wanting for a more solid conclusion for Maddie, Ellen, and Mist though. I guess that must be my own nostalgia for corporeal existence showing. I never got got much of a sense of rising action or stakes in Maddie's personal life (though the world is clearly going downhill fast), and her relationship with Mist is pretty tragic since they can't ever see eye to eye by nature of their existence. Ellen's plot felt forgotten by the end, but all she really did was inform Maddie about the world anyway. She didn't even interact with Mist once, come to think of it. Shouldn't she want to meet her dead husband's daughter?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm left feeling hollow at the end of this one, but maybe that's what he was going for. It reminds me a lot of Phillip K Dick's stories actually. The plot just kinda happens and you're left to make sense of it after the fact rather than in the moment. I felt that a lot of the heavy lifting of the story was left to me the reader rather than the writer. It makes it feel thought provoking to be sure, but also meandering, and a little confusing. Its hard to tell what the next step is at any given moment, even compared to the previous two stories in the series. That's not to say it wasn't worth a read. Its just not your typical plot is all.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="horror"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The third story in 'The Gods Will Not Be Slain' series has thrown me for a bit of a loop. It's a thought provoking story in more ways than one, and not at all what I was expecting. I like having my expectations defied, especially when a story goes above and beyond, but I'm not sure how I feel about it overall. I'll give a quick synopsis first. The story feels as ephemeral as the mind of the machine intelligence that pervades Maddie's life throughout, and most of it takes place from just one little room. First it immediately resolves a cliff hanger from the second story by introducing Mist, Maddie's cloud-born sister. She is a child of David, and possibly many others, who has inherited their traits, including David's love of Maddie and Ellen. The structure of the story is built around Maddie getting to know Mist as they strive to keep a new threat from rising. After burying the last vestiges of David, Mist informs Maddie that a new company called Everlasting has been scouring what networks remain after the world wars have cooled, searching for pieces of the old gods that brought civilization to its knees. Its obvious that the mysterious CEO, Adam Ever, is trying to piece together a new way to upload people's minds to the cloud. Their systems are bulletproof too. Mist can't seem to hack her way in to stop them but she does get ahold of all the scraps of code they've compiled and sends them to Maddie. Maddie, meanwhile, studies the scraps and tries to piece together what it was that made the gods turn on the world they left behind. Again, all this takes place from one room. Mist gives Maddie regular news reports relating to Everlasting's progress and the general state of the world beyond. Ellen has been working as an advisor to the city of Boston, and also serves as an inlet so the reader can learn new things about the world. Basically everyone is starving and civilization is on the brink of collapse. Its just not possible to support billions of human lives without the advanced infrastructure destroyed in the wars. The milieu and the inquiry into Everlasting and the gods are the plot threads that drive the story forward. The relationship between Maddie and Mist ties back in when Maddie starts buying up robot parts to build Mist a body so she can interact with the 'real world.' Mist however, doesn't seem to have much of an interest. The body she builds is a cute little rover with a bunch of sensors and mechanical arms, and very neat. Maddie built it to assuage the crippling nostalgia for the real world that she discovers in the leftover bits of code. She comes to realize that this nostalgia is what drove Chanda and the others to destroy the world (a point I'm not completely clear on, but I'll get to that). Mist however does not have this critical flaw. Her body extends into every machine and network on the planet, and since she never lived a corporeal life, she feels no lost connection to the world. The small addendum that Maddie built for her is inconsequential by comparison the vast legion of machines and sensors that Mist can take advantage of. In the end, Adam Ever makes contact with Mist. And yes, it kinda does just come out of nowhere. Through Mist, he meets Maddie, and explains that the world is too fragile to support mankind's ambitions any longer, and that his ultimate goal is to upload as many human minds as possible so that humanity might live on in the cloud. He overcame the flaw by willingly destroying his healthy body in the upload process, and to save the world, everybody else will have to join him. The end. The structure is ... pretty weird, honestly. The antagonist is really slippery, and by that I mean, hard to identify. If I had to classify this story, I'd call it a man vs self. From how I'm interpreting this, I think Maddie is in the process of overcoming her own nostalgia for the world while still living in it. Not a single scene takes place outside of her house, indicative of how withdrawn she already is. Adam Ever is also not really the bad guy despite serving the role for most of the story. The natural conclusion after their meeting would be for Maddie to upload her mind and escape from the limitations of the human world (in my opinion) although the end is left more open than that. If I could change any one thing about the story, it would be to introduce Adam Ever much earlier in the series. His turnabout into a figure that's not actually trying to destroy the world, but save it, would be a lot stronger if he had existed for more than, like, ten pages. There are other things I would change too though. I think the main goal of this story was provoke deep thought about the corporeal nature of human existence. It feels like the point that Liu was trying to get across all along, and in that way, it resolves the other two stories pretty well. I can't help but feel wanting for a more solid conclusion for Maddie, Ellen, and Mist though. I guess that must be my own nostalgia for corporeal existence showing. I never got got much of a sense of rising action or stakes in Maddie's personal life (though the world is clearly going downhill fast), and her relationship with Mist is pretty tragic since they can't ever see eye to eye by nature of their existence. Ellen's plot felt forgotten by the end, but all she really did was inform Maddie about the world anyway. She didn't even interact with Mist once, come to think of it. Shouldn't she want to meet her dead husband's daughter? I'm left feeling hollow at the end of this one, but maybe that's what he was going for. It reminds me a lot of Phillip K Dick's stories actually. The plot just kinda happens and you're left to make sense of it after the fact rather than in the moment. I felt that a lot of the heavy lifting of the story was left to me the reader rather than the writer. It makes it feel thought provoking to be sure, but also meandering, and a little confusing. Its hard to tell what the next step is at any given moment, even compared to the previous two stories in the series. That's not to say it wasn't worth a read. Its just not your typical plot is all. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 524: All Systems Red</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/20/day-524-all-systems-red/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 524: All Systems Red"/><published>2025-03-21T01:33:58+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T01:33:58+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/20/day-524-all-systems-red</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/20/day-524-all-systems-red/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Between the stories in 'The Hidden Girl,' I decided to give 'All Systems Red,' the first book in the Murderbot Diaries series a try, and boy did it grab me. I could not put this book down. It is an action-packed little thriller with a deeply immersive narrator and a ton of juicy sci-fi elements. In other words, everything I love to see in a story. There's not too much to this book since it is a novella, but it held my attention well enough to keep me reading straight through to the end in a single sitting. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The narrator is Murderbot, a partially organic security robot that has been rented to a team of surveyors investigating an alien planet. For a guy designed to shoot and get shot at and not much else, he has a surprising amount of heart. He became a rogue unit after hacking into the governor in his head that would usually force him to follow company protocols to the letter. This gives him a huge degree of freedom compared to his chilly counterparts. Naturally, as a guy who works a boring security job for a living, he spends a lot of his free time watching hundreds of hours worth of soap operas from the entertainment stream coming in from a company satellite whenever he has a little downtime. He's relatable in a depressingly funny way, poking fun at the corporate robots that already exist in our society. He grows a lot over the course of the story, and provides a strong backbone for the reader to experience the plot.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>When the survey team Murderbot is assigned to protect realizes that another company on the other side of the planet has gone dark, they can't help but go investigate. An accident in the intro of the novel wherein Murderbot saves a few members of the survey team has already tipped them off that this is not your usual security bot. The prospect of being discovered terrifies him however. If they realize that he's a rogue unit and report that back to the company, he may be decommissioned, or worse, turned into a laboratory experiment. Surprisingly, the humans don't seem to be entirely unsympathetic to this emotional machine though. This adds a great layer of suspense that carries the plot through in the slow moments, and heightens the tension in the tense combat scenes where Murderbot has to trust his allies. And yes, as it turns out, Murderbot has to do some murdering to protect his new favorite humans from the competition. The planet has a secret that another survey team does not want getting out, and they'll use any means necessary to keep that secret for themselves. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I thought the characters fell a little flat though. In fact, I barely remember their names. They serve a useful plot purpose in that Murderbot comes to enjoy their company and that gives him something to strive towards, but other than that, I didn't get any sense of character progression from them at all. The antagonists are even thinner. They kinda just have a half-assed plan to take the planet for themselves, and that's really it. The star of the show is certainly the titular character. It gets away with it because of how fun it is to be in Murderbot's head, but I still have to call em' like I see em'. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thankfully, he carried my interest as hard as he carried the survey team on his back. He's got some really cool features like his regenerating organic parts, the feed in his head that lets him connect to all kinds of different computer systems, and his integrated weapons and reconnaissance systems that pop up time and again throughout the story. His backstory is pretty cool too, and there's a lot of room for growth in a (painfully) relatable way. He's socially stunted, but also weirdly charming at times too. I would love to read the rest of this series sometime just to see how Murderbot progresses as he gains more and more freedom, and there's even a new show on Apple TV that just came out this month. If you do end up enjoying this character, there is plenty of good content surrounding him.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Despite its flaws, I thought this was a fun little read with a cool and compelling protagonist. I highly recommend you give this a try at some point.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="science-fiction"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Between the stories in 'The Hidden Girl,' I decided to give 'All Systems Red,' the first book in the Murderbot Diaries series a try, and boy did it grab me. I could not put this book down. It is an action-packed little thriller with a deeply immersive narrator and a ton of juicy sci-fi elements. In other words, everything I love to see in a story. There's not too much to this book since it is a novella, but it held my attention well enough to keep me reading straight through to the end in a single sitting. The narrator is Murderbot, a partially organic security robot that has been rented to a team of surveyors investigating an alien planet. For a guy designed to shoot and get shot at and not much else, he has a surprising amount of heart. He became a rogue unit after hacking into the governor in his head that would usually force him to follow company protocols to the letter. This gives him a huge degree of freedom compared to his chilly counterparts. Naturally, as a guy who works a boring security job for a living, he spends a lot of his free time watching hundreds of hours worth of soap operas from the entertainment stream coming in from a company satellite whenever he has a little downtime. He's relatable in a depressingly funny way, poking fun at the corporate robots that already exist in our society. He grows a lot over the course of the story, and provides a strong backbone for the reader to experience the plot. When the survey team Murderbot is assigned to protect realizes that another company on the other side of the planet has gone dark, they can't help but go investigate. An accident in the intro of the novel wherein Murderbot saves a few members of the survey team has already tipped them off that this is not your usual security bot. The prospect of being discovered terrifies him however. If they realize that he's a rogue unit and report that back to the company, he may be decommissioned, or worse, turned into a laboratory experiment. Surprisingly, the humans don't seem to be entirely unsympathetic to this emotional machine though. This adds a great layer of suspense that carries the plot through in the slow moments, and heightens the tension in the tense combat scenes where Murderbot has to trust his allies. And yes, as it turns out, Murderbot has to do some murdering to protect his new favorite humans from the competition. The planet has a secret that another survey team does not want getting out, and they'll use any means necessary to keep that secret for themselves. I thought the characters fell a little flat though. In fact, I barely remember their names. They serve a useful plot purpose in that Murderbot comes to enjoy their company and that gives him something to strive towards, but other than that, I didn't get any sense of character progression from them at all. The antagonists are even thinner. They kinda just have a half-assed plan to take the planet for themselves, and that's really it. The star of the show is certainly the titular character. It gets away with it because of how fun it is to be in Murderbot's head, but I still have to call em' like I see em'. Thankfully, he carried my interest as hard as he carried the survey team on his back. He's got some really cool features like his regenerating organic parts, the feed in his head that lets him connect to all kinds of different computer systems, and his integrated weapons and reconnaissance systems that pop up time and again throughout the story. His backstory is pretty cool too, and there's a lot of room for growth in a (painfully) relatable way. He's socially stunted, but also weirdly charming at times too. I would love to read the rest of this series sometime just to see how Murderbot progresses as he gains more and more freedom, and there's even a new show on Apple TV that just came out this month. If you do end up enjoying this character, there is plenty of good content surrounding him. Despite its flaws, I thought this was a fun little read with a cool and compelling protagonist. I highly recommend you give this a try at some point. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 523: The Gods Will Not Be Slain</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/19/day-523-the-gods-will-not-be-slain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 523: The Gods Will Not Be Slain"/><published>2025-03-20T01:26:46+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T01:26:46+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/19/day-523-the-gods-will-not-be-slain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/19/day-523-the-gods-will-not-be-slain/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Continuing Ken Liu's 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series, the second story is a lot more action focused. Again I'll be mostly comparing this to the TV adaptation, 'Pantheon,' and this one has some really interesting contrasts that arise from the difference in medium.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Sometimes, the story read almost as if poking fun at the way the show portrays the UIs fighting each other in a virtual realm. The show uses a ton of cool animation to portray how the gods might fight each other, usually from the perspective of Maddie's virtual reality setup. The stories take a different approach though, and are a lot more vague and realistic, but because of that realism, they make the show seem a little hokey by comparison. It's kinda funny sometimes.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>One of my favorite moments comes when Maddie's father David and another UI named Vinod Chanda are going at each other. Chanda, unlike in the show, is a straight-up warmonger without any redeeming qualities. He's the primary antagonist of the second story, and wants nothing more than to watch the world burn for how humans turned him into a machine intelligence. To that end, he and several other violent UIs have been starting conventional wars between destabilized nations by cutting off power and other utilities, sending the world spiraling. David and has been fighting him tooth and nail across all digital fronts to prevent him from getting his hands on the nuclear codes he'll need to wipe out all life on the planet. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And unfortunately, he's winning. Chanda takes out one of David's allies, Laurie Lowell (who I was bummed to find out that Maddie never actually meets in the story), and then goes after David. Its hard fought, but without Laurie's help, David can't hold off Chanda's onslaught.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Here's an earlier quote that gives some insight into how the UIs fight each other.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>But wars among the gods happened in a matter of nanoseconds. Within the darkness of the memory inside some servermissile command, power grid, stock exchange, or even an ancient inventory systemthe programs slashed and hacked at each other, escalating privileges, modifying stacks, exploiting system vulnerabilities, masking themselves as other programs, overflowing buffers, overwriting memory locations, sabotaging each other like viruses. Maddie was a good enough programmer to at least understand that in such a war, the need to reach over the network for some piece of data could mean a delay of millisecondsan eternity in the context of the gigahertz clock cycles of modern processors</em>.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Maddie makes a roadtrip with her mother to tearfully resurrect her father by using the vestiges of David that have been running on the Logorhythms server he was originally installed on. To her horror though, she discovers that she's accidentally brought Chanda right to David by means of a tracking virus he implanted in David's code during their earlier confrontation. After a quick back-and-forth, David makes his final stand as Maddie watches from the physical world. This is where some of the unintentional humor begins.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>Unlike the movies, there wasnt going to be some fancy graphical gauge showing her what was happening in the ether.</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That and the earlier explanation are pretty much all you get. Its much more focused on the emotional stakes for Maddie. It's pretty cool to see the veil of calm that falls over the room, knowing that the battle going on just right there in those computers could end the world. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Compare this to the equivalent scene in the show though ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"> <div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper"> https://youtu.be/xlJIaa2ZHA4?si=c2GI6_Ntz_0CVwy_ </div> </figure> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Which is a five-minute long, fully choreographed and animated fight scene. There's just a lot more going on, and it's funny how the story avoids this kinda tropey virtual fight scene by leaning into a human character's perspective.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>For all the extra bells and whistles in the show, Chanda doesn't get to drop this epic line though:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p><em>"These wars are too slow. Ive made up my mind, even if I must burn with the world. Its time for the nukes."</em></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I won't spoil it any more than I have. The story is pretty good, but what's missing is actually the main antagonist of the show, Stephen Holstrom, the pioneer who invented the technology to upload human minds to the cloud in the first place. I'm not sure how he'll be handled in the third story, but it seems like a pretty tight time constraint to explain who begot all this violence and why without even having mentioned him in the first two-thirds of the story. I'm excited to see where it goes though.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Continuing Ken Liu's 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series, the second story is a lot more action focused. Again I'll be mostly comparing this to the TV adaptation, 'Pantheon,' and this one has some really interesting contrasts that arise from the difference in medium. Sometimes, the story read almost as if poking fun at the way the show portrays the UIs fighting each other in a virtual realm. The show uses a ton of cool animation to portray how the gods might fight each other, usually from the perspective of Maddie's virtual reality setup. The stories take a different approach though, and are a lot more vague and realistic, but because of that realism, they make the show seem a little hokey by comparison. It's kinda funny sometimes. One of my favorite moments comes when Maddie's father David and another UI named Vinod Chanda are going at each other. Chanda, unlike in the show, is a straight-up warmonger without any redeeming qualities. He's the primary antagonist of the second story, and wants nothing more than to watch the world burn for how humans turned him into a machine intelligence. To that end, he and several other violent UIs have been starting conventional wars between destabilized nations by cutting off power and other utilities, sending the world spiraling. David and has been fighting him tooth and nail across all digital fronts to prevent him from getting his hands on the nuclear codes he'll need to wipe out all life on the planet. And unfortunately, he's winning. Chanda takes out one of David's allies, Laurie Lowell (who I was bummed to find out that Maddie never actually meets in the story), and then goes after David. Its hard fought, but without Laurie's help, David can't hold off Chanda's onslaught. Here's an earlier quote that gives some insight into how the UIs fight each other. But wars among the gods happened in a matter of nanoseconds. Within the darkness of the memory inside some servermissile command, power grid, stock exchange, or even an ancient inventory systemthe programs slashed and hacked at each other, escalating privileges, modifying stacks, exploiting system vulnerabilities, masking themselves as other programs, overflowing buffers, overwriting memory locations, sabotaging each other like viruses. Maddie was a good enough programmer to at least understand that in such a war, the need to reach over the network for some piece of data could mean a delay of millisecondsan eternity in the context of the gigahertz clock cycles of modern processors. Maddie makes a roadtrip with her mother to tearfully resurrect her father by using the vestiges of David that have been running on the Logorhythms server he was originally installed on. To her horror though, she discovers that she's accidentally brought Chanda right to David by means of a tracking virus he implanted in David's code during their earlier confrontation. After a quick back-and-forth, David makes his final stand as Maddie watches from the physical world. This is where some of the unintentional humor begins. Unlike the movies, there wasnt going to be some fancy graphical gauge showing her what was happening in the ether. That and the earlier explanation are pretty much all you get. Its much more focused on the emotional stakes for Maddie. It's pretty cool to see the veil of calm that falls over the room, knowing that the battle going on just right there in those computers could end the world. Compare this to the equivalent scene in the show though ... https://youtu.be/xlJIaa2ZHA4?si=c2GI6_Ntz_0CVwy_ Which is a five-minute long, fully choreographed and animated fight scene. There's just a lot more going on, and it's funny how the story avoids this kinda tropey virtual fight scene by leaning into a human character's perspective. For all the extra bells and whistles in the show, Chanda doesn't get to drop this epic line though: "These wars are too slow. Ive made up my mind, even if I must burn with the world. Its time for the nukes." I won't spoil it any more than I have. The story is pretty good, but what's missing is actually the main antagonist of the show, Stephen Holstrom, the pioneer who invented the technology to upload human minds to the cloud in the first place. I'm not sure how he'll be handled in the third story, but it seems like a pretty tight time constraint to explain who begot all this violence and why without even having mentioned him in the first two-thirds of the story. I'm excited to see where it goes though. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 522: Jeffries Problem</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/18/day-522-jeffries-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 522: Jeffries Problem"/><published>2025-03-19T01:59:12+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T01:59:12+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/18/day-522-jeffries-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/18/day-522-jeffries-problem/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Slow day today. First time in a while where I just couldn't seem to get anything down. Usually I'll get at least a few hundred words, but there was just nothing coming down the pipe. I'm too distracted.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I'm not sure what to do with 'Jeffries.' All the advice I've gotten from anybody in the industry has been to turn it into a full-length novel and it'll make it way, way more likely to get published. I don't know if I've got it in me to more than double the word count and edit everything over again though. I've been procrastinating a little with the short stories I've been working on while trying to decide, not that they're worthless, but I am running out of time to make this whole thing work. The writer I had a meeting with last week from the writing conference even told me I was really close to publishing 'Jeffries' and he thought the writing quality was there, if only it were a book and not a novella. It's hard to say no to that kind of feedback, and now I'm stuck feeling like anything else I work on right now is a waste of time even though I'm still waiting to hear back from a few agents about it in the current novella state. I feel like I'm stuck between a rock and a hard place. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Not to whine or anything (ok, maybe a little, or a lot), but it feels really weird to regret receiving what normally would be great feedback. Maybe I should have just planned for it to be a novel in the first place. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Slow day today. First time in a while where I just couldn't seem to get anything down. Usually I'll get at least a few hundred words, but there was just nothing coming down the pipe. I'm too distracted. I'm not sure what to do with 'Jeffries.' All the advice I've gotten from anybody in the industry has been to turn it into a full-length novel and it'll make it way, way more likely to get published. I don't know if I've got it in me to more than double the word count and edit everything over again though. I've been procrastinating a little with the short stories I've been working on while trying to decide, not that they're worthless, but I am running out of time to make this whole thing work. The writer I had a meeting with last week from the writing conference even told me I was really close to publishing 'Jeffries' and he thought the writing quality was there, if only it were a book and not a novella. It's hard to say no to that kind of feedback, and now I'm stuck feeling like anything else I work on right now is a waste of time even though I'm still waiting to hear back from a few agents about it in the current novella state. I feel like I'm stuck between a rock and a hard place. Not to whine or anything (ok, maybe a little, or a lot), but it feels really weird to regret receiving what normally would be great feedback. Maybe I should have just planned for it to be a novel in the first place. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>