<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-11T01:16:13+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DangerousDayJob</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Day 516: Writing Battle Results</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 516: Writing Battle Results"/><published>2025-03-11T01:11:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-11T01:11:15+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/10/day-516-writing-battle-results/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>Over the weekend I finally got the results back from the writing battle I joined over a month ago. Long story short, I made top 16! It was my first battle and I'm happy to have gotten so far on a story that I enjoyed working on so much. Now that the competition is over, I decided to make the story public so anybody can read it on the website. <a href="https://www.writingbattle.com/story/debrief/31955646-9785-40c5-841f-00058f81ad10?uploadedStory">If you're interested, check it out right here!</a></p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The feedback I got from the judges was largely positive and I'm happy with what I've got. They brought up a few points where they were a little confused or thrown by my word choice, but there was nothing critically wrong with the story, so I'll take that as a big win. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The whole experience has been the most fun I've had with a writing competition. The format of receiving round by round results and getting feedback from fellow participants makes it so much more engaging than all the other 'fire and forget' competitions I've joined. I hope the Writing Battles site continues to grow and prosper into the future.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="literature"/><category term="short story"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the weekend I finally got the results back from the writing battle I joined over a month ago. Long story short, I made top 16! It was my first battle and I'm happy to have gotten so far on a story that I enjoyed working on so much. Now that the competition is over, I decided to make the story public so anybody can read it on the website. If you're interested, check it out right here! The feedback I got from the judges was largely positive and I'm happy with what I've got. They brought up a few points where they were a little confused or thrown by my word choice, but there was nothing critically wrong with the story, so I'll take that as a big win. The whole experience has been the most fun I've had with a writing competition. The format of receiving round by round results and getting feedback from fellow participants makes it so much more engaging than all the other 'fire and forget' competitions I've joined. I hope the Writing Battles site continues to grow and prosper into the future. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 515: Made it to Finals!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 515: Made it to Finals!"/><published>2025-03-08T02:53:40+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-08T02:53:40+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/07/day-515-made-it-to-finals/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>The Writing Battle competition is entering it's final stretch! They'll be judging finals over the weekend and should be getting us the results on Sunday. I've been so nervous about pitching I hadn't thought about it in a while. Looks like both I and a friend of mine, Rick, made it to finals together! We'll be waiting with baited breath for the results on Sunday. You can track the competition too right here, <a href="https://writingbattle.com/">https://writingbattle.com/</a> or wait for Monday to come around when I'll announce the final results here!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Writing Battle competition is entering it's final stretch! They'll be judging finals over the weekend and should be getting us the results on Sunday. I've been so nervous about pitching I hadn't thought about it in a while. Looks like both I and a friend of mine, Rick, made it to finals together! We'll be waiting with baited breath for the results on Sunday. You can track the competition too right here, https://writingbattle.com/ or wait for Monday to come around when I'll announce the final results here! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 514: Pitch Letter</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 514: Pitch Letter"/><published>2025-03-07T01:55:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-07T01:55:01+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/06/day-514-pitch-letter/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>This coming Sunday I'll be heading to a writer's conference where I'll be pitching my story 'Jeffries' for the first time, and I'm finding the pitch to be some of the most difficult writing I've had to do. Taking the most interesting elements of a fictional story and turning it into a persuasive piece designed to get someone's attention sounds like it would be pretty simple. I imagine most readers like myself have tried to convince friends and family to read our favorite stories, written by other people that is. I even wrote a piece yesterday about how good I think 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is, and I write reviews pretty often, so you'd think I'd be an old hat summing up the most attractive qualities of a novel by now. It <em>has </em>helped a lot in terms of quality, but it sure doesn't make it any easier. The thought of saying my pitch out loud makes me wanna go hide. I have it written at least, so maybe I can keep refining it over the weekend. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That's why I decided to post it today and see if anybody has any suggestions before I head to the writers conference. Any comments would be appreciated! Anyway, here it is:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Dear [Name]:</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>In a grim near-future, both of Jeffry Morgan’s bodies meet every evening to synchronize their memories. Half of Jeffry’s forty-eight waking hours are those of a simple laborer, fulfilling his obligation to society as the law dictates. The other half he spends at his dream job in the most advanced biocomputing lab in the world, researching the technology that enables his split existence: the double-body program.&nbsp;</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>He’s been moving up fast at Wetworks despite his young age, thanks in no small part to his boss and CTO, Tyrell Thompson. Tyrell promised him a leading role in the company, and a raise that may even be large enough to buy his way out of compulsory labor. It’s fantastic news to share, but upon arriving home, he realizes with a shock that he’s lost track of himself. One of his bodies is nowhere to be found.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Jeffry is forced to grapple with the morality of the double-body program after Tyrell pressures him to replace the missing body, even if the existing Jeffry Morgan may still be alive out there somewhere. Meanwhile, his other half attempts to deal with the ruthless abductors who have a mysterious purpose in mind for their stolen bioengineer. He can only hope that his other self will find him before it’s too late.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>‘Jeffries’ (~35,000 words) is a hard sci-fi story set in a dystopian future about Jeffry Morgan’s abduction and his ensuing search for himself. The story appeals to readers of novella-length sci-fi in magazines like ‘The Magazine of Science Fiction and Fantasy,’ or anthologies such as Ken Liu’s ‘The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,’ as well as anyone seeking an introspective tale about the nature of sentience and human rights.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I’ve been writing full-time for two years. I have published poetry in TulipTree Publishing’s ‘Stories that Need to be Told: 2023’ anthology titled ‘Mayflies’ and a short story in ‘The Book of Choices Vol. 1’ anthology from Wolf Grove Media titled ‘Death’s Dilemma.’ I also run a blog where I publish reviews, literary analysis, and personal articles.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for your consideration,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="horror"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="short-stories"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This coming Sunday I'll be heading to a writer's conference where I'll be pitching my story 'Jeffries' for the first time, and I'm finding the pitch to be some of the most difficult writing I've had to do. Taking the most interesting elements of a fictional story and turning it into a persuasive piece designed to get someone's attention sounds like it would be pretty simple. I imagine most readers like myself have tried to convince friends and family to read our favorite stories, written by other people that is. I even wrote a piece yesterday about how good I think 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is, and I write reviews pretty often, so you'd think I'd be an old hat summing up the most attractive qualities of a novel by now. It has helped a lot in terms of quality, but it sure doesn't make it any easier. The thought of saying my pitch out loud makes me wanna go hide. I have it written at least, so maybe I can keep refining it over the weekend. That's why I decided to post it today and see if anybody has any suggestions before I head to the writers conference. Any comments would be appreciated! Anyway, here it is: Dear [Name]: In a grim near-future, both of Jeffry Morgan’s bodies meet every evening to synchronize their memories. Half of Jeffry’s forty-eight waking hours are those of a simple laborer, fulfilling his obligation to society as the law dictates. The other half he spends at his dream job in the most advanced biocomputing lab in the world, researching the technology that enables his split existence: the double-body program.&nbsp; He’s been moving up fast at Wetworks despite his young age, thanks in no small part to his boss and CTO, Tyrell Thompson. Tyrell promised him a leading role in the company, and a raise that may even be large enough to buy his way out of compulsory labor. It’s fantastic news to share, but upon arriving home, he realizes with a shock that he’s lost track of himself. One of his bodies is nowhere to be found. Jeffry is forced to grapple with the morality of the double-body program after Tyrell pressures him to replace the missing body, even if the existing Jeffry Morgan may still be alive out there somewhere. Meanwhile, his other half attempts to deal with the ruthless abductors who have a mysterious purpose in mind for their stolen bioengineer. He can only hope that his other self will find him before it’s too late. ‘Jeffries’ (~35,000 words) is a hard sci-fi story set in a dystopian future about Jeffry Morgan’s abduction and his ensuing search for himself. The story appeals to readers of novella-length sci-fi in magazines like ‘The Magazine of Science Fiction and Fantasy,’ or anthologies such as Ken Liu’s ‘The Hidden Girl and Other Stories,’ as well as anyone seeking an introspective tale about the nature of sentience and human rights. I’ve been writing full-time for two years. I have published poetry in TulipTree Publishing’s ‘Stories that Need to be Told: 2023’ anthology titled ‘Mayflies’ and a short story in ‘The Book of Choices Vol. 1’ anthology from Wolf Grove Media titled ‘Death’s Dilemma.’ I also run a blog where I publish reviews, literary analysis, and personal articles. Thank you for your consideration, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 513: Blood Over Bright Haven</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 513: Blood Over Bright Haven"/><published>2025-03-06T04:45:39+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-06T04:45:39+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/05/day-513-blood-over-bright-haven/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I finished up 'Blood Over Bright Haven' and I'm happy to say the quality of the book remains high for the whole length of the novel, even after that killer first chapter. After Thomil manages to cross over into the city of Tiran, the book diverts from his character for a while to introduce the real protagonist, Sciona Freynan. But who is Thomil you ask? Well, I accidentally called him Beyern in the first impressions post. The first chapter threw like ten names at me so I got confused. Oops. He was the man who ran across the ice field into Tiran, losing his tribe, but saving his niece in the process. His story remains unknown for a while as Sciona develops.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Her story begins with an exam, her final exam in fact. Women in Tiran society don't typically practice magic at the highest level, but Sciona has staked her entire life on her mastery of the field. She's progressed as far as a mage as any woman ever has in Tiran history, but there's still one more hurdle. If she can pass her exam, she'll become one of a hundred Highmages in the entire city, and the first woman to have ever achieved the rank. As women are only allowed to take the exam once every ten years, this is her only chance to prove herself to the all-male court of Archmages who will decide her future. The exam is a really cool introduction to the magic, and Sciona as a character too (one of the most egotistical, obsessive characters I've ever read, but I'll get to that). It's a really cool language-based magic that has developed over three centuries into what is pretty close to a programming language. Using a spellograph, which is like typewriter for spells, mages are able to source energy from a place known as 'the otherworld' and turn that energy into action in the real world. The mysterious otherworld is Sciona's specialty, and she knows how to map it better than anybody else in the whole city. Like any good magic system, there's a dark side. Siphoning energy from 'the forbidden coordinates' will do ... bad things. Nobody is quite sure what since this dark magic was only ever practiced by the evil mage Sabernyn, who used it murder his enemies in cold blood. That won't be a problem for Sciona though. Right? </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Naturally, she passes the exam, but not without some difficulties. Her benefactor, Archmage Bringham, is overjoyed to let her know she's become the first female Highmage in Tiran. He plays an important role in the story as a sort of 'benevolent' patriarch, helping Sciona adjust to the life of a highmage. After inducting her into the society, he puts her first task before her: develop a mapping solution that will allow her to source enough energy from the Otherworld to expand the massive barrier around the city. It's no small project, and the Highmages will be in tense competition to recommend the best solution. She's got her work cut out for her. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Even though she's successfully become the first female Highmage, her fellow Highmages, who are all massive assholes without exception, treat her like garbage. Many of them make sexist remarks about how she rose to such heights against the odds (including the suggestion that she probably has a sexual relationship with her 60-year-old benefactor, disgusting), but the worst among them is Cleon Renthorn. He's pure slime, a trust-fund adult made up of almost nothing but ego, arrogance, and spite. Sciona doesn't even get the satisfaction of being better than him thanks to his immense skill as a mage, making him a real threat. What I find most interesting about Renthorn is how much Sciona has in common with him, a point that's brought up a few times throughout the book. Sciona has a massive ego and a lot of spite in her heart too, due in no small part to the rampant sexism in Tiran culture. She's cold hearted, driven, and powerful, an intimidating combo for someone like the janitor she encounters on her first day as a Highmage. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Renthorn, as the guy in charge of staff, assigns Sciona a Kwen janitor as an assistant instead of an educated mage in an attempt to put her in her place. The janitor turns out to be none other than Thomil, who has survived in the city since his traumatic crossing years ago. I love how he ties back into the story as a result of Renthorn being a huge dick because he ends up being a blessing in disguise for Sciona. He's kind, patient, quiet, listens well, and is surprisingly intelligent. The opposite of Renthorn in every way. Like Thomil, those from the world beyond the barrier are known as Kwen, and are treated as an underclass in Tiran society. Sometimes people refer to them using the slur 'blighters,' which is kinda like if a Nazi referred to a Jewish person as a 'gasser.' It's pretty messed up. They work the hardest, lowest paying jobs in the city, and if they can't work, they're thrown outside the barrier to suffer the same fate as the rest of Thomil's tribe, obliterated by blight. It's a pretty miserable existence all things considered, but things turn around for him after becoming Sciona's assistant. He gets a raise, doesn't have to do as much manual labor, and he gets a free education. Sciona is happy with him despite her prejudices against Kwen, and even finds herself becoming his friend after they get plastered together at the bar. Wins all around. Of course, she'd never fall for him though ... right?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Yeah, there's a romance that plays a big part in the story. I actually didn't see much marketing for it as a romantasy, but I think the romance is such a big part that it probably counts. After reading this book, I've come to think of it as a really good version of what 'The Fourth Wing' was trying to be. It's a lot more creative, the writing is way better, and the characters actually make me care about them, but there remains some undeniable parallels with the strong female lead, feminist themes, prominent romance, and oppressive fantasy world. Another (much better) story it reminds me of is Ursula K. Le Guin's short story 'Those Who Walk Away From Omelas.' Mostly its the themes that coincide, but honestly 'Blood Over Bright Haven' has a lot more time and wiggle room to really nail down the moral ... I'd go so far as to say that I actually prefer this story despite Le Guin being a titan of politically oriented sci-fi. Sorry!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And with that I'm getting into some huge spoilers. Don't read further if you'd like to have this one unspoiled. If you decide not to read on, thanks for reading as far as you have! I hope it's clear by now that the book is a solid recommendation from me.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Right, the themes. There's this intriguing moral dilemma at the heart of the story, shown through the cultural differences between Thomil and Sciona. Thomil asks her at some point if she believes a person with good intentions who does awful things by accident is a better person than someone with bad intentions who accidentally ends up doing good. While Sciona is convinced that good intentions are what matters, especially to her God, Thomil believes the opposite, that the actual effect one has on the world is the only way to judge a person's morality. This burgeoning conflict between them leads right into a crazy twist. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>After months of work and some brilliant deductions, Sciona and Thomil master a mapping algorithm that will let them look into the Otherworld in more detail and full color, something only ancient Kwen mages were capable of. But when Sciona uses this new magic to siphon energy from the Otherworld just as she usually does, Thomil recognizes something horrific. The window they've peered through looks almost identical to his home, a snowy white field where scarce bushes grow. He throws the spellograph off the desk when the siphoning begins, physically ill over what he's seen. Siphoning energy from the bushes on the plain looks identical to the blight that took his family. Combine this with the fact that the forbidden coordinates happen to overlap with the barrier around Tiran, and the terrible truth becomes obvious: that the magic in Tiran is powered by the lives of Kwen living beyond the barrier. The Tirans have been using magic to siphon energy from PEOPLE! Their lives power the trains, the lights, the heaters, everything! Every single one of the thousands of spells Sciona has written over her career has taken the lives of people outside the barrier just like Thomil. She, and everybody else in the city, are unwitting mass murderers.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The twist is probably the best part of the novel because its so obvious in hindsight. The book is paced just well enough that you might not catch on until it hits, even though it's pretty clear that <em>something </em>isn't right. I mean, it can't all be rosy with what happened in that explosive first chapter, right?</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The conflict between Thomil and Sciona ramps up because she's unable to accept the truth and says some pretty racist things to him about her God being the only objective Truth, with the implication that it was only just that his tribe died for Tiran's magic. Part of this is that her ego won't allow her to sacrifice something as important to her as magic, not even for Thomil. He turns his back and spends some time with his niece for a while, the one he saved in the first chapter. His niece is an interesting side character, but doesn't contribute too much to the plot. I'm pushing my word count as is, but suffice to say she hates Sciona for good reason but comes around as they grow together. Thomil has felt guilty for raising her as a member of his tribe rather than a Tiranish woman who might have an easier life, but Sciona helps him overcome his guilt by convincing him that his people are worth carrying on for even if it's hard.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>That comes long after some well-warranted depressive soul searching though, (the only part of the novel that did drag a little for me). Sciona realizes how right Thomil is and decides to do something about it. Despite Sciona's best efforts though, she's unable to convince any of the other mages to stop using magic (most of whom already knew what they were doing to people anyway). Even her mentor Archmage Bringham has accepted 'God's Truth' that the Kwen are inherently lesser, made to be harvested for the glory of Tiran. Renthorn is the worst of them though. He not only knows about the sacrifices, but tries to convince Sciona to show him her mapping solution so he can <em>get off on watching his spells turn people into pulp</em>. Thomil decks the hell out of him when he tries to get handsy with Sciona right after she refuses him, which is probably Thomil's best single moment. Sciona and Thomil make up (and the romance comes full swing), just in time to decide the only recourse is good old-fashioned violence. Meanwhile, the highmages are thinking about expanding the coordinate system so they can harvest people's bioenergy from other continents too, so they definitely have it coming. Sciona uses her new spell to show the whole city the truth, a race war ensues, Bringham reveals his even darker colors, and Renthorn gets a large object dropped on his head. Then Sciona nobly sacrifices herself to wipe out all the high mages by siphoning from the forbidden coordinates in the very spot that she first passed her exam. A fitting end if you ask me. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>To sum up, I really enjoyed this novel. Author M. L. Wang made some decisions that could easily have turned the book sour that actually end up making it as good as it is. For one thing, Sciona is not a likeable character. Other than the goodness Thomil brings to her life, she's kind of a deranged egotist psycho. I'm sure if she hadn't met him she would have ended up accepting the deaths of the Kwen as a necessary sacrifice to fuel her power. This is a weird choice because even three fourths of the way through the novel, she's still doing really unlikeable, unrelatable things to people. What the book gains from this though is an unparalleled opportunity for Sciona to grow and change. She starts out almost inhumanly driven to her singular purpose of becoming a Highmage, but eventually grows a heart and learns to care about the people around her. Thomil also gets a little growth by the end, but he was certainly a more static character. Someone with a soul to judge Sciona against to see how far she's come. I think his story has a really traumatic ending to the point where I almost wish he would have gone out with Sciona. It comes full circle really well too though with how he lives on for his tribe and his niece. I'm torn on Thomil. Sciona on the other hand is extremely capable and powerful, and supremely interesting to follow, even if I'd probably never call her a friend.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I can't call it a heartwarming tale, but it does make you feel like even the worst of the worst can learn to be better. And that's really saying something from a book where almost every character is a mass-murderer who looks down on women and thinks other races are little more than fuel for their God-given gift of magic. I'd love to read some of her other stories in the future. I hope they're just as delightfully grim as 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="review"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I finished up 'Blood Over Bright Haven' and I'm happy to say the quality of the book remains high for the whole length of the novel, even after that killer first chapter. After Thomil manages to cross over into the city of Tiran, the book diverts from his character for a while to introduce the real protagonist, Sciona Freynan. But who is Thomil you ask? Well, I accidentally called him Beyern in the first impressions post. The first chapter threw like ten names at me so I got confused. Oops. He was the man who ran across the ice field into Tiran, losing his tribe, but saving his niece in the process. His story remains unknown for a while as Sciona develops. Her story begins with an exam, her final exam in fact. Women in Tiran society don't typically practice magic at the highest level, but Sciona has staked her entire life on her mastery of the field. She's progressed as far as a mage as any woman ever has in Tiran history, but there's still one more hurdle. If she can pass her exam, she'll become one of a hundred Highmages in the entire city, and the first woman to have ever achieved the rank. As women are only allowed to take the exam once every ten years, this is her only chance to prove herself to the all-male court of Archmages who will decide her future. The exam is a really cool introduction to the magic, and Sciona as a character too (one of the most egotistical, obsessive characters I've ever read, but I'll get to that). It's a really cool language-based magic that has developed over three centuries into what is pretty close to a programming language. Using a spellograph, which is like typewriter for spells, mages are able to source energy from a place known as 'the otherworld' and turn that energy into action in the real world. The mysterious otherworld is Sciona's specialty, and she knows how to map it better than anybody else in the whole city. Like any good magic system, there's a dark side. Siphoning energy from 'the forbidden coordinates' will do ... bad things. Nobody is quite sure what since this dark magic was only ever practiced by the evil mage Sabernyn, who used it murder his enemies in cold blood. That won't be a problem for Sciona though. Right? Naturally, she passes the exam, but not without some difficulties. Her benefactor, Archmage Bringham, is overjoyed to let her know she's become the first female Highmage in Tiran. He plays an important role in the story as a sort of 'benevolent' patriarch, helping Sciona adjust to the life of a highmage. After inducting her into the society, he puts her first task before her: develop a mapping solution that will allow her to source enough energy from the Otherworld to expand the massive barrier around the city. It's no small project, and the Highmages will be in tense competition to recommend the best solution. She's got her work cut out for her. Even though she's successfully become the first female Highmage, her fellow Highmages, who are all massive assholes without exception, treat her like garbage. Many of them make sexist remarks about how she rose to such heights against the odds (including the suggestion that she probably has a sexual relationship with her 60-year-old benefactor, disgusting), but the worst among them is Cleon Renthorn. He's pure slime, a trust-fund adult made up of almost nothing but ego, arrogance, and spite. Sciona doesn't even get the satisfaction of being better than him thanks to his immense skill as a mage, making him a real threat. What I find most interesting about Renthorn is how much Sciona has in common with him, a point that's brought up a few times throughout the book. Sciona has a massive ego and a lot of spite in her heart too, due in no small part to the rampant sexism in Tiran culture. She's cold hearted, driven, and powerful, an intimidating combo for someone like the janitor she encounters on her first day as a Highmage. Renthorn, as the guy in charge of staff, assigns Sciona a Kwen janitor as an assistant instead of an educated mage in an attempt to put her in her place. The janitor turns out to be none other than Thomil, who has survived in the city since his traumatic crossing years ago. I love how he ties back into the story as a result of Renthorn being a huge dick because he ends up being a blessing in disguise for Sciona. He's kind, patient, quiet, listens well, and is surprisingly intelligent. The opposite of Renthorn in every way. Like Thomil, those from the world beyond the barrier are known as Kwen, and are treated as an underclass in Tiran society. Sometimes people refer to them using the slur 'blighters,' which is kinda like if a Nazi referred to a Jewish person as a 'gasser.' It's pretty messed up. They work the hardest, lowest paying jobs in the city, and if they can't work, they're thrown outside the barrier to suffer the same fate as the rest of Thomil's tribe, obliterated by blight. It's a pretty miserable existence all things considered, but things turn around for him after becoming Sciona's assistant. He gets a raise, doesn't have to do as much manual labor, and he gets a free education. Sciona is happy with him despite her prejudices against Kwen, and even finds herself becoming his friend after they get plastered together at the bar. Wins all around. Of course, she'd never fall for him though ... right? Yeah, there's a romance that plays a big part in the story. I actually didn't see much marketing for it as a romantasy, but I think the romance is such a big part that it probably counts. After reading this book, I've come to think of it as a really good version of what 'The Fourth Wing' was trying to be. It's a lot more creative, the writing is way better, and the characters actually make me care about them, but there remains some undeniable parallels with the strong female lead, feminist themes, prominent romance, and oppressive fantasy world. Another (much better) story it reminds me of is Ursula K. Le Guin's short story 'Those Who Walk Away From Omelas.' Mostly its the themes that coincide, but honestly 'Blood Over Bright Haven' has a lot more time and wiggle room to really nail down the moral ... I'd go so far as to say that I actually prefer this story despite Le Guin being a titan of politically oriented sci-fi. Sorry! And with that I'm getting into some huge spoilers. Don't read further if you'd like to have this one unspoiled. If you decide not to read on, thanks for reading as far as you have! I hope it's clear by now that the book is a solid recommendation from me. Right, the themes. There's this intriguing moral dilemma at the heart of the story, shown through the cultural differences between Thomil and Sciona. Thomil asks her at some point if she believes a person with good intentions who does awful things by accident is a better person than someone with bad intentions who accidentally ends up doing good. While Sciona is convinced that good intentions are what matters, especially to her God, Thomil believes the opposite, that the actual effect one has on the world is the only way to judge a person's morality. This burgeoning conflict between them leads right into a crazy twist. After months of work and some brilliant deductions, Sciona and Thomil master a mapping algorithm that will let them look into the Otherworld in more detail and full color, something only ancient Kwen mages were capable of. But when Sciona uses this new magic to siphon energy from the Otherworld just as she usually does, Thomil recognizes something horrific. The window they've peered through looks almost identical to his home, a snowy white field where scarce bushes grow. He throws the spellograph off the desk when the siphoning begins, physically ill over what he's seen. Siphoning energy from the bushes on the plain looks identical to the blight that took his family. Combine this with the fact that the forbidden coordinates happen to overlap with the barrier around Tiran, and the terrible truth becomes obvious: that the magic in Tiran is powered by the lives of Kwen living beyond the barrier. The Tirans have been using magic to siphon energy from PEOPLE! Their lives power the trains, the lights, the heaters, everything! Every single one of the thousands of spells Sciona has written over her career has taken the lives of people outside the barrier just like Thomil. She, and everybody else in the city, are unwitting mass murderers. The twist is probably the best part of the novel because its so obvious in hindsight. The book is paced just well enough that you might not catch on until it hits, even though it's pretty clear that something isn't right. I mean, it can't all be rosy with what happened in that explosive first chapter, right? The conflict between Thomil and Sciona ramps up because she's unable to accept the truth and says some pretty racist things to him about her God being the only objective Truth, with the implication that it was only just that his tribe died for Tiran's magic. Part of this is that her ego won't allow her to sacrifice something as important to her as magic, not even for Thomil. He turns his back and spends some time with his niece for a while, the one he saved in the first chapter. His niece is an interesting side character, but doesn't contribute too much to the plot. I'm pushing my word count as is, but suffice to say she hates Sciona for good reason but comes around as they grow together. Thomil has felt guilty for raising her as a member of his tribe rather than a Tiranish woman who might have an easier life, but Sciona helps him overcome his guilt by convincing him that his people are worth carrying on for even if it's hard. That comes long after some well-warranted depressive soul searching though, (the only part of the novel that did drag a little for me). Sciona realizes how right Thomil is and decides to do something about it. Despite Sciona's best efforts though, she's unable to convince any of the other mages to stop using magic (most of whom already knew what they were doing to people anyway). Even her mentor Archmage Bringham has accepted 'God's Truth' that the Kwen are inherently lesser, made to be harvested for the glory of Tiran. Renthorn is the worst of them though. He not only knows about the sacrifices, but tries to convince Sciona to show him her mapping solution so he can get off on watching his spells turn people into pulp. Thomil decks the hell out of him when he tries to get handsy with Sciona right after she refuses him, which is probably Thomil's best single moment. Sciona and Thomil make up (and the romance comes full swing), just in time to decide the only recourse is good old-fashioned violence. Meanwhile, the highmages are thinking about expanding the coordinate system so they can harvest people's bioenergy from other continents too, so they definitely have it coming. Sciona uses her new spell to show the whole city the truth, a race war ensues, Bringham reveals his even darker colors, and Renthorn gets a large object dropped on his head. Then Sciona nobly sacrifices herself to wipe out all the high mages by siphoning from the forbidden coordinates in the very spot that she first passed her exam. A fitting end if you ask me. To sum up, I really enjoyed this novel. Author M. L. Wang made some decisions that could easily have turned the book sour that actually end up making it as good as it is. For one thing, Sciona is not a likeable character. Other than the goodness Thomil brings to her life, she's kind of a deranged egotist psycho. I'm sure if she hadn't met him she would have ended up accepting the deaths of the Kwen as a necessary sacrifice to fuel her power. This is a weird choice because even three fourths of the way through the novel, she's still doing really unlikeable, unrelatable things to people. What the book gains from this though is an unparalleled opportunity for Sciona to grow and change. She starts out almost inhumanly driven to her singular purpose of becoming a Highmage, but eventually grows a heart and learns to care about the people around her. Thomil also gets a little growth by the end, but he was certainly a more static character. Someone with a soul to judge Sciona against to see how far she's come. I think his story has a really traumatic ending to the point where I almost wish he would have gone out with Sciona. It comes full circle really well too though with how he lives on for his tribe and his niece. I'm torn on Thomil. Sciona on the other hand is extremely capable and powerful, and supremely interesting to follow, even if I'd probably never call her a friend. I can't call it a heartwarming tale, but it does make you feel like even the worst of the worst can learn to be better. And that's really saying something from a book where almost every character is a mass-murderer who looks down on women and thinks other races are little more than fuel for their God-given gift of magic. I'd love to read some of her other stories in the future. I hope they're just as delightfully grim as 'Blood Over Bright Haven' is. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 512: The Hidden Girl and Other Stories</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 512: The Hidden Girl and Other Stories"/><published>2025-03-05T02:45:43+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T02:45:43+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/04/day-512-the-hidden-girl-and-other-stories/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I'm already adding to the book haul. I think I have literature problem. Actually I've been meaning to get this book for a long time and it slipped my mind when I bought this round, so I always meant to include it! It's not an extra book so much as it is a misplaced book. Or so I tell myself.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>It's called 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' by Ken Liu. Fitting with this haul's theme, it's a sci-fi anthology with <em>seventeen </em>stories! I'm most excited to read 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series. I've never seen a trilogy of short stories before, so I'm excited to see how the structure works. I never considered writing multiple short stories in series because I just figured you would write a novel instead if you wanted to do that. A while back I watched an animated adaptation of this trilogy, a show called 'Pantheon' that I've reviewed before, but I've read that the stories themselves are very different from the show. If they're half as entertaining, I'll be happy with my purchase. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I went ahead and read the first story 'Ghost Days' (though I'm still working on 'Blood Over Bright Haven') and what I found most striking was (again) the structure. It starts in the future and traces the path of an old bronze antique deep into the past and all the way back again through a series of vignettes that feature the object. I can't help but wonder if this story was originally based on some kind of prompt or exercise because of how uniquely organized it is. The prose is here and there and I think some of the dialogue can be a little clunky, but the story itself is so interesting that it doesn't make much of a difference. I'm hoping they only get better as I continue.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading, </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm already adding to the book haul. I think I have literature problem. Actually I've been meaning to get this book for a long time and it slipped my mind when I bought this round, so I always meant to include it! It's not an extra book so much as it is a misplaced book. Or so I tell myself. It's called 'The Hidden Girl and Other Stories' by Ken Liu. Fitting with this haul's theme, it's a sci-fi anthology with seventeen stories! I'm most excited to read 'The Gods Will Not Be Chained' series. I've never seen a trilogy of short stories before, so I'm excited to see how the structure works. I never considered writing multiple short stories in series because I just figured you would write a novel instead if you wanted to do that. A while back I watched an animated adaptation of this trilogy, a show called 'Pantheon' that I've reviewed before, but I've read that the stories themselves are very different from the show. If they're half as entertaining, I'll be happy with my purchase. I went ahead and read the first story 'Ghost Days' (though I'm still working on 'Blood Over Bright Haven') and what I found most striking was (again) the structure. It starts in the future and traces the path of an old bronze antique deep into the past and all the way back again through a series of vignettes that feature the object. I can't help but wonder if this story was originally based on some kind of prompt or exercise because of how uniquely organized it is. The prose is here and there and I think some of the dialogue can be a little clunky, but the story itself is so interesting that it doesn't make much of a difference. I'm hoping they only get better as I continue. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 511: Blood Over Bright Haven First Impressions</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 511: Blood Over Bright Haven First Impressions"/><published>2025-03-04T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-04T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/03/03/day-511-blood-over-bright-haven-first-impressions/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I started reading 'Blood Over Bright Haven' by M. L. Wang over the weekend and was completely blown away. I think the first chapter of this novel is the best I've ever read. It somehow established massive stakes, multiple great characters, an immediate call to action, and an interesting fantasy world to boot. It's easily the most action-packed first chapter I've ever read too, and the emotional investment it got out of me within ten pages is more than some whole novels. Seriously, I can't understate how incredible the intro is. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story begins with a dying tribe making their last ditch attempt to reach to safety. It reads a bit more like a prologue than a true chapter one with how it plays out, but I'm more than forgiving it for that nitpick. I won't be able to get across the depth of emotion the perspective character, Beyern, goes through in trying to save his family, but I can tell you that I've never gotten as upset over a first chapter before. Their tribe, who live in an unforgiving tundra plagued by something known as blight, once numbered in the tens of thousands. Now there are but forty left, the only ones not killed by blight and starvation. Their salvation awaits under the magic dome of the city of Tiran, which keeps out the blight and creates an area of warm weather, but to get there, they'll have to cross over a frozen lake. Its not the thin ice or the freezing temperatures that Beyern feels so threatened by though. Blight is waiting beneath the ice, and begins to take his fellows one at a time as soon as the two-mile crossing starts. Streamers of light erupt from the ice to pierce the skin, and just a touch is enough to kill, unravelling their bodies like packaged meat. Will Beyern make it across the lake in time with his sister and niece? And even if they do make it, will they be able to carry on the tribe's legacy into the future?! Read to find out!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Okay, I don't want to spoil it too badly, but I think you can probably guess what happens. Wang is able to establish the kind of stakes I dream of with this horrific crossing by making it about more than just a character. She highlights many of the tribe's long-held traditions as Beyern watches his fellows die horribly to blight. It's not just his people he's losing, but his whole society, a once-great nation reduced to puddles of blood behind him as he sprints to safety with his niece in his arms. Their children are all that stand between them and extinction now. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Pushing the stakes hard, all the way up to a societal level is difficult to execute in normal circumstances, but Wang was able to do it smoothly within only ten pages or so. It's so easy to slip into meaningless statistics, but these people were not just names or numbers. They felt like well-developed characters. The skills, traditions, and memories they carry are all summed up in relation to Beyern in just a sentence or three, but every single one who goes down hurts. It was also a sneaky way to inject a huge amount of world building into a small, tension-fraught package, which I can't help but be a little jealous of too. The gut-punch at the end just as they reach safety ties the chapter up nicely, and flows right into the next chapter. It's so good it's hard to wrap my head around. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I can't wait to read the rest of this. It slows down a lot in the second chapter, but the stakes are still relatively high and I'm once again immediately invested in the new characters that show up. I'm certain this book will be a great read.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="book-reviews"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I started reading 'Blood Over Bright Haven' by M. L. Wang over the weekend and was completely blown away. I think the first chapter of this novel is the best I've ever read. It somehow established massive stakes, multiple great characters, an immediate call to action, and an interesting fantasy world to boot. It's easily the most action-packed first chapter I've ever read too, and the emotional investment it got out of me within ten pages is more than some whole novels. Seriously, I can't understate how incredible the intro is. The story begins with a dying tribe making their last ditch attempt to reach to safety. It reads a bit more like a prologue than a true chapter one with how it plays out, but I'm more than forgiving it for that nitpick. I won't be able to get across the depth of emotion the perspective character, Beyern, goes through in trying to save his family, but I can tell you that I've never gotten as upset over a first chapter before. Their tribe, who live in an unforgiving tundra plagued by something known as blight, once numbered in the tens of thousands. Now there are but forty left, the only ones not killed by blight and starvation. Their salvation awaits under the magic dome of the city of Tiran, which keeps out the blight and creates an area of warm weather, but to get there, they'll have to cross over a frozen lake. Its not the thin ice or the freezing temperatures that Beyern feels so threatened by though. Blight is waiting beneath the ice, and begins to take his fellows one at a time as soon as the two-mile crossing starts. Streamers of light erupt from the ice to pierce the skin, and just a touch is enough to kill, unravelling their bodies like packaged meat. Will Beyern make it across the lake in time with his sister and niece? And even if they do make it, will they be able to carry on the tribe's legacy into the future?! Read to find out! Okay, I don't want to spoil it too badly, but I think you can probably guess what happens. Wang is able to establish the kind of stakes I dream of with this horrific crossing by making it about more than just a character. She highlights many of the tribe's long-held traditions as Beyern watches his fellows die horribly to blight. It's not just his people he's losing, but his whole society, a once-great nation reduced to puddles of blood behind him as he sprints to safety with his niece in his arms. Their children are all that stand between them and extinction now. Pushing the stakes hard, all the way up to a societal level is difficult to execute in normal circumstances, but Wang was able to do it smoothly within only ten pages or so. It's so easy to slip into meaningless statistics, but these people were not just names or numbers. They felt like well-developed characters. The skills, traditions, and memories they carry are all summed up in relation to Beyern in just a sentence or three, but every single one who goes down hurts. It was also a sneaky way to inject a huge amount of world building into a small, tension-fraught package, which I can't help but be a little jealous of too. The gut-punch at the end just as they reach safety ties the chapter up nicely, and flows right into the next chapter. It's so good it's hard to wrap my head around. I can't wait to read the rest of this. It slows down a lot in the second chapter, but the stakes are still relatively high and I'm once again immediately invested in the new characters that show up. I'm certain this book will be a great read. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 510: Book Haul!</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 510: Book Haul!"/><published>2025-03-01T02:13:51+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T02:13:51+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/28/day-510-book-haul/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It's been a long time coming, but I'm finally buying some more books. Despite my belated book haul, it's not like I've been wanting for something to read. Quite the contrary! I've been involved in multiple peer-judged competitions, and I've been doing some beta reading for friends. Also, the last thing I read was the Green Bone Saga and I needed to recover after that one. Anyway, here's what's next on my menu!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>This time I wanted to focus on more contemporary sci-fi and fantasy. That's why first up is a novel published in 2023 by M. L. Wang called 'Blood Over Bright Haven.' Its a fantasy novel about the first woman ever admitted to a prestigious order of mages. She unravels a secret conspiracy that could change the practice of magic forever. I totally stole that phrasing from Google by the way. It sounds pretty fun, I'm imagining dark Harry Potter at the moment, but we'll see how it goes after I get into it. I heard about it at my writing group. In fact, I think every book on this list was a recommendation from someone or another. I've got a lot of catching up to do on recommendations I guess ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>No time like today to get started, and that's with a book that someone recommended me so long ago that I bought it as a Christmas gift. I'm looking forward to reading it, it's 'Red Rising,' by Pierce Brown, a dystopian novel that centers around the conflict generated by an oppressive caste system. I remember eating 'The Hunger Games' up as a kid, so I'm sure I'll enjoy this one. There's something about a good underdog story set in an abysmally tragic world that always works.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Well, I hope so anyway, because this next novel is pretty similar actually. Another dystopian novel about a utopian island where everything is not as it seems. And yes, I did steal that phrasing from Google too. 'The Ferryman,' by Justin Cronin is one of the more mysterious books I've come across. Not even the internet will spoil it for me, much less my friends, which means that the concept is either amazing, or just really, really complicated. Hopefully the former.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And finally, 'Pushing Ice,' by Alastair Reynolds. I've read Reynolds before, specifically his Revelation Space trilogy, and this is anything like that, I know I'm bound to be blown away. The sci-fi concepts he's able to come up with are like nothing else I've ever read, and he seems to have an unlimited number of incredible ideas for future technology, alien (and not-so-alien) civilization, and unusual characters to fit into these strange new worlds. I'm excited to read this one, which is why I've left it for last! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>And as always, I'll probably add a book to these somewhere along the line. Expect many reviews in the next few weeks! </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="book-review"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="literature"/><category term="reading"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a long time coming, but I'm finally buying some more books. Despite my belated book haul, it's not like I've been wanting for something to read. Quite the contrary! I've been involved in multiple peer-judged competitions, and I've been doing some beta reading for friends. Also, the last thing I read was the Green Bone Saga and I needed to recover after that one. Anyway, here's what's next on my menu! This time I wanted to focus on more contemporary sci-fi and fantasy. That's why first up is a novel published in 2023 by M. L. Wang called 'Blood Over Bright Haven.' Its a fantasy novel about the first woman ever admitted to a prestigious order of mages. She unravels a secret conspiracy that could change the practice of magic forever. I totally stole that phrasing from Google by the way. It sounds pretty fun, I'm imagining dark Harry Potter at the moment, but we'll see how it goes after I get into it. I heard about it at my writing group. In fact, I think every book on this list was a recommendation from someone or another. I've got a lot of catching up to do on recommendations I guess ... No time like today to get started, and that's with a book that someone recommended me so long ago that I bought it as a Christmas gift. I'm looking forward to reading it, it's 'Red Rising,' by Pierce Brown, a dystopian novel that centers around the conflict generated by an oppressive caste system. I remember eating 'The Hunger Games' up as a kid, so I'm sure I'll enjoy this one. There's something about a good underdog story set in an abysmally tragic world that always works. Well, I hope so anyway, because this next novel is pretty similar actually. Another dystopian novel about a utopian island where everything is not as it seems. And yes, I did steal that phrasing from Google too. 'The Ferryman,' by Justin Cronin is one of the more mysterious books I've come across. Not even the internet will spoil it for me, much less my friends, which means that the concept is either amazing, or just really, really complicated. Hopefully the former. And finally, 'Pushing Ice,' by Alastair Reynolds. I've read Reynolds before, specifically his Revelation Space trilogy, and this is anything like that, I know I'm bound to be blown away. The sci-fi concepts he's able to come up with are like nothing else I've ever read, and he seems to have an unlimited number of incredible ideas for future technology, alien (and not-so-alien) civilization, and unusual characters to fit into these strange new worlds. I'm excited to read this one, which is why I've left it for last! And as always, I'll probably add a book to these somewhere along the line. Expect many reviews in the next few weeks! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 509: Shadow</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 509: Shadow"/><published>2025-02-28T02:52:19+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-28T02:52:19+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/27/day-509-shadow/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>There's this Chinese movie I go back and watch again every once in a while called 'Shadow' that always hits just right. It's got a little bit of everything, being part period film, part fantasy, part espionage thriller, and probably like three part Kung Fu movie on top off all that. It's got some really artistic and creative action sequences, and some great effects too, but where I think it really shines is the twisty plot and excellent character building. I find a little something new in every rewatch, putting it in that rare category of movies I'm not sure I'll ever stop seeing again. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The story begins years ago, in the aftermath of the kingdom of Pei's losing war against the kingdom of Yang. The important city of Jingzhou was lost after their genius Commander Ziyu was mortally wounded in combat by Yang Cang, and in the time since, Ziyu has been planning his revenge from deep within a secret chamber of the royal palace. To that end, he directs his shadow, a body double, to challenge Yang Cang to single combat. This angers the crafty, but young and undisciplined King, who demands that Ziyu's double play a duet with the Commader's wife for him in recompense. His refusal to do so sets the plot in motion as the King begins to suspect that Ziyu's body double is not the real Commander ...</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>There's a lot going on even from the very beginning, and the plot never stops getting thicker. There's some question as to whether the Commander's wife will far for his double, and the King's sister becomes a pawn in his plans, and the Yangs have their own role to play in all of this. Oh and the coolest part of the whole movie are the razor blade umbrellas that the protagonist learns to wield in order to defeat Yang. I mean just look at these things.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>The acting and the insane action and crazy twists do get a little ridiculous at times, but they never over stay their welcome so much that it's not still cool. Like here, the secret army that the Commader builds up uses a bunch of umbrellas stacked atop one another to slide down the main street of Jingzhou firing wrist-mounted crossbows to take out all the town guards. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Is it kinda silly? Yes. Is it incredibly epic at the same time? Also yes.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>I really can't get enough of this movie and think everybody should give it a watch. Let me know if you've ever seen this movie in the comments and if you liked it as much as I did!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="fantasy"/><category term="film"/><category term="horror"/><category term="literature"/><category term="movies"/><category term="review"/><category term="reviews"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There's this Chinese movie I go back and watch again every once in a while called 'Shadow' that always hits just right. It's got a little bit of everything, being part period film, part fantasy, part espionage thriller, and probably like three part Kung Fu movie on top off all that. It's got some really artistic and creative action sequences, and some great effects too, but where I think it really shines is the twisty plot and excellent character building. I find a little something new in every rewatch, putting it in that rare category of movies I'm not sure I'll ever stop seeing again. The story begins years ago, in the aftermath of the kingdom of Pei's losing war against the kingdom of Yang. The important city of Jingzhou was lost after their genius Commander Ziyu was mortally wounded in combat by Yang Cang, and in the time since, Ziyu has been planning his revenge from deep within a secret chamber of the royal palace. To that end, he directs his shadow, a body double, to challenge Yang Cang to single combat. This angers the crafty, but young and undisciplined King, who demands that Ziyu's double play a duet with the Commader's wife for him in recompense. His refusal to do so sets the plot in motion as the King begins to suspect that Ziyu's body double is not the real Commander ... There's a lot going on even from the very beginning, and the plot never stops getting thicker. There's some question as to whether the Commander's wife will far for his double, and the King's sister becomes a pawn in his plans, and the Yangs have their own role to play in all of this. Oh and the coolest part of the whole movie are the razor blade umbrellas that the protagonist learns to wield in order to defeat Yang. I mean just look at these things. The acting and the insane action and crazy twists do get a little ridiculous at times, but they never over stay their welcome so much that it's not still cool. Like here, the secret army that the Commader builds up uses a bunch of umbrellas stacked atop one another to slide down the main street of Jingzhou firing wrist-mounted crossbows to take out all the town guards. Is it kinda silly? Yes. Is it incredibly epic at the same time? Also yes. I really can't get enough of this movie and think everybody should give it a watch. Let me know if you've ever seen this movie in the comments and if you liked it as much as I did! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 508: Update on Jeffries</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 508: Update on Jeffries"/><published>2025-02-27T03:27:38+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T03:27:38+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/26/day-508-update-on-jeffries/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>I know it's been a long time coming, but I think I'm finally, finally getting to the end of editing 'Jeffries.' I did a read through today and didn't feel the need to change much, which is a nice feeling. There's one more scene I want to work in. I know I keep saying that. But this time it really is the last one. The previous last scene ended up spiraling into three separate scenes, but that's always how it is. I'm very close to done. It's not perfect, but the only way to make it any better would be to gut the entire ending and start over, and honestly? If I don't do this at some point it will never be finished. I'm gonna finish this last scene, do one more editing pass, and then call it quits on 'Jeffries.' After that, I'll seek to get it published as is. If it's not good enough for trad publishing in a magazine or on it's own, I'll just publish it myself as a standalone on Amazon.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Then all I have to do is decide what to write next!</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="sci fi"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I know it's been a long time coming, but I think I'm finally, finally getting to the end of editing 'Jeffries.' I did a read through today and didn't feel the need to change much, which is a nice feeling. There's one more scene I want to work in. I know I keep saying that. But this time it really is the last one. The previous last scene ended up spiraling into three separate scenes, but that's always how it is. I'm very close to done. It's not perfect, but the only way to make it any better would be to gut the entire ending and start over, and honestly? If I don't do this at some point it will never be finished. I'm gonna finish this last scene, do one more editing pass, and then call it quits on 'Jeffries.' After that, I'll seek to get it published as is. If it's not good enough for trad publishing in a magazine or on it's own, I'll just publish it myself as a standalone on Amazon. Then all I have to do is decide what to write next! Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 507: Goodbye Finn</title><link href="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 507: Goodbye Finn"/><published>2025-02-26T00:53:54+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-26T00:53:54+00:00</updated><id>https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hawleybenjamin1.github.io/2025/02/25/day-507-goodbye-finn/"><![CDATA[<p></p> <p>It was a sad day today. I drove over to see my grandparents and help bury their cat, Finn. They got him back in 2012 along with two other cats, Jack and Jill, who have been a fixture in their house ever since. Finn was laid to rest right alongside the other family pets buried on the property in good company. I'm sure he will be sorely missed. </p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Here's a favorite of my grandfather's, a picture he took of Finn with his brother Jack in the background, looking as if he has two heads.</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Thank you for reading,</p> <p></p> <p></p> <p>Benjamin Hawley</p> <p></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;login&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com&quot;, &quot;display_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;bhawleywrites&quot;, &quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>hawleybenjamin1@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Daily"/><category term="author"/><category term="authors"/><category term="blog"/><category term="books"/><category term="dangerousdayjob"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It was a sad day today. I drove over to see my grandparents and help bury their cat, Finn. They got him back in 2012 along with two other cats, Jack and Jill, who have been a fixture in their house ever since. Finn was laid to rest right alongside the other family pets buried on the property in good company. I'm sure he will be sorely missed. Here's a favorite of my grandfather's, a picture he took of Finn with his brother Jack in the background, looking as if he has two heads. Thank you for reading, Benjamin Hawley]]></summary></entry></feed>